Genesis  4 : 1 - 26

4 Now Adam had sexual relations with his wife Eve, and she became pregnant. When she gave birth to Cain, she said: “I have produced[*] a male child with the help of Jehovah.” 2 Later she again gave birth, to his brother Abel.

Abel became a shepherd of the flock, but Cain became a cultivator of the ground. 3 After some time, Cain brought some fruits of the land as an offering to Jehovah. 4 But Abel brought some firstlings of his flock, including their fat. While Jehovah looked with favor on Abel and on his offering, 5 he did not look with any favor on Cain and on his offering. So Cain grew hot with anger and was dejected.[*] 6 Then Jehovah said to Cain: “Why are you so angry and dejected? 7 If you turn to doing good, will you not be restored to favor?[*] But if you do not turn to doing good, sin is crouching at the door, and its craving is to dominate you; but will you get the mastery over it?”

8 After that Cain said to his brother Abel: “Let us go over into the field.” So while they were in the field, Cain assaulted his brother Abel and killed him. 9 Later on, Jehovah said to Cain: “Where is your brother Abel?” and he said: “I do not know. Am I my brother’s guardian?” 10 At this He said: “What have you done? Listen! Your brother’s blood is crying out to me from the ground. 11 And now you are cursed in banishment from the ground that has opened its mouth to receive your brother’s blood from your hand. 12 When you cultivate the ground, it will not give you back its produce.[*] You will become a wanderer and a fugitive in the earth.” 13 At this Cain said to Jehovah: “The punishment for my error is too great to bear. 14 Today you are driving me from the land,[*] and I will be hidden from your face; and I will become a wanderer and a fugitive on the earth, and anyone who finds me will certainly kill me.” 15 So Jehovah said to him: “For that reason, anyone who kills Cain will suffer vengeance seven times.”

So Jehovah set up[*] a sign for Cain in order that no one finding him would strike him. 16 Then Cain went away from before Jehovah and took up residence in the land of Exile,[*] to the east of E′den.

17 Afterward Cain had sexual relations with his wife, and she became pregnant and gave birth to E′noch. Then he engaged in building a city and named the city after his son E′noch. 18 Later I′rad was born to E′noch. And I′rad became father to Me·hu′ja·el, and Me·hu′ja·el became father to Me·thu′sha·el, and Me·thu′sha·el became father to La′mech.

19 La′mech took two wives for himself. The name of the first was A′dah, and the name of the second was Zil′lah. 20 A′dah gave birth to Ja′bal. He was the founder of those who dwell in tents and have livestock. 21 His brother’s name was Ju′bal. He was the founder of all those who play the harp and the pipe.[*] 22 Also, Zil′lah gave birth to Tu′bal-cain, who forged every sort of tool of copper and iron. And the sister of Tu′bal-cain was Na′a·mah. 23 Then La′mech composed these words for his wives A′dah and Zil′lah:

“Hear my voice, you wives of La′mech;

Give ear to my saying:

A man I have killed for wounding me,

Yes, a young man for striking me.

24 If 7 times Cain is to be avenged,

Then La′mech 77 times.”

25 Adam again had sexual relations with his wife, and she gave birth to a son. She named him Seth[*] because, as she said, “God has appointed for me another offspring[*] in place of Abel, because Cain killed him.” 26 There was also born to Seth a son, and he named him E′nosh. At that time people began calling on the name of Jehovah.

^ Gen. 4:1 Or “given birth to.”

^ Gen. 4:5 Lit., “and his face fell.”

^ Gen. 4:7 Or “will there not be an exaltation?”

^ Gen. 4:12 Lit., “power.”

^ Gen. 4:14 Lit., “from the face of the ground.”

^ Gen. 4:15 Or “established.”

^ Gen. 4:16 Or “the land of Nod.”

^ Gen. 4:21 Or “flute.”

^ Gen. 4:25 Meaning “Appointed; Put; Set.”

^ Gen. 4:25 Lit., “seed.”

Genesis  5 : 1 - 32

5 This is the book of Adam’s history. In the day that God created Adam, he made him in the likeness of God. 2 Male and female he created them. On the day they were created, he blessed them and named them Man.[*]

3 Adam lived for 130 years and then became father to a son in his likeness, in his image, and he named him Seth. 4 After becoming father to Seth, Adam lived for 800 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 5 So all the days of Adam’s life amounted to 930 years, and then he died.

6 Seth lived for 105 years and then became father to E′nosh. 7 After becoming father to E′nosh, Seth lived for 807 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 8 So all the days of Seth amounted to 912 years, and then he died.

9 E′nosh lived for 90 years and then became father to Ke′nan. 10 After becoming father to Ke′nan, E′nosh lived for 815 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 11 So all the days of E′nosh amounted to 905 years, and then he died.

12 Ke′nan lived for 70 years and then became father to Ma·hal′a·lel. 13 After becoming father to Ma·hal′a·lel, Ke′nan lived for 840 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 14 So all the days of Ke′nan amounted to 910 years, and then he died.

15 Ma·hal′a·lel lived for 65 years and then became father to Ja′red. 16 After becoming father to Ja′red, Ma·hal′a·lel lived for 830 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 17 So all the days of Ma·hal′a·lel amounted to 895 years, and then he died.

18 Ja′red lived for 162 years and then became father to E′noch. 19 After becoming father to E′noch, Ja′red lived for 800 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 20 So all the days of Ja′red amounted to 962 years, and then he died.

21 E′noch lived for 65 years and then became father to Me·thu′se·lah. 22 After becoming father to Me·thu′se·lah, E′noch continued to walk with the true God[*] for 300 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 23 So all the days of E′noch amounted to 365 years. 24 E′noch kept walking with the true God. Then he was no more, for God took him.

25 Me·thu′se·lah lived for 187 years and then became father to La′mech. 26 After becoming father to La′mech, Me·thu′se·lah lived for 782 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 27 So all the days of Me·thu′se·lah amounted to 969 years, and then he died.

28 La′mech lived for 182 years and then became father to a son. 29 He named him Noah,[*] saying: “This one will bring us comfort[*] from our labor and from the painful toil of our hands because of the ground that Jehovah has cursed.” 30 After becoming father to Noah, La′mech lived for 595 years. And he became father to sons and daughters. 31 So all the days of La′mech amounted to 777 years, and then he died.

32 After Noah reached 500 years of age, he became father to Shem, Ham, and Ja′pheth.

^ Gen. 5:2 Or “Adam; Mankind.”

^ Gen. 5:22 Lit., “the God.” See Glossary.

^ Gen. 5:29 Probably meaning “Rest; Consolation.”

^ Gen. 5:29 Or “relief.”

Genesis  14 : 1 - 24

14 Now in the days of Am′ra·phel king of Shi′nar, Ar′i·och king of El·la′sar, Ched·or·la·o′mer king of E′lam, and Ti′dal king of Goi′im, 2 these made war with Be′ra king of Sod′om, Bir′sha king of Go·mor′rah, Shi′nab king of Ad′mah, Shem·e′ber king of Ze·boi′im, and the king of Be′la, that is, Zo′ar. 3 All of these joined forces at the Valley[*] of Sid′dim, that is, the Salt Sea.[*]

4 They had served Ched·or·la·o′mer for 12 years, but they rebelled in the 13th year. 5 So in the 14th year, Ched·or·la·o′mer and the kings who were with him came and defeated the Reph′a·im in Ash′te·roth-kar·na′im, the Zu′zim in Ham, the E′mim in Sha′veh-kir·i·a·tha′im, 6 and the Hor′ites in their mountain of Se′ir down to El-pa′ran, which is at the wilderness. 7 Then they turned back and came to En-mish′pat, that is, Ka′desh, and conquered the whole territory of the A·mal′ek·ites and also the Am′or·ites who were dwelling in Haz′a·zon-ta′mar.

8 At this point, the king of Sod′om went on the march, and also the king of Go·mor′rah, the king of Ad′mah, the king of Ze·boi′im, and the king of Be′la, that is, Zo′ar, and they drew up in battle formation against them in the Valley[*] of Sid′dim, 9 against Ched·or·la·o′mer king of E′lam, Ti′dal king of Goi′im, Am′ra·phel king of Shi′nar, and Ar′i·och king of El·la′sar—four kings against the five. 10 Now the Valley[*] of Sid′dim was full of bitumen pits, and the kings of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah tried to escape and fell into them, and those who remained fled to the mountainous region. 11 Then the victors took all the goods of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and all their food and went on their way. 12 They also took Lot, the son of A′bram’s brother who was dwelling in Sod′om, as well as his goods, and they continued on their way.

13 After that a man who had escaped came and told A′bram the Hebrew. He was then dwelling[*] among the big trees of Mam′re the Am′or·ite, the brother of Esh′col and A′ner. These men were allies of A′bram. 14 Thus A′bram heard that his relative[*] had been taken captive. With that he mobilized his trained men, 318 servants born in his household, and went in pursuit up to Dan. 15 During the night, he divided his forces, and he and his servants attacked and defeated them. And he pursued them up to Ho′bah, which is north of Damascus. 16 He recovered all the goods, and he also recovered Lot his relative, his goods, the women, and the other people.

17 After A′bram returned from defeating Ched·or·la·o′mer and the kings who were with him, the king of Sod′om went out to meet A′bram at the Valley[*] of Sha′veh, that is, the Valley of the King. 18 And Mel·chiz′e·dek king of Sa′lem brought out bread and wine; he was priest of the Most High God.

19 Then he blessed him and said:

“Blessed be A′bram by the Most High God,

Maker of heaven and earth;

20 And praised be the Most High God,

Who has handed your oppressors over to you!”

And A′bram gave him a tenth of everything.

21 After that the king of Sod′om said to A′bram: “Give me the people,[*] but take the goods for yourself.” 22 But A′bram said to the king of Sod′om: “I raise my hand in an oath to Jehovah the Most High God, Maker of heaven and earth, 23 that I will not take anything that is yours, from a thread to a sandal lace, so that you may not say, ‘I made A′bram rich.’ 24 I will take nothing except what the young men have already eaten. As for the share of the men who went with me, A′ner, Esh′col, and Mam′re—let them take their share.”

^ Gen. 14:3 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Gen. 14:3 That is, the Dead Sea.

^ Gen. 14:8 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Gen. 14:10 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Gen. 14:13 Or “dwelling in tents.”

^ Gen. 14:14 Lit., “brother.”

^ Gen. 14:17 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Gen. 14:21 Or “souls.”

Genesis  16 : 1 - 16

16 Now A′bram’s wife Sar′ai had borne him no children, but she had an Egyptian servant whose name was Ha′gar. 2 So Sar′ai said to A′bram: “Please now! Jehovah has prevented me from bearing children. Please, have relations with my servant. Perhaps I can have children by means of her.” So A′bram listened to what Sar′ai said. 3 After A′bram had lived for ten years in the land of Ca′naan, A′bram’s wife Sar′ai took her Egyptian servant Ha′gar and gave her to her husband A′bram as his wife. 4 So he had relations with Ha′gar, and she became pregnant. When she realized that she was pregnant, she began to despise her mistress.

5 At this Sar′ai said to A′bram: “The injury done to me is your fault. I was the one who put my servant in your arms,[*] but when she realized that she was pregnant, she began to despise me. May Jehovah judge between me and you.” 6 So A′bram said to Sar′ai: “Look! Your servant is under your authority. Do to her whatever you think is best.” Then Sar′ai humiliated her, and she ran away from her.

7 Later Jehovah’s angel found her at a spring of waters in the wilderness, the spring on the way to Shur. 8 And he said: “Ha′gar, servant of Sar′ai, where have you come from and where are you going?” To this she said: “I am running away from my mistress Sar′ai.” 9 Jehovah’s angel then said to her: “Return to your mistress and humble yourself under her hand.” 10 Then Jehovah’s angel said: “I will greatly multiply your offspring,[*] so that they will be too numerous to count.” 11 Jehovah’s angel added: “Here you are pregnant, and you will give birth to a son, and you must name him Ish′ma·el,[*] for Jehovah has heard your affliction. 12 He will be a wild donkey[*] of a man. His hand will be against everyone, and everyone’s hand will be against him, and he will dwell opposite all his brothers.”[*]

13 Then she called on the name of Jehovah, who was speaking to her: “You are a God of sight,” for she said: “Have I here actually looked upon the one who sees me?” 14 That is why the well was called Be′er-la′hai-roi.[*] (It is between Ka′desh and Be′red.) 15 So Ha′gar bore to A′bram a son, and A′bram named his son, whom Ha′gar bore, Ish′ma·el. 16 A′bram was 86 years old when Ha′gar bore Ish′ma·el to him.

^ Gen. 16:5 Lit., “in your bosom.”

^ Gen. 16:10 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 16:11 Meaning “God Hears.”

^ Gen. 16:12 Or “an onager,” a kind of wild donkey, though some think that it refers to a zebra. Likely a reference to an independent disposition.

^ Gen. 16:12 Or possibly, “and he will live in hostility to all his brothers.”

^ Gen. 16:14 Meaning “Well of the Living One Who Sees Me.”

Genesis  25 : 1 - 34

25 Now Abraham again took a wife, and her name was Ke·tu′rah. 2 In time she bore him Zim′ran, Jok′shan, Me′dan, Mid′i·an, Ish′bak, and Shu′ah.

3 Jok′shan became father to She′ba and De′dan.

The sons of De′dan were As·shu′rim, Le·tu′shim, and Le·um′mim.

4 The sons of Mid′i·an were E′phah, E′pher, Ha′noch, A·bi′da, and El·da′ah.

All of these were the sons of Ke·tu′rah.

5 Later on Abraham gave everything he had to Isaac, 6 but Abraham gave gifts to his sons by his concubines. Then while he was still alive, he sent them eastward, away from Isaac his son, to the land of the East. 7 The years of Abraham’s life were 175 years. 8 Then Abraham breathed his last and died at a good old age, old and satisfied, and was gathered to his people.[*] 9 His sons Isaac and Ish′ma·el buried him in the cave of Mach·pe′lah in the field of E′phron the son of Zo′har the Hit′tite that is in front of Mam′re, 10 the field that Abraham had purchased from the sons of Heth. There Abraham was buried, with his wife Sarah. 11 After Abraham’s death, God continued to bless his son Isaac, and Isaac was dwelling near Be′er-la′hai-roi.

12 This is the history of Ish′ma·el the son of Abraham whom Ha′gar the Egyptian, the servant of Sarah, bore to Abraham.

13 Now these are the names of the sons of Ish′ma·el, by their names according to their family origins: Ish′ma·el’s firstborn Ne·ba′ioth, then Ke′dar, Ad′be·el, Mib′sam, 14 Mish′ma, Du′mah, Mas′sa, 15 Ha′dad, Te′ma, Je′tur, Na′phish, and Ked′e·mah. 16 These are the sons of Ish′ma·el, and these are their names by their settlements and by their encampments,[*] 12 chieftains according to their clans. 17 And Ish′ma·el lived for 137 years. Then he breathed his last and died and was gathered to his people.[*] 18 And they took up dwelling from Hav′i·lah near Shur, which is close to Egypt, as far as As·syr′i·a. He settled near all his brothers.[*]

19 And this is the history of Isaac the son of Abraham.

Abraham became father to Isaac. 20 Isaac was 40 years old when he married Re·bek′ah, the daughter of Be·thu′el the A·ra·mae′an of Pad′dan-a′ram, the sister of La′ban the A·ra·mae′an. 21 And Isaac kept pleading with Jehovah regarding his wife, because she was barren; so Jehovah responded to his plea, and his wife Re·bek′ah became pregnant. 22 And the sons within her began to struggle with each other, so that she said: “If this is the way it is, why should I go on living?” So she inquired of Jehovah. 23 And Jehovah said to her: “Two nations are in your womb, and two peoples will be separated from within you; and the one nation will be stronger than the other nation, and the older will serve the younger.”

24 When the time came for her to give birth, look! twins were in her womb. 25 Then the first came out red all over and was like a garment of hair, so they named him E′sau.[*] 26 After that his brother came out and his hand was holding onto the heel of E′sau, so he named him Jacob.[*] Isaac was 60 years old when she gave birth to them.

27 As the boys got bigger, E′sau became a skilled hunter, a man of the field, but Jacob was a blameless man, dwelling in tents. 28 And Isaac loved E′sau because it meant game in his mouth, whereas Re·bek′ah loved Jacob. 29 On one occasion Jacob was boiling some stew when E′sau returned from the field exhausted. 30 So E′sau said to Jacob: “Quick, please, give me some[*] of the red stew that you have there,[*] for I am exhausted!”[*] That is why his name was E′dom.[*] 31 To this Jacob said: “First sell me your right as firstborn!” 32 And E′sau continued: “Here I am about to die! What use is a birthright to me?” 33 And Jacob added: “Swear to me first!” So he swore to him and sold his right as firstborn to Jacob. 34 Then Jacob gave E′sau bread and lentil stew, and he ate and drank, and he got up and went away. Thus E′sau despised the birthright.

^ Gen. 25:8 This is a poetic expression for death.

^ Gen. 25:16 Or “walled camps.”

^ Gen. 25:17 This is a poetic expression for death.

^ Gen. 25:18 Or possibly, “He lived in hostility to all his brothers.”

^ Gen. 25:25 Meaning “Hairy.”

^ Gen. 25:26 Meaning “One Seizing the Heel; Supplanter.”

^ Gen. 25:30 Or “give me a swallow.”

^ Gen. 25:30 Lit., “the red, this the red.”

^ Gen. 25:30 Or “famished.”

^ Gen. 25:30 Meaning “Red.”

Genesis  26 : 1 - 35

26 Now there was a famine in the land, in addition to the first famine that occurred in the days of Abraham, so that Isaac went to A·bim′e·lech king of the Phi·lis′tines, in Ge′rar. 2 Then Jehovah appeared to him and said: “Do not go down to Egypt. Dwell in the land that I designate to you. 3 Reside as a foreigner in this land, and I will continue with you and bless you because to you and to your offspring[*] I will give all these lands, and I will carry out the oath that I swore to your father Abraham: 4 ‘I will multiply your offspring[*] like the stars of the heavens; and I will give to your offspring[*] all these lands; and by means of your offspring,[*] all nations of the earth will obtain a blessing for themselves,’ 5 on account of the fact that Abraham listened to my voice and continued to keep my requirements, my commands, my statutes, and my laws.” 6 So Isaac continued to dwell in Ge′rar.

7 When the men of the place kept asking about his wife, he would say: “She is my sister.” He was afraid to say, “She is my wife,” for he said, “The men of the place might kill me because of Re·bek′ah,” for she was beautiful in appearance. 8 After some time had passed, A·bim′e·lech king of the Phi·lis′tines was looking out of the window, and he saw Isaac displaying affection for[*] Re·bek′ah his wife. 9 At once A·bim′e·lech called Isaac and said: “She is actually your wife! Why did you say, ‘She is my sister’?” At this Isaac said to him: “I said it for fear I should die because of her.” 10 But A·bim′e·lech continued: “What have you done to us? One of the people could easily have lain down with your wife, and you would have brought guilt upon us!” 11 Then A·bim′e·lech commanded all the people, saying: “Anybody touching this man and his wife will surely be put to death!”

12 And Isaac began to sow seed in that land, and in that year he reaped 100 times what he sowed, for Jehovah was blessing him. 13 The man became wealthy, and he continued to prosper until he became very wealthy. 14 He acquired flocks of sheep and herds of cattle and a large body of servants, and the Phi·lis′tines began to envy him.

15 So the Phi·lis′tines took soil and stopped up all the wells that his father’s servants had dug in the days of Abraham. 16 A·bim′e·lech then said to Isaac: “Move from our neighborhood, for you have grown far stronger than we are.” 17 So Isaac moved from there and encamped in the valley[*] of Ge′rar and began dwelling there. 18 And Isaac again dug the wells that had been dug in the days of his father Abraham but that the Phi·lis′tines had stopped up after Abraham’s death, and he called them by the names that his father had given them.

19 When the servants of Isaac were digging in the valley,[*] they found a well of fresh water. 20 And the shepherds of Ge′rar began quarreling with the shepherds of Isaac, saying: “The water is ours!” So he named the well E′sek,[*] because they had quarreled with him. 21 And they started digging another well, and they began quarreling over it also. So he named it Sit′nah.[*] 22 Later he moved away from there and dug another well, but they did not quarrel over it. So he named it Re·ho′both[*] and said: “It is because now Jehovah has given us ample room and has made us fruitful in the land.”

23 Then he went up from there to Be′er-she′ba. 24 That night Jehovah appeared to him and said: “I am the God of your father Abraham. Do not be afraid, for I am with you, and I will bless you and multiply your offspring[*] on account of Abraham my servant.” 25 So he built an altar there and called on the name of Jehovah. And Isaac pitched his tent there, and his servants dug a well there.

26 Later A·bim′e·lech came to him from Ge′rar with A·huz′zath his personal adviser and Phi′col the chief of his army. 27 At this Isaac said to them: “Why have you come to me, seeing that you hated me and sent me away from your neighborhood?” 28 To this they said: “We have clearly seen that Jehovah has been with you. So we said, ‘Let there, please, be an oath of obligation between us and you, and let us make a covenant with you 29 that you will do nothing bad to us just as we have not harmed you, seeing that we have done only good to you in that we sent you away in peace. You now are the blessed of Jehovah.’” 30 Then he made a feast for them, and they ate and drank. 31 In the morning they got up early and swore an oath to each other. After that Isaac sent them away, and they went from him in peace.

32 On that day the servants of Isaac came and reported to him about the well that they had dug, and they told him: “We have found water!” 33 So he named it Shi′bah. That is why the name of the city is Be′er-she′ba to this day.

34 When E′sau was 40 years old, he took as wife Ju′dith the daughter of Be·e′ri the Hit′tite and also Bas′e·math the daughter of E′lon the Hit′tite. 35 They were a source of great grief[*] to Isaac and Re·bek′ah.

^ Gen. 26:3 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 26:4 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 26:4 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 26:4 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 26:8 Or “embracing.”

^ Gen. 26:17 Or “wadi.”

^ Gen. 26:19 Or “wadi.”

^ Gen. 26:20 Meaning “Contention.”

^ Gen. 26:21 Meaning “Accusation.”

^ Gen. 26:22 Meaning “Broad Places.”

^ Gen. 26:24 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 26:35 Lit., “bitterness of spirit.”

Genesis  28 : 1 - 22

28 So Isaac called Jacob and blessed him and commanded him, saying: “You must not take a wife from the daughters of Ca′naan. 2 Go away to Pad′dan-a′ram to the house of Be·thu′el, your mother’s father, and from there take for yourself a wife from the daughters of La′ban, your mother’s brother. 3 God Almighty will bless you and make you fruitful and multiply you, and you will certainly become a congregation of peoples. 4 And he will give to you the blessing of Abraham, to you and to your offspring[*] with you, so that you may take possession of the land where you have been living as a foreigner, which God has given to Abraham.”

5 So Isaac sent Jacob away, and he departed for Pad′dan-a′ram, to La′ban the son of Be·thu′el the A·ra·mae′an, the brother of Re·bek′ah, the mother of Jacob and E′sau.

6 E′sau saw that Isaac had blessed Jacob and had sent him away to Pad′dan-a′ram to take a wife from there and that when he blessed him, he commanded him, “Do not take a wife from the daughters of Ca′naan,” 7 and that Jacob obeyed his father and his mother and departed for Pad′dan-a′ram. 8 E′sau then realized that the daughters of Ca′naan were displeasing to his father Isaac, 9 so E′sau went to Ish′ma·el and took as wife Ma′ha·lath the daughter of Abraham’s son Ish′ma·el, the sister of Ne·ba′ioth, in addition to the other wives he already had.

10 Jacob departed from Be′er-she′ba and kept going toward Ha′ran. 11 In time he came to a place and prepared to spend the night there because the sun had set. So he took one of the stones of that place and set it to rest his head on and lay down there. 12 Then he had a dream, and look! there was a stairway[*] set on the earth, and its top reached up to the heavens; and there were God’s angels ascending and descending on it. 13 And look! there was Jehovah stationed above it, and he said:

“I am Jehovah the God of Abraham your father and the God of Isaac. The land on which you are lying, to you I am going to give it and to your offspring.[*] 14 And your offspring[*] will certainly become like the dust particles of the earth, and you will spread abroad to the west and to the east and to the north and to the south, and by means of you and by means of your offspring[*] all the families of the ground will certainly be blessed.[*] 15 I am with you, and I will safeguard you wherever you go, and I will return you to this land. I will not leave you until I have done what I have promised you.”

16 Then Jacob awoke from his sleep and said: “Truly Jehovah is in this place, and I did not know it.” 17 And he grew fearful and added: “How awe-inspiring this place is! This can only be the house of God, and this is the gate of the heavens.” 18 So Jacob got up early in the morning and took the stone on which he had rested his head and set it up as a pillar and poured oil on top of it. 19 So he named that place Beth′el,[*] but previously the city’s name was Luz.

20 Jacob then made a vow, saying: “If God will continue with me and will protect me on my journey and will give me bread to eat and garments to wear 21 and I return in peace to the house of my father, then Jehovah will certainly have proved to be my God. 22 And this stone that I have set up as a pillar will become a house of God, and without fail I will give you a tenth of everything you give to me.”

^ Gen. 28:4 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 28:12 Or “ladder.”

^ Gen. 28:13 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 28:14 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 28:14 Lit., “seed.”

^ Gen. 28:14 Or “will obtain a blessing for themselves.”

^ Gen. 28:19 Meaning “House of God.”

Genesis  36 : 1 - 43

36 This is the history of E′sau, that is, E′dom.

2 E′sau took his wives from the daughters of Ca′naan: A′dah the daughter of E′lon the Hit′tite; and O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, the granddaughter of Zib′e·on the Hi′vite; 3 and Bas′e·math, Ish′ma·el’s daughter, the sister of Ne·ba′ioth.

4 And A′dah bore El′i·phaz to E′sau, and Bas′e·math bore Reu′el, 5 and O·hol·i·ba′mah bore Je′ush, Ja′lam, and Kor′ah.

These are the sons of E′sau, who were born to him in the land of Ca′naan. 6 After that E′sau took his wives, his sons, his daughters, all the members[*] of his household, his herd and all his other beasts, and all the wealth he had accumulated in the land of Ca′naan and he went to another land some distance away from Jacob his brother. 7 For their goods had become too many for them to dwell together, and the land where they were residing[*] was not able to sustain them because of their herds. 8 So E′sau took up dwelling in the mountainous region of Se′ir. E′sau is E′dom.

9 And this is the history of E′sau the father of E′dom in the mountainous region of Se′ir.

10 These are the names of the sons of E′sau: El′i·phaz the son of A′dah, E′sau’s wife; Reu′el the son of Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

11 The sons of El′i·phaz were Te′man, O′mar, Ze′pho, Ga′tam, and Ke′naz. 12 Tim′na became the concubine of El′i·phaz, E′sau’s son. In time she bore to El′i·phaz, Am′a·lek. These are the sons of A′dah, E′sau’s wife.

13 These are the sons of Reu′el: Na′hath, Ze′rah, Sham′mah, and Miz′zah. These were the sons of Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

14 These were the sons of O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, the granddaughter of Zib′e·on, E′sau’s wife, whom she bore to E′sau: Je′ush, Ja′lam, and Kor′ah.

15 These are the sheikhs[*] of the sons of E′sau: The sons of El′i·phaz, E′sau’s firstborn: Sheikh Te′man, Sheikh O′mar, Sheikh Ze′pho, Sheikh Ke′naz, 16 Sheikh Kor′ah, Sheikh Ga′tam, and Sheikh Am′a·lek. These are the sheikhs of El′i·phaz in the land of E′dom. These are the sons by A′dah.

17 These are the sons of Reu′el, E′sau’s son: Sheikh Na′hath, Sheikh Ze′rah, Sheikh Sham′mah, and Sheikh Miz′zah. These are the sheikhs of Reu′el in the land of E′dom. These are the sons by Bas′e·math, E′sau’s wife.

18 Finally these are the sons of O·hol·i·ba′mah, E′sau’s wife: Sheikh Je′ush, Sheikh Ja′lam, and Sheikh Kor′ah. These are the sheikhs of O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah, E′sau’s wife.

19 These are the sons of E′sau, and these are their sheikhs. He is E′dom.

20 These are the sons of Se′ir the Hor′ite, the inhabitants of the land: Lo′tan, Sho′bal, Zib′e·on, A′nah, 21 Di′shon, E′zer, and Di′shan. These are the sheikhs of the Hor′ites, the sons of Se′ir, in the land of E′dom.

22 The sons of Lo′tan were Ho′ri and He′mam, and Lo′tan’s sister was Tim′na.

23 These are the sons of Sho′bal: Al′van, Man′a·hath, E′bal, She′pho, and O′nam.

24 These are the sons of Zib′e·on: A′iah and A′nah. This is the A′nah who found the hot springs in the wilderness while he was tending the donkeys for Zib′e·on his father.

25 These are the children of A′nah: Di′shon and O·hol·i·ba′mah the daughter of A′nah.

26 These are the sons of Di′shon: Hem′dan, Esh′ban, Ith′ran, and Che′ran.

27 These are the sons of E′zer: Bil′han, Za′a·van, and A′kan.

28 These are the sons of Di′shan: Uz and A′ran.

29 These are the sheikhs of the Hor′ites: Sheikh Lo′tan, Sheikh Sho′bal, Sheikh Zib′e·on, Sheikh A′nah, 30 Sheikh Di′shon, Sheikh E′zer, and Sheikh Di′shan. These are the sheikhs of the Hor′ites according to their sheikhs in the land of Se′ir.

31 Now these are the kings who reigned in the land of E′dom before any king reigned over the Israelites.[*] 32 Be′la son of Be′or reigned in E′dom, and the name of his city was Din′ha·bah. 33 When Be′la died, Jo′bab son of Ze′rah from Boz′rah began to reign in his place. 34 When Jo′bab died, Hu′sham from the land of the Te′man·ites began to reign in his place. 35 When Hu′sham died, Ha′dad son of Be′dad, who defeated the Mid′i·an·ites in the territory[*] of Mo′ab, began to reign in his place, and the name of his city was A′vith. 36 When Ha′dad died, Sam′lah from Mas·re′kah began to reign in his place. 37 When Sam′lah died, Sha′ul from Re·ho′both by the River began to reign in his place. 38 When Sha′ul died, Ba′al-ha′nan the son of Ach′bor began to reign in his place. 39 When Ba′al-ha′nan the son of Ach′bor died, Ha′dar began to reign in his place. The name of his city was Pa′u, and the name of his wife was Me·het′a·bel the daughter of Ma′tred the daughter of Me′za·hab.

40 So these are the names of the sheikhs of E′sau according to their families, according to their places, by their names: Sheikh Tim′na, Sheikh Al′vah, Sheikh Je′theth, 41 Sheikh O·hol·i·ba′mah, Sheikh E′lah, Sheikh Pi′non, 42 Sheikh Ke′naz, Sheikh Te′man, Sheikh Mib′zar, 43 Sheikh Mag′di·el, and Sheikh I′ram. These are the sheikhs of E′dom according to their settlements in the land of their possession. This is E′sau the father of E′dom.

^ Gen. 36:6 Or “souls.”

^ Gen. 36:7 Or “living as foreigners.”

^ Gen. 36:15 A sheikh was a tribal chief.

^ Gen. 36:31 Lit., “the sons of Israel.”

^ Gen. 36:35 Lit., “field.”

Genesis  47 : 1 - 31

47 So Joseph went and reported to Phar′aoh: “My father and my brothers and their flocks and their herds and all that they possess have come from the land of Ca′naan, and they are in the land of Go′shen.” 2 He took five of his brothers and presented them to Phar′aoh.

3 Phar′aoh said to his brothers: “What is your occupation?” They replied to Phar′aoh: “Your servants are herders of sheep, both we and our forefathers.” 4 Then they said to Phar′aoh: “We have come to reside as foreigners in the land because there are no pastures for the flock of your servants, for the famine is severe in the land of Ca′naan. So please let your servants dwell in the land of Go′shen.” 5 At that Phar′aoh said to Joseph: “Your father and your brothers have come here to you. 6 The land of Egypt is at your disposal. Have your father and your brothers dwell in the very best part of the land. Let them dwell in the land of Go′shen, and if you know of any capable men among them, put them in charge of my livestock.”

7 Then Joseph brought in Jacob his father and presented him to Phar′aoh, and Jacob blessed Phar′aoh. 8 Phar′aoh asked Jacob: “How old are you?” 9 Jacob said to Phar′aoh: “The years of my wanderings[*] are 130. Few and distressing the years of my life have been, and they are not as long as the years of the lives of my forefathers during their wanderings.”[*] 10 After that Jacob blessed Phar′aoh and went out from before him.

11 So Joseph settled his father and his brothers, and he gave them a possession in the land of Egypt, in the very best part of the land, in the land of Ram′e·ses, just as Phar′aoh had commanded. 12 And Joseph kept supplying his father and his brothers and the entire household of his father with food[*] according to the number of their children.

13 Now there was no food[*] in all the land, because the famine was very severe, and the land of Egypt and the land of Ca′naan became exhausted as a result of the famine. 14 Joseph was collecting all the money that was to be found in the land of Egypt and in the land of Ca′naan for the grain that people were buying, and Joseph kept bringing the money into Phar′aoh’s house. 15 In time the money from the land of Egypt and the land of Ca′naan was spent, and all the Egyptians began coming to Joseph, saying: “Give us food! Why should we die before your very eyes because our money has run out?” 16 Then Joseph said: “If your money has run out, hand over your livestock, and I will give you food in exchange for your livestock.” 17 So they began bringing their livestock to Joseph, and Joseph kept giving them food in exchange for their horses, the livestock of the flock and of the herd, and the donkeys, and he kept providing them with food in exchange for all their livestock during that year.

18 When that year came to its close, they began coming to him the next year and saying: “We will not hide from my lord that the money and the stock of domestic animals have already been given to my lord. We have nothing left for my lord but our bodies and our land. 19 Why should we die before your eyes, both we and our land? Buy us and our land in exchange for food, and we together with our land will become slaves to Phar′aoh. Give us seed so that we may live and not die and that our land may not become desolate.” 20 Joseph then bought all the land of the Egyptians for Phar′aoh because every Egyptian sold his field, for the famine was very severe; and the land became Phar′aoh’s.

21 Then he moved the people into cities, from one end of the territory of Egypt to its other end. 22 Only the land of the priests he did not buy, because the rations for the priests were from Phar′aoh and they lived on their rations that Phar′aoh gave them. That is why they did not sell their land. 23 Then Joseph said to the people: “See, I have today bought you and your land for Phar′aoh. Here is seed for you, and you must sow the land with it. 24 When it produces, give a fifth to Phar′aoh, but four parts will be yours as seed for the field and as food for you and for those in your houses and for your children to eat.” 25 So they said: “You have preserved our lives. Let us find favor in the eyes of my lord, and we will become slaves to Phar′aoh.” 26 Then Joseph made it a decree, which is valid until today over the land of Egypt, that a fifth belongs to Phar′aoh. It was only the land of the priests that did not become Phar′aoh’s.

27 Israel continued to dwell in the land of Egypt, in the land of Go′shen, and they settled in it and were fruitful and increased greatly. 28 And Jacob lived on in the land of Egypt for 17 years, so that the days of Jacob’s life came to be 147 years.

29 The time was approaching for Israel to die, so he called his son Joseph and said: “If, now, I have found favor in your eyes, place your hand, please, under my thigh, and show loyal love and faithfulness to me. Please, do not bury me in Egypt. 30 When I die,[*] you must carry me out of Egypt and bury me in the grave of my forefathers.” Accordingly, he said: “I will do just as you say.” 31 Then he said: “Swear to me.” So he swore to him. At that Israel bowed down at the head of his bed.

^ Gen. 47:9 Or “sojourning; residing as a foreigner.”

^ Gen. 47:9 Or “sojourning; residing as foreigners.”

^ Gen. 47:12 Lit., “bread.”

^ Gen. 47:13 Lit., “bread.”

^ Gen. 47:30 Lit., “lie down with my fathers.”

Numbers  1 : 1 - 54

NUMBERS

1 And Jehovah spoke to Moses in the wilderness of Si′nai, in the tent of meeting, on the first day of the second month, in the second year of their coming out of the land of Egypt. He said: 2 “Take a census of the whole assembly of the Israelites[*] individually[*] according to their families, according to their paternal houses, according to the count of the names of all the males. 3 You and Aaron are to register by their companies[*] all those from 20 years old and up who can serve in the army in Israel.

4 “Take with you one man from each tribe; each one is to be a head of his paternal house. 5 These are the names of the men who will stand with you: of Reu′ben, E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur; 6 of Sim′e·on, She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai; 7 of Judah, Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab; 8 of Is′sa·char, Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar; 9 of Zeb′u·lun, E·li′ab the son of He′lon; 10 of the sons of Joseph: from E′phra·im, E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud; from Ma·nas′seh, Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur; 11 of Benjamin, Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni; 12 of Dan, A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai; 13 of Ash′er, Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran; 14 of Gad, E·li′a·saph the son of Deu′el; 15 of Naph′ta·li, A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 16 These are the ones summoned from the assembly. They are the chieftains of the tribes of their fathers, the heads of the thousands of Israel.”

17 So Moses and Aaron took these men who had been designated by name. 18 They gathered all the assembly on the first day of the second month, so that they might be registered individually by name, by family, and by their paternal houses, from 20 years old and up, 19 just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. So he registered them in the wilderness of Si′nai.

20 The sons of Reu′ben, the descendants of Israel’s firstborn, were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted individually, 21 and the number registered of the tribe of Reu′ben was 46,500.

22 The descendants of Sim′e·on were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted individually, 23 and the number registered of the tribe of Sim′e·on was 59,300.

24 The descendants of Gad were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 25 and the number registered of the tribe of Gad was 45,650.

26 The descendants of Judah were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 27 and the number registered of the tribe of Judah was 74,600.

28 The descendants of Is′sa·char were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 29 and the number registered of the tribe of Is′sa·char was 54,400.

30 The descendants of Zeb′u·lun were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 31 and the number registered of the tribe of Zeb′u·lun was 57,400.

32 The descendants of Joseph through E′phra·im were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 33 and the number registered of the tribe of E′phra·im was 40,500.

34 The descendants of Ma·nas′seh were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 35 and the number registered of the tribe of Ma·nas′seh was 32,200.

36 The descendants of Benjamin were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 37 and the number registered of the tribe of Benjamin was 35,400.

38 The descendants of Dan were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 39 and the number registered of the tribe of Dan was 62,700.

40 The descendants of Ash′er were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 41 and the number registered of the tribe of Ash′er was 41,500.

42 The descendants of Naph′ta·li were listed by name, by family, and by their paternal houses. All the males from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army were counted, 43 and the number registered of the tribe of Naph′ta·li was 53,400.

44 These were registered by Moses together with Aaron and the 12 chieftains of Israel, each representing his paternal house. 45 All the Israelites from 20 years old and up who could serve in the army in Israel were registered by their paternal house, 46 and the total number registered was 603,550.

47 But the Levites were not registered in among them by the tribe of their fathers. 48 So Jehovah told Moses: 49 “Only the tribe of Le′vi you are not to register, and you should not include the number of them along with the other Israelites. 50 You should appoint the Levites over the tabernacle of the Testimony and over all its utensils and over everything that belongs to it. They will carry the tabernacle and all its utensils, and they will minister at it, and they are to camp around the tabernacle. 51 Whenever the tabernacle is to be moved, the Levites should take it down; and when the tabernacle is to be reassembled, the Levites should set it up; and any unauthorized person[*] who comes near should be put to death.

52 “Each Israelite should set up his tent in his assigned camp, each man according to his three-tribe division[*] by their companies.[*] 53 And the Levites should encamp around the tabernacle of the Testimony, so that no indignation may arise against the assembly of the Israelites; and the Levites must be responsible for the care of[*] the tabernacle of the Testimony.”

54 The people of Israel did all that Jehovah had commanded Moses. They did just so.

^ Num. 1:2 Lit., “sons of Israel.”

^ Num. 1:2 Or “head by head of them.”

^ Num. 1:3 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 1:51 Lit., “any stranger,” that is, a non-Levite.

^ Num. 1:52 Or “by his standard (banner).”

^ Num. 1:52 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 1:53 Or “for guarding; for carrying out their service at.”

Numbers  2 : 1 - 34

2 Jehovah now spoke to Moses and Aaron, saying: 2 “The Israelites should encamp where their three-tribe division is assigned, each man near the banner[*] of his paternal house. They should camp facing the tent of meeting, all around it.

3 “Those camping on the east side, toward the sunrise, will be the three-tribe division of the encampment of Judah by their companies;[*] the chieftain for the sons of Judah is Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab. 4 Those registered in his army are 74,600. 5 Camping alongside him will be the tribe of Is′sa·char; the chieftain for the sons of Is′sa·char is Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar. 6 Those registered in his army are 54,400. 7 Next is the tribe of Zeb′u·lun; the chieftain for the sons of Zeb′u·lun is E·li′ab the son of He′lon. 8 Those registered in his army are 57,400.

9 “All those registered in the armies of the camp of Judah are 186,400. They should break camp first.

10 “The three-tribe division of the encampment of Reu′ben by their companies[*] will be toward the south; the chieftain for the sons of Reu′ben is E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur. 11 Those registered in his army are 46,500. 12 Camping alongside him will be the tribe of Sim′e·on; the chieftain for the sons of Sim′e·on is She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai. 13 Those registered in his army are 59,300. 14 Next is the tribe of Gad; the chieftain for the sons of Gad is E·li′a·saph the son of Reu′el. 15 Those registered in his army are 45,650.

16 “All those registered in the armies of the camp of Reu′ben are 151,450, and they should break camp second.

17 “When the tent of meeting is moved, the camp of the Levites should be in the middle of the other camps.

“They should travel in the same order as they encamp, with each in his place, according to their three-tribe divisions.

18 “The three-tribe division of the encampment of E′phra·im by their companies[*] will be toward the west; the chieftain for the sons of E′phra·im is E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud. 19 Those registered in his army are 40,500. 20 Next to him will be the tribe of Ma·nas′seh; the chieftain for the sons of Ma·nas′seh is Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur. 21 Those registered in his army are 32,200. 22 Next is the tribe of Benjamin; the chieftain for the sons of Benjamin is Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni. 23 Those registered in his army are 35,400.

24 “All those registered in the armies of the camp of E′phra·im are 108,100, and they should break camp third.

25 “The three-tribe division of the encampment of Dan by their companies[*] will be toward the north; the chieftain for the sons of Dan is A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai. 26 Those registered in his army are 62,700. 27 Camping alongside him will be the tribe of Ash′er; the chieftain for the sons of Ash′er is Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran. 28 Those registered in his army are 41,500. 29 Next is the tribe of Naph′ta·li; the chieftain for the sons of Naph′ta·li is A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 30 Those registered in his army are 53,400.

31 “All those registered in the camp of Dan are 157,600. They should break camp last, according to their three-tribe divisions.”

32 These were the Israelites who were registered according to their paternal houses; the total of those in the camps registered for the army was 603,550. 33 But the Levites did not get registered along with the other Israelites, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses. 34 The Israelites did everything that Jehovah had commanded Moses. This is how they encamped by their three-tribe divisions and how they broke camp, each by family and according to their paternal houses.

^ Num. 2:2 Or “sign.”

^ Num. 2:3 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 2:10 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 2:18 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 2:25 Lit., “according to their armies.”

Numbers  3 : 1 - 51

3 Now these were the family lines[*] of Aaron and Moses in the day that Jehovah spoke with Moses on Mount Si′nai. 2 These were the names of Aaron’s sons: the firstborn Na′dab, and A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar, and Ith′a·mar. 3 These were the names of Aaron’s sons, the anointed priests who had been installed[*] to serve as priests. 4 However, Na′dab and A·bi′hu died before Jehovah when they offered unauthorized fire before Jehovah in the wilderness of Si′nai, and they did not have any sons. But El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar continued to serve as priests along with Aaron their father.

5 Jehovah then said to Moses: 6 “Bring the tribe of Le′vi forward, and stand them before Aaron the priest, and they will minister to him. 7 They are to fulfill their responsibilities toward him and toward all the assembly before the tent of meeting by carrying out their service in connection with the tabernacle. 8 They are to take care of all the utensils of the tent of meeting and to carry out their responsibilities toward the Israelites by taking care of the services related to the tabernacle. 9 You are to give the Levites to Aaron and his sons. They are given ones, given to him from the Israelites. 10 You should appoint Aaron and his sons, and they are to carry out their priestly duties, and any unauthorized person[*] who comes near should be put to death.”

11 Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 12 “As for me, look! I take the Levites from among the Israelites in place of all the firstborn[*] of the Israelites, and the Levites will become mine. 13 For every firstborn is mine. In the day that I struck every firstborn in the land of Egypt, I sanctified to myself every firstborn in Israel from man to beast. They are to become mine. I am Jehovah.”

14 Jehovah spoke further to Moses in the wilderness of Si′nai, saying: 15 “Register the sons of Le′vi by their paternal houses and by their families. You should register every male from a month old and up.” 16 So Moses registered them at the order of Jehovah, just as he had been commanded. 17 These were the names of the sons of Le′vi: Ger′shon, Ko′hath, and Me·rar′i.

18 Now these were the names of the sons of Ger′shon by their families: Lib′ni and Shim′e·i.

19 The sons of Ko′hath by their families were Am′ram, Iz′har, Heb′ron, and Uz′zi·el.

20 The sons of Me·rar′i by their families were Mah′li and Mu′shi.

These were the families of the Levites by their paternal houses.

21 From Ger′shon came the family of the Lib′nites and the family of the Shim′e·ites. These were the families of the Ger′shon·ites. 22 The number of all their males a month old and up who were registered was 7,500. 23 The families of the Ger′shon·ites were encamped behind the tabernacle toward the west. 24 The chieftain of the paternal house of the Ger′shon·ites was E·li′a·saph the son of La′el. 25 The responsibility of the sons of Ger′shon in the tent of meeting was to care for the tabernacle and the tent, its covering, the screen[*] of the entrance of the tent of meeting, 26 the hanging curtains of the courtyard, the screen[*] of the entrance of the courtyard that surrounds the tabernacle and the altar, its tent cords, and all the service connected with these.

27 From Ko′hath came the family of the Am′ram·ites, the family of the Iz′har·ites, the family of the Heb′ron·ites, and the family of the Uz·zi′el·ites. These were the families of the Ko′hath·ites. 28 The number of all the males from a month old and up was 8,600; they were responsible for taking care of the holy place. 29 The families of the sons of Ko′hath camped on the south side of the tabernacle. 30 The chieftain of the paternal house of the families of the Ko′hath·ites was E·li·za′phan the son of Uz′zi·el. 31 Their responsibility was to care for the Ark, the table, the lampstand, the altars, the utensils used to minister in the holy place, the screen,[*] and all the service connected with these.

32 The head chieftain of the Levites was El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest, who had the oversight of those taking care of the responsibilities of the holy place.

33 From Me·rar′i came the family of the Mah′lites and the family of the Mu′shites. These were the families of Me·rar′i. 34 The number of all the males from a month old and up who were registered was 6,200. 35 The chieftain of the paternal house of the families of Me·rar′i was Zu′ri·el the son of Ab′i·ha·il. They were encamped on the north side of the tabernacle. 36 The sons of Me·rar′i were responsible for overseeing the panel frames of the tabernacle, its bars, its pillars, its socket pedestals, all its utensils, and all the service connected with these, 37 as well as the pillars that were all around the courtyard and their socket pedestals, their tent pins, and their tent cords.

38 Those camping in front of the tabernacle toward the east, before the tent of meeting toward the sunrise, were Moses and Aaron and his sons. They were responsible for taking care of the sanctuary as their obligation in behalf of the Israelites. Any unauthorized person[*] coming near would be put to death.

39 All the Levite males from a month old and up, whom Moses and Aaron registered by their families at the order of Jehovah, were 22,000.

40 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Register all the firstborn males of the Israelites from a month old and up, count them, and make a list of their names. 41 You must take the Levites for me—I am Jehovah—in place of all the firstborn of the Israelites, and take the domestic animals of the Levites in place of all the firstborn of the domestic animals of the Israelites.” 42 Moses then registered all the firstborn among the Israelites, just as Jehovah had commanded him. 43 The number of all the firstborn males who were registered by name from a month old and up was 22,273.

44 Jehovah continued to speak to Moses, saying: 45 “Take the Levites in place of all the firstborn among the Israelites, and take the domestic animals of the Levites in place of their domestic animals, and the Levites must become mine. I am Jehovah. 46 As the ransom price of the 273 of the firstborn of the Israelites who are in excess of the Levites, 47 you are to take five shekels[*] for each individual, according to the standard shekel of the holy place.[*] A shekel is 20 ge′rahs.[*] 48 You are to give the money to Aaron and his sons as the ransom price of those who are in excess of them.” 49 So Moses took the money of the redemption price from those who were in excess of the ransom price of the Levites. 50 He took the money from the firstborn of the Israelites, 1,365 shekels, according to the standard shekel of the holy place. 51 Then Moses gave the money of the ransom price to Aaron and his sons according to the word[*] of Jehovah, just as Jehovah had commanded Moses.

^ Num. 3:1 Lit., “the generations.”

^ Num. 3:3 Lit., “whose hands had been filled.”

^ Num. 3:10 Lit., “any stranger,” that is, a man not of Aaron’s family.

^ Num. 3:12 Lit., “of every firstborn opening the womb.”

^ Num. 3:25 Or “curtain.”

^ Num. 3:26 Or “curtain.”

^ Num. 3:31 Or “curtain.”

^ Num. 3:38 Lit., “Any stranger,” that is, a non-Levite.

^ Num. 3:47 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Num. 3:47 Or “by the holy shekel.”

^ Num. 3:47 A gerah equaled 0.57 g (0.01835 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Num. 3:51 Lit., “mouth.”

Numbers  10 : 1 - 36

10 Jehovah then said to Moses: 2 “Make two trumpets for yourself; make them of hammered silver, and use them to summon the assembly and to break up the camps. 3 When both of them are blown, the whole assembly must be summoned to you at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 4 If just one is blown, only the chieftains, the heads of the thousands of Israel, will be summoned to you.

5 “When you sound a fluctuating trumpet blast, the camps of those to the east should depart. 6 When you sound a fluctuating trumpet blast a second time, the camps of those to the south should depart. They should sound the trumpet blasts in this way each time one of them departs.

7 “Now when calling the congregation together, you should blow the trumpets, but not with fluctuating blasts. 8 Aaron’s sons, the priests, should blow the trumpets, and the use of them will serve as a lasting statute for you throughout your generations.

9 “If you should go to war in your land against an oppressor who is harassing you, you should sound a war call on the trumpets, and you will be remembered by Jehovah your God and be saved from your enemies.

10 “Also, on your joyous occasions—your festivals and at the beginning of your months—you are to sound the trumpets over your burnt offerings and your communion sacrifices; they will serve as a reminder for you before your God. I am Jehovah your God.”

11 Now in the second year, in the second month, on the 20th day of the month, the cloud lifted from over the tabernacle of the Testimony. 12 So the Israelites began to pull away from the wilderness of Si′nai in the order established for their departure, and the cloud settled in the wilderness of Pa′ran. 13 This was the first time they departed following the order of Jehovah through Moses.

14 So the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of Judah departed first by their companies,[*] and Nah′shon the son of Am·min′a·dab was over its company. 15 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Is′sa·char was Ne·than′el the son of Zu′ar. 16 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Zeb′u·lun was E·li′ab the son of He′lon.

17 When the tabernacle was taken down, the sons of Ger′shon and the sons of Me·rar′i, who carried the tabernacle, departed.

18 Then the three-tribe division of the camp of Reu′ben departed by their companies,[*] and E·li′zur the son of Shed′e·ur was over its company. 19 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Sim′e·on was She·lu′mi·el the son of Zu·ri·shad′dai. 20 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Gad was E·li′a·saph the son of Deu′el.

21 Then the Ko′hath·ites, who carried the sanctuary items, departed. The tabernacle was to be set up by the time they arrived.

22 Then the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of E′phra·im departed by their companies,[*] and E·lish′a·ma the son of Am·mi′hud was over its company. 23 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Ma·nas′seh was Ga·ma′li·el the son of Pe·dah′zur. 24 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin was Ab′i·dan the son of Gid·e·o′ni.

25 Then the three-tribe division of the camp of the sons of Dan departed by their companies,[*] forming the rear guard for all the camps, and A·hi·e′zer the son of Am·mi·shad′dai was over its company. 26 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Ash′er was Pa′gi·el the son of Och′ran. 27 Over the company of the tribe of the sons of Naph′ta·li was A·hi′ra the son of E′nan. 28 This was the order of departure that the Israelites and their companies[*] followed when they would depart.

29 Then Moses said to Ho′bab the son of Reu′el[*] the Mid′i·an·ite, the father-in-law of Moses: “We are setting out for the place about which Jehovah said, ‘I will give it to you.’ Do come with us, and we will treat you well, because Jehovah has promised good things for Israel.” 30 But he said to him: “I will not go. I will return to my own country and to my relatives.” 31 At this he said: “Please do not leave us, for you know where we should camp in the wilderness, and you can serve as our guide.[*] 32 And if you do come with us, whatever goodness Jehovah shows to us, we will surely show to you.”

33 So they began marching from the mountain of Jehovah for a journey of three days, and the ark of Jehovah’s covenant traveled before them for the three-day journey to search out a resting-place for them. 34 And Jehovah’s cloud was over them by day when they set out from the encampment.

35 Whenever the Ark was moved, Moses would say: “Rise up, O Jehovah, and let your enemies be scattered, and let those who hate you flee from before you.” 36 And when it would rest, he would say: “Do return, O Jehovah, to the countless[*] thousands of Israel.”

^ Num. 10:14 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 10:18 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 10:22 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 10:25 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 10:28 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 10:29 That is, Jethro.

^ Num. 10:31 Or “eyes.”

^ Num. 10:36 Or “myriads of.”

Numbers  21 : 1 - 35

21 When the Ca′naan·ite king of A′rad, who dwelled in the Neg′eb, heard that Israel had come by the way of Ath′a·rim, he attacked Israel and carried away some of them as captives. 2 So Israel made this vow to Jehovah: “If you give this people into my hand, I will without fail devote their cities to destruction.” 3 So Jehovah listened to Israel’s voice and gave the Ca′naan·ites over to them, and they devoted them and their cities to destruction. Therefore, they named the place Hor′mah.[*]

4 As they continued their journey from Mount Hor by the way of the Red Sea in order to go around the land of E′dom, the people[*] became weary of the journey. 5 And the people kept speaking against God and Moses, saying: “Why have you brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness? There is no food and no water, and we[*] have come to hate[*] this contemptible bread.” 6 So Jehovah sent poisonous[*] serpents among the people, and they kept biting the people, so that many Israelites died.

7 So the people came to Moses and said: “We have sinned by speaking against Jehovah and against you. Intercede with Jehovah so that he may remove the serpents from us.” And Moses interceded on behalf of the people. 8 Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Make a replica of a poisonous[*] snake and put it on a pole. Then when anyone has been bitten, he will have to look at it in order to keep alive.” 9 Moses at once made a serpent of copper and put it on the pole, and whenever a serpent had bitten a man and he looked at the copper serpent, he survived.

10 After that the Israelites departed and camped in O′both. 11 Then they departed from O′both and camped in I′ye-ab′a·rim, in the wilderness that faces Mo′ab, toward the east. 12 From there they departed and camped by the Valley[*] of Ze′red. 13 From there they departed and camped in the region of the Ar′non, which is in the wilderness that extends from the border of the Am′or·ites, for the Ar′non is the boundary of Mo′ab, between Mo′ab and the Am′or·ites. 14 That is why the book of the Wars of Jehovah speaks of “Va′heb in Su′phah and the valleys[*] of Ar′non, 15 and the descent[*] of the valleys,[*] which extends toward the settlement of Ar and adjoins the border of Mo′ab.”

16 Next they went on to Be′er. This is the well about which Jehovah said to Moses: “Gather the people, and let me give them water.”

17 At that time, Israel sang this song:

“Spring up, O well!—Respond[*] to it!

18 The well that princes dug, that nobles of the people excavated,

With a commander’s staff and with their own staffs.”

Then they went from the wilderness on to Mat′ta·nah, 19 from Mat′ta·nah on to Na·hal′i·el, and from Na·hal′i·el on to Ba′moth. 20 They went from Ba′moth on to the valley that is in the territory[*] of Mo′ab, on top of Pis′gah, which overlooks Je·shi′mon.[*]

21 Israel now sent messengers to Si′hon, the king of the Am′or·ites, saying: 22 “Let us pass through your land. We will not turn aside into a field or a vineyard. We will not drink water from any well. We will march on the King’s Road until we pass through your territory.” 23 But Si′hon did not allow Israel to pass through his territory. Instead, Si′hon gathered all his people and went out against Israel in the wilderness and came to Ja′haz and began fighting with Israel. 24 But Israel defeated him with the sword and took possession of his land from the Ar′non to the Jab′bok, near the Am′mon·ites, because Ja′zer borders the territory of the Am′mon·ites.

25 So Israel took all these cities, and they began dwelling in all the cities of the Am′or·ites, in Hesh′bon and all its dependent[*] towns. 26 For Hesh′bon was the city of Si′hon, the king of the Am′or·ites, who had fought with the king of Mo′ab and taken all his land from him as far as the Ar′non. 27 That is what gave rise to the taunting proverbial saying:

“Come to Hesh′bon.

Let the city of Si′hon be built and firmly established.

28 For a fire came out of Hesh′bon, a flame from the town of Si′hon.

It has consumed Ar of Mo′ab, the lords of the high places of the Ar′non.

29 Woe to you, Mo′ab! You will be destroyed, O people of Che′mosh!

He makes his sons fugitives and his daughters captives of Si′hon, the king of the Am′or·ites.

30 Let us shoot at them;

Hesh′bon will be destroyed as far as Di′bon;

Let us desolate it as far as No′phah;

Fire will spread as far as Med′e·ba.”

31 So Israel began to dwell in the land of the Am′or·ites. 32 Moses then sent some men to spy on Ja′zer. They captured its dependent[*] towns and drove out the Am′or·ites who were there. 33 After that they turned and went up by way of Ba′shan. And Og the king of Ba′shan came out with all his people to meet them in battle at Ed′re·i. 34 Jehovah said to Moses: “Do not be afraid of him, for I will give him and all his people and his land into your hand, and you will do to him just as you did to Si′hon the king of the Am′or·ites, who lived in Hesh′bon.” 35 So they kept striking him down, along with his sons and all his people, until none of his people survived, and they took possession of his land.

^ Num. 21:3 Meaning “A Devoting to Destruction.”

^ Num. 21:4 Or “the soul of the people.”

^ Num. 21:5 Or “our souls.”

^ Num. 21:5 Or “abhor.”

^ Num. 21:6 Or “fiery.”

^ Num. 21:8 Or “fiery.”

^ Num. 21:12 Or “Wadi.”

^ Num. 21:14 Or “wadis.”

^ Num. 21:15 Lit., “mouth.”

^ Num. 21:15 Or “wadis.”

^ Num. 21:17 Or “Sing.”

^ Num. 21:20 Lit., “field.”

^ Num. 21:20 Or possibly, “the desert; the wilderness.”

^ Num. 21:25 Or “surrounding.”

^ Num. 21:32 Or “surrounding.”

Numbers  22 : 1 - 41

22 Then the Israelites departed and camped on the desert plains of Mo′ab across the Jordan from Jer′i·cho. 2 Now Ba′lak the son of Zip′por saw all that Israel had done to the Am′or·ites, 3 and Mo′ab became very frightened of the people, because they were so many; indeed, Mo′ab felt sick with fear because of the Israelites. 4 So Mo′ab said to the elders of Mid′i·an: “Now this congregation will devour all our surroundings, just as a bull devours the grass in the field.”

Ba′lak the son of Zip′por was king of Mo′ab at that time. 5 He sent messengers to Ba′laam the son of Be′or at Pe′thor, which is by the River[*] in his native land. He summoned him, saying: “Look! A people has come out of Egypt. Look! They have covered the face[*] of the earth,[*] and they are dwelling right in front of me. 6 Now, please, come and curse this people for me, for they are mightier than I am. Perhaps I can defeat them and drive them out of the land, for I well know that the one whom you bless is blessed and the one whom you curse is cursed.”

7 So the elders of Mo′ab and the elders of Mid′i·an traveled with the fee for divination in their hands and went to Ba′laam and conveyed to him Ba′lak’s message. 8 At that he said to them: “Spend the night here, and I will bring back to you whatever word Jehovah speaks to me.” So the princes of Mo′ab stayed with Ba′laam.

9 Then God came to Ba′laam and said: “Who are these men with you?” 10 Ba′laam said to the true God: “Ba′lak the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab, has sent me a message, saying, 11 ‘Look! The people who are coming out of Egypt are covering the face[*] of the earth.[*] Now come and put a curse on them for me. Perhaps I may be able to fight against them and drive them out.’” 12 But God said to Ba′laam: “You must not go with them. You must not curse the people, for they are blessed.”

13 Ba′laam got up in the morning and said to the princes of Ba′lak: “Go to your land, for Jehovah has refused to let me go with you.” 14 So the princes of Mo′ab departed and returned to Ba′lak and said: “Ba′laam has refused to come with us.”

15 However, Ba′lak again sent princes, more numerous and more distinguished than the first group. 16 They came to Ba′laam and said to him: “This is what Ba′lak the son of Zip′por has said, ‘Please do not let anything hinder you from coming to me, 17 for I will honor you greatly and I will do anything you tell me to do. So come, please, and curse this people for me.’” 18 But Ba′laam answered the servants of Ba′lak: “If Ba′lak were to give me his own house full of silver and gold, I could not do anything beyond the order of Jehovah my God, whether small or great. 19 But please stay here tonight also, so that I may learn what else Jehovah will tell me.”

20 Then God came to Ba′laam by night and said to him: “If these men have come to summon you, go along with them. But you may speak only the words that I tell you to say.” 21 So Ba′laam got up in the morning and saddled his donkey[*] and went with the princes of Mo′ab.

22 But God’s anger blazed because he was going, and Jehovah’s angel stationed himself in the road to resist him. Now Ba′laam was riding on his donkey, and two of his attendants were with him. 23 And when the donkey saw Jehovah’s angel standing in the road with a drawn sword in his hand, it tried to turn off the road into the field. But Ba′laam began to beat the donkey to make it return to the road. 24 Then Jehovah’s angel stood in a narrow path between two vineyards, with stone walls on both sides. 25 When the donkey saw Jehovah’s angel, it began to squeeze itself against the wall and it jammed Ba′laam’s foot against the wall, and Ba′laam began beating it again.

26 Jehovah’s angel now passed by again and stood in a narrow place where there was no way to turn to the right or to the left. 27 When the donkey saw Jehovah’s angel, it lay down under Ba′laam, so Ba′laam became furious and kept beating the donkey with his staff. 28 Finally Jehovah caused the donkey to speak,[*] and it said to Ba′laam: “What have I done to you to make you beat me these three times?” 29 Ba′laam replied to the donkey: “It is because you have made a fool of me. If only I had a sword in my hand, I would kill you!” 30 Then the donkey said to Ba′laam: “Am I not your donkey that you have ridden on all your life until today? Have I ever treated you this way before?” He replied: “No!” 31 Then Jehovah uncovered Ba′laam’s eyes, and he saw Jehovah’s angel standing in the road with a drawn sword in his hand. At once he bowed low and prostrated himself on his face.

32 Then Jehovah’s angel said to him: “Why have you beaten your donkey these three times? Look! I myself came out to offer resistance, because your way is in defiance of my will. 33 The donkey saw me and tried to turn away from me these three times. Supposing it had not turned away from me! By now I would have killed you and let the donkey live.” 34 Ba′laam said to Jehovah’s angel: “I have sinned, because I did not know that it was you standing in the road to meet me. And now if it is bad in your eyes, I will go back.” 35 But Jehovah’s angel said to Ba′laam: “Go with the men, but you may speak only the words that I tell you.” So Ba′laam continued going with the princes of Ba′lak.

36 When Ba′lak heard that Ba′laam had come, he immediately went out to meet him at the city of Mo′ab, which is on the bank of the Ar′non on the border of the territory. 37 Ba′lak said to Ba′laam: “Did I not send for you? Why did you not come to me? Did you think I am not able to honor you greatly?” 38 Ba′laam replied to Ba′lak: “Well, I have come to you now. But will I be allowed to say anything? I can only speak words that God puts in my mouth.”

39 So Ba′laam went with Ba′lak, and they came to Kir′i·ath-hu′zoth. 40 Ba′lak sacrificed cattle and sheep and sent some to Ba′laam and the princes who were with him. 41 In the morning Ba′lak took Ba′laam and brought him up to Ba′moth-ba′al; from there he could see all the people.

^ Num. 22:5 Evidently, the Euphrates.

^ Num. 22:5 Lit., “eye.”

^ Num. 22:5 Or “land.”

^ Num. 22:11 Lit., “eye.”

^ Num. 22:11 Or “land.”

^ Num. 22:21 Lit., “female donkey.”

^ Num. 22:28 Lit., “opened the mouth of the female donkey.”

Numbers  26 : 1 - 65

26 After the scourge, Jehovah said to Moses and El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron the priest: 2 “Take a census of the whole assembly of the Israelites from 20 years of age and up, by their paternal houses, counting all those who can serve in the army in Israel.” 3 So Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest spoke with them in the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, saying: 4 “Take a census of them from the age of 20 years and up, just as Jehovah commanded Moses.”

Now the sons of Israel who went out of the land of Egypt were: 5 Reu′ben, Israel’s firstborn; Reu′ben’s sons were: of Ha′noch, the family of the Ha′noch·ites; of Pal′lu, the family of the Pal′lu·ites; 6 of Hez′ron, the family of the Hez′ron·ites; of Car′mi, the family of the Car′mites. 7 These were the families of the Reu′ben·ites, and their registered ones amounted to 43,730.

8 The son of Pal′lu was E·li′ab. 9 And the sons of E·li′ab were Nem′u·el, Da′than, and A·bi′ram. This Da′than and A·bi′ram were chosen ones of the assembly who fought against Moses and Aaron along with Kor′ah’s group when they fought against Jehovah.

10 Then the earth opened[*] and swallowed them up. As for Kor′ah, he died with his supporters when the fire consumed 250 men. And they became a warning example. 11 However, the sons of Kor′ah did not die.

12 The sons of Sim′e·on by their families were: of Nem′u·el, the family of the Nem′u·el·ites; of Ja′min, the family of the Ja′min·ites; of Ja′chin, the family of the Ja′chin·ites; 13 of Ze′rah, the family of the Ze′rah·ites; of Sha′ul, the family of the Sha·u′lites. 14 These were the families of the Sim′e·on·ites: 22,200.

15 The sons of Gad by their families were: of Ze′phon, the family of the Ze′phon·ites; of Hag′gi, the family of the Hag′gites; of Shu′ni, the family of the Shu′nites; 16 of Oz′ni, the family of the Oz′nites; of E′ri, the family of the E′rites; 17 of Ar′od, the family of the Ar′od·ites; of A·re′li, the family of the A·re′lites. 18 These were the families of the sons of Gad, and their registered ones were 40,500.

19 The sons of Judah were Er and O′nan. However, Er and O′nan died in the land of Ca′naan. 20 And the sons of Judah by their families were: of She′lah, the family of the She·la′nites; of Pe′rez, the family of the Per′e·zites; of Ze′rah, the family of the Ze′rah·ites. 21 And the sons of Pe′rez were: of Hez′ron, the family of the Hez′ron·ites; of Ha′mul, the family of the Ha·mu′lites. 22 These were the families of Judah, and their registered ones were 76,500.

23 The sons of Is′sa·char by their families were: of To′la, the family of the To′la·ites; of Pu′vah, the family of the Pu′nites; 24 of Ja′shub, the family of the Jash′u·bites; of Shim′ron, the family of the Shim′ron·ites. 25 These were the families of Is′sa·char, and their registered ones were 64,300.

26 The sons of Zeb′u·lun by their families were: of Se′red, the family of the Ser′e·dites; of E′lon, the family of the E′lon·ites; of Jah′le·el, the family of the Jah′le·el·ites. 27 These were the families of the Ze·bu′lu·nites, and their registered ones were 60,500.

28 The sons of Joseph by their families were: Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im. 29 The sons of Ma·nas′seh were: of Ma′chir, the family of the Ma′chir·ites; and Ma′chir became father to Gil′e·ad; of Gil′e·ad, the family of the Gil′e·ad·ites. 30 These were the sons of Gil′e·ad: of Ie′zer, the family of the Ie′zer·ites; of He′lek, the family of the He′lek·ites; 31 of As′ri·el, the family of the As′ri·el·ites; of She′chem, the family of the She′chem·ites; 32 of She·mi′da, the family of the She·mi′da·ites; of He′pher, the family of the He′pher·ites. 33 Now Ze·lo′phe·had the son of He′pher had no sons, only daughters, and the names of the daughters of Ze·lo′phe·had were Mah′lah, Noah, Hog′lah, Mil′cah, and Tir′zah. 34 These were the families of Ma·nas′seh, and their registered ones were 52,700.

35 These were the sons of E′phra·im by their families: of Shu′the·lah, the family of the Shu′thel·a′hites; of Be′cher, the family of the Be′cher·ites; of Ta′han, the family of the Ta′han·ites. 36 And these were the sons of Shu′the·lah: of E′ran, the family of the E′ran·ites. 37 These were the families of the sons of E′phra·im, and their registered ones were 32,500. These were the sons of Joseph by their families.

38 The sons of Benjamin by their families were: of Be′la, the family of the Be′la·ites; of Ash′bel, the family of the Ash′bel·ites; of A·hi′ram, the family of the A·hi′ram·ites; 39 of She·phu′pham, the family of the Shu′pham·ites; of Hu′pham, the family of the Hu′pham·ites. 40 The sons of Be′la were Ard and Na′a·man: of Ard, the family of the Ard′ites; of Na′a·man, the family of the Na′a·mites. 41 These were the sons of Benjamin by their families, and their registered ones were 45,600.

42 These were the sons of Dan by their families: of Shu′ham, the family of the Shu′ham·ites. These were the families of Dan by their families. 43 All the families of the Shu′ham·ites, of their registered ones, were 64,400.

44 The sons of Ash′er by their families were: of Im′nah, the family of the Im′nites; of Ish′vi, the family of the Ish′vites; of Be·ri′ah, the family of the Be·ri′ites; 45 of the sons of Be·ri′ah: of He′ber, the family of the He′ber·ites; of Mal′chi·el, the family of the Mal′chi·el·ites. 46 The name of Ash′er’s daughter was Se′rah. 47 These were the families of the sons of Ash′er, and their registered ones were 53,400.

48 The sons of Naph′ta·li by their families were: of Jah′ze·el, the family of the Jah′ze·el·ites; of Gu′ni, the family of the Gu′nites; 49 of Je′zer, the family of the Je′zer·ites; of Shil′lem, the family of the Shil′lem·ites. 50 These were the families of Naph′ta·li by their families, and their registered ones were 45,400.

51 This is the total of those registered of the Israelites: 601,730.

52 After that Jehovah said to Moses: 53 “Among these the land should be divided as an inheritance according to the list of the names.[*] 54 For the larger groups, you should increase the inheritance, and for the smaller groups, you should reduce the inheritance. Each group’s inheritance should be given in proportion to the number of those registered. 55 However, the land should be apportioned by lot. They should receive their inheritance according to the names of the tribes of their fathers. 56 Each inheritance will be determined by lot and apportioned among the larger and the smaller groups.”

57 Now these were the registered ones of the Levites by their families: of Ger′shon, the family of the Ger′shon·ites; of Ko′hath, the family of the Ko′hath·ites; of Me·rar′i, the family of the Me·rar′ites. 58 These were the families of the Levites: the family of the Lib′nites, the family of the Heb′ron·ites, the family of the Mah′lites, the family of the Mu′shites, the family of the Kor′ah·ites.

Ko′hath became father to Am′ram. 59 And the name of Am′ram’s wife was Joch′e·bed, Le′vi’s daughter, whom his wife bore to Le′vi in Egypt. And to Am′ram she bore Aaron and Moses and their sister Mir′i·am. 60 Then to Aaron there were born Na′dab, A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar, and Ith′a·mar. 61 But Na′dab and A·bi′hu died for presenting unauthorized fire before Jehovah.

62 The total of those registered was 23,000, all males from a month old and up. For they were not registered among the Israelites, because no inheritance was to be given to them among the Israelites.

63 These were the ones registered by Moses and El·e·a′zar the priest when they registered the Israelites in the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho. 64 But among them there was no one who had been registered by Moses and Aaron the priest in the census of the Israelites taken in the wilderness of Si′nai. 65 For Jehovah had said concerning them: “They will die without fail in the wilderness.” So there was not a man left of them except Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh and Joshua the son of Nun.

^ Num. 26:10 Lit., “opened its mouth.”

^ Num. 26:53 Or “proportionate to the number of names listed.”

Numbers  33 : 1 - 56

33 These were the stages of the journey of the people of Israel when they went out of the land of Egypt by their companies[*] under the direction of Moses and Aaron. 2 Moses kept recording the departure places by the stages of their journey at the order of Jehovah, and these were their stages from one departure place to another: 3 They departed from Ram′e·ses in the first month, on the 15th day of the month. On the very day after the Passover, the Israelites went out with confidence[*] before the eyes of all the Egyptians. 4 Meanwhile, the Egyptians were burying all the firstborn whom Jehovah had struck down among them, for Jehovah had executed judgments on their gods.

5 So the Israelites departed from Ram′e·ses and camped at Suc′coth. 6 Then they departed from Suc′coth and camped at E′tham, which is on the edge of the wilderness. 7 Next they departed from E′tham and turned back toward Pi·ha·hi′roth, which is in view of Ba′al-ze′phon, and they camped before Mig′dol. 8 After that they departed from Pi·ha·hi′roth and passed through the midst of the sea to the wilderness and kept marching a three-day journey in the wilderness of E′tham and camped at Ma′rah.

9 Then they departed from Ma′rah and came to E′lim. Now in E′lim there were 12 springs of water and 70 palm trees, so they camped there. 10 Next they departed from E′lim and camped by the Red Sea. 11 After that they departed from the Red Sea and camped in the wilderness of Sin. 12 Then they departed from the wilderness of Sin and camped at Doph′kah. 13 Later they departed from Doph′kah and camped at A′lush. 14 They next departed from A′lush and camped at Reph′i·dim, where there was no water for the people to drink. 15 After that they departed from Reph′i·dim and camped in the wilderness of Si′nai.

16 They departed from the wilderness of Si′nai and camped at Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah. 17 Then they departed from Kib′roth-hat·ta′a·vah and camped at Ha·ze′roth. 18 After that they departed from Ha·ze′roth and camped at Rith′mah. 19 Next they departed from Rith′mah and camped at Rim′mon-pe′rez. 20 Then they departed from Rim′mon-pe′rez and camped at Lib′nah. 21 They departed from Lib′nah and camped at Ris′sah. 22 Next they departed from Ris′sah and camped at Ke·he·la′thah. 23 Then they departed from Ke·he·la′thah and camped at Mount She′pher.

24 After that they departed from Mount She′pher and camped at Har·a′dah. 25 Then they departed from Har·a′dah and camped at Mak·he′loth. 26 Next they departed from Mak·he′loth and camped at Ta′hath. 27 After that they departed from Ta′hath and camped at Te′rah. 28 Then they departed from Te′rah and camped at Mith′kah. 29 Later they departed from Mith′kah and camped at Hash·mo′nah. 30 Next they departed from Hash·mo′nah and camped at Mo·se′roth. 31 Then they departed from Mo·se′roth and camped at Ben′e-ja′a·kan. 32 And they departed from Ben′e-ja′a·kan and camped at Hor-hag·gid′gad. 33 Next they departed from Hor-hag·gid′gad and camped at Jot′ba·thah. 34 Later they departed from Jot′ba·thah and camped at A·bro′nah. 35 Then they departed from A·bro′nah and camped at E′zi·on-ge′ber. 36 After that they departed from E′zi·on-ge′ber and camped in the wilderness of Zin, that is, Ka′desh.

37 Later they departed from Ka′desh and camped at Mount Hor, on the frontier of the land of E′dom. 38 And Aaron the priest went up into Mount Hor at the order of Jehovah and died there in the 40th year after the Israelites left the land of Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first of the month. 39 Aaron was 123 years old at his death on Mount Hor.

40 Now the king of A′rad, the Ca′naan·ite who was dwelling in the Neg′eb in the land of Ca′naan, heard about the coming of the Israelites.

41 In time they departed from Mount Hor and camped at Zal·mo′nah. 42 After that they departed from Zal·mo′nah and camped at Pu′non. 43 Next they departed from Pu′non and camped at O′both. 44 Then they departed from O′both and camped at I′ye-ab′a·rim, on the border of Mo′ab. 45 Later they departed from I′yim and camped at Di′bon-gad. 46 After that they departed from Di′bon-gad and camped at Al′mon-dib·la·tha′im. 47 Then they departed from Al′mon-dib·la·tha′im and camped in the mountains of Ab′a·rim before Ne′bo. 48 Finally they departed from the mountains of Ab′a·rim and camped on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho. 49 They continued camping along the Jordan, from Beth-jesh′i·moth as far as A′bel-shit′tim, on the desert plains of Mo′ab.

50 Jehovah spoke to Moses on the desert plains of Mo′ab by the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, saying: 51 “Speak to the Israelites and tell them, ‘You are crossing the Jordan into the land of Ca′naan. 52 You must drive away all the inhabitants of the land from before you and destroy all their carvings of stone and all their metal statues,[*] and you should demolish all their sacred high places. 53 And you will take possession of the land and dwell in it, because I will certainly give you the land as a possession. 54 You must apportion the land by lot as a possession among your families. To the larger group you should increase his inheritance, and to the smaller group you should reduce his inheritance. Everyone’s inheritance will be where his lot falls. You will receive your property as an inheritance by the tribes of your fathers.

55 “‘If, though, you do not drive the inhabitants of the land away from before you, those whom you allow to remain will be as irritants in your eyes and thorns in your sides, and they will harass you in the land where you will dwell. 56 And I will do to you what I intended to do to them.’”

^ Num. 33:1 Lit., “according to their armies.”

^ Num. 33:3 Lit., “with uplifted hand.”

^ Num. 33:52 Or “molten statues.”

Deuteronomy  2 : 1 - 37

2 “Then we turned and departed for the wilderness by the way of the Red Sea, just as Jehovah had told me, and we traveled for many days around Mount Se′ir. 2 Finally Jehovah said to me, 3 ‘You have gone around this mountain long enough. Now turn north. 4 And give this command to the people: “You will pass by the border of your brothers, the descendants of E′sau, who are dwelling in Se′ir, and they will be afraid of you, and you must be very careful. 5 Do not engage in hostilities with[*] them, for I will not give you any of their land, not even the space of a footprint, because I have given Mount Se′ir to E′sau as his possession. 6 You should give them money for the food you will eat, and you should pay for the water you will drink. 7 For Jehovah your God has blessed you in all that you have done. He is fully aware of your walking through this great wilderness. These 40 years Jehovah your God has been with you, and you have lacked nothing.”’ 8 So we passed by our brothers, the descendants of E′sau, who are dwelling in Se′ir, keeping away from the way of the Ar′a·bah, from E′lath and from E′zi·on-ge′ber.

“Next we turned and traveled by the way of the wilderness of Mo′ab. 9 Jehovah then said to me, ‘Do not engage in hostilities or in war with Mo′ab, for I will not give you any of his land as a possession because I have given Ar as a possession to the descendants of Lot. 10 (The E′mim formerly lived there, a people great and numerous and tall like the An′a·kim. 11 The Reph′a·im were also considered like the An′a·kim, and the Mo′ab·ites used to call them E′mim. 12 Previously, the Hor′ites were living in Se′ir, but the descendants of E′sau dispossessed and annihilated them and settled in their place, just as Israel will do to the land that is their possession, which Jehovah will certainly give to them.) 13 Now go and cross over the Valley[*] of Ze′red.’ So we crossed over the Valley[*] of Ze′red. 14 The time it took us to walk from Ka′desh-bar′ne·a until we crossed the Valley[*] of Ze′red was 38 years, until the entire generation of the men of war had perished from the camp, just as Jehovah had sworn to them. 15 Jehovah’s hand was against them to eliminate them from the camp until they had perished.

16 “As soon as all the men of war had died off from among the people, 17 Jehovah spoke to me again, saying, 18 ‘Today you are to pass by the territory of Mo′ab, that is, Ar. 19 When you come near to the Am′mon·ites, do not harass or provoke them, for I will not give you any of the land of the Am′monites as a possession, because I have given it to the descendants of Lot as their possession. 20 This too used to be considered the land of the Reph′a·im. (The Reph′a·im formerly lived there, and the Am′mon·ites used to call them Zam·zum′mim. 21 They were a great and numerous and tall people like the An′a·kim; but Jehovah annihilated them before the Am′monites, and these drove them out and settled in their place. 22 That is what he did for the descendants of E′sau, who now dwell in Se′ir, when he annihilated the Hor′ites from before them, so that they could dispossess them and dwell in their place to this very day. 23 As for the Av′vim, they had dwelled in settlements as far as Gaz′a until the Caph′to·rim, who came out from Caph′tor,[*] annihilated them and settled in their place.)

24 “‘Get up, and make your way across the Ar′non Valley.[*] See, I have given into your hand Si′hon the Am′or·ite, king of Hesh′bon. So begin taking possession of his land, and engage him in war. 25 This day I will start to put the dread and the fear of you upon all the people under the heavens who hear the report about you. They will be disturbed and will tremble[*] because of you.’

26 “Then I sent messengers from the wilderness of Ked′e·moth to King Si′hon of Hesh′bon, with these peaceful words, 27 ‘Let me pass through your land. I will remain on the road and not turn to the right or to the left. 28 I will eat only the food and drink only the water that you will sell to me. Just allow me to pass through on foot 29 —that is what the descendants of E′sau dwelling in Se′ir and the Mo′ab·ites dwelling in Ar did for me—until I pass over the Jordan into the land that Jehovah our God is giving to us.’ 30 But King Si′hon of Hesh′bon did not let us pass through, because Jehovah your God allowed his spirit to become obstinate and his heart to become hard, in order to give him into your hand as is now the case.

31 “Then Jehovah said to me, ‘See, I have already begun to give Si′hon and his land over to you. Start to take possession of his land.’ 32 When Si′hon came out along with all his people to meet us in battle at Ja′haz, 33 Jehovah our God handed him over to us, so that we defeated him, his sons, and all his people. 34 We captured all his cities at that time and devoted every city to destruction, including men, women, and children. We left no survivor. 35 We plundered only the livestock for ourselves along with the spoils from the cities that we had captured. 36 From A·ro′er, which is on the rim of the Ar′non Valley[*] (including the city that is in the valley), as far as Gil′e·ad, no town was beyond our reach. Jehovah our God handed them all over to us. 37 However, you did not approach the land of the Am′mon·ites, the whole bank of the Valley[*] of Jab′bok and the cities of the mountainous region, or any other place forbidden by Jehovah our God.

^ Deut. 2:5 Or “Do not provoke.”

^ Deut. 2:13 Or “Wadi.”

^ Deut. 2:13 Or “Wadi.”

^ Deut. 2:14 Or “Wadi.”

^ Deut. 2:23 That is, Crete.

^ Deut. 2:24 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Deut. 2:25 Or “have pains like those of childbirth.”

^ Deut. 2:36 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Deut. 2:37 Or “Wadi.”

Joshua  12 : 1 - 24

12 Now these are the kings of the land whom the Israelites defeated, whose land they took possession of on the east side of the Jordan, from the Ar′non Valley[*] up to Mount Her′mon and all the Ar′a·bah toward the east: 2 King Si′hon of the Am′or·ites, who lived in Hesh′bon and ruled from A·ro′er, which was on the rim of the Ar′non Valley,[*] and from the middle of the valley, and half of Gil′e·ad as far as the Valley[*] of Jab′bok, the boundary of the Am′mon·ites. 3 He also ruled over the Ar′a·bah as far as the Sea of Chin′ne·reth[*] toward the east and as far as the Sea of the Ar′a·bah, the Salt Sea,[*] to the east in the direction of Beth-jesh′i·moth, and toward the south under the slopes of Pis′gah.

4 Also the territory of King Og of Ba′shan, who was one of the last of the Reph′a·im and who lived in Ash′ta·roth and Ed′re·i 5 and ruled in Mount Her′mon, in Sal′e·cah, and in all Ba′shan, as far as the boundary of the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites, and half of Gil′e·ad, to the territory of King Si′hon of Hesh′bon.

6 Moses the servant of Jehovah and the Israelites defeated them, after which Moses the servant of Jehovah gave their land as a possession to the Reu′ben·ites, the Gad′ites, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh.

7 These are the kings of the land whom Joshua and the Israelites defeated on the west side of the Jordan, from Ba′al-gad in the Valley of Leb′a·non and as far as Mount Ha′lak, which goes up to Se′ir, after which Joshua gave their land to the tribes of Israel as a possession by their shares, 8 in the mountainous region, in the She·phe′lah, in the Ar′a·bah, on the slopes, in the wilderness, and in the Neg′eb—the land of the Hit′tites, the Am′or·ites, the Ca′naan·ites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites:

 9 The king of Jer′i·cho, one; the king of A′i, which was beside Beth′el, one;

10 the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Heb′ron, one;

11 the king of Jar′muth, one; the king of La′chish, one;

12 the king of Eg′lon, one; the king of Ge′zer, one;

13 the king of De′bir, one; the king of Ge′der, one;

14 the king of Hor′mah, one; the king of A′rad, one;

15 the king of Lib′nah, one; the king of A·dul′lam, one;

16 the king of Mak·ke′dah, one; the king of Beth′el, one;

17 the king of Tap′pu·ah, one; the king of He′pher, one;

18 the king of A′phek, one; the king of Las·shar′on, one;

19 the king of Ma′don, one; the king of Ha′zor, one;

20 the king of Shim′ron-me′ron, one; the king of Ach′shaph, one;

21 the king of Ta′a·nach, one; the king of Me·gid′do, one;

22 the king of Ke′desh, one; the king of Jok′ne·am in Car′mel, one;

23 the king of Dor on the slopes of Dor, one; the king of Goi′im in Gil′gal, one;

24 the king of Tir′zah, one; a total of 31 kings.

^ Josh. 12:1 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Josh. 12:2 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Josh. 12:2 Or “Wadi.”

^ Josh. 12:3 That is, the lake of Gennesaret, or the Sea of Galilee.

^ Josh. 12:3 That is, the Dead Sea.

Joshua  13 : 1 - 33

13 Now Joshua had grown old and was advanced in years. So Jehovah said to him: “You have grown old and are advanced in years; but much of the land remains to be taken in possession.[*] 2 This is the land remaining: all the regions of the Phi·lis′tines and all the Gesh′ur·ites 3 (from the branch of the Nile[*] that is east of[*] Egypt up to the border of Ek′ron to the north, which used to be considered Ca′naan·ite territory) including that of the five lords of the Phi·lis′tines—the Gaz′ites, the Ash′dod·ites, the Ash′ke·lon·ites, the Git′tites, and the Ek′ron·ites; that of the Av′vim 4 to the south; all the land of the Ca′naan·ites; Me·ar′ah, which belongs to the Si·do′ni·ans, as far as A′phek, to the border of the Am′or·ites; 5 the land of the Ge′bal·ites and all of Leb′a·non toward the east, from Ba′al-gad at the base of Mount Her′mon to Le′bo-ha′math;[*] 6 all the inhabitants of the mountainous region from Leb′a·non to Mis′re·photh-ma′im; and all the Si·do′ni·ans. I will drive them out[*] before the Israelites. You have only to assign it to Israel as an inheritance, just as I have commanded you. 7 Now you must apportion this land as an inheritance to the nine tribes and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh.”

8 With the other half tribe, the Reu′ben·ites and the Gad′ites took their inheritance that Moses gave them on the east side of the Jordan, just as Moses the servant of Jehovah had given them: 9 from A·ro′er, which is on the rim of the Ar′non Valley,[*] and the city that is in the middle of the valley, and all the tableland[*] of Med′e·ba as far as Di′bon; 10 and all the cities of King Si′hon of the Am′or·ites, who reigned in Hesh′bon, up to the border of the Am′mon·ites; 11 also Gil′e·ad and the territory of the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites and all Mount Her′mon and all Ba′shan as far as Sal′e·cah; 12 all the royal realm of Og in Ba′shan, who reigned in Ash′ta·roth and in Ed′re·i. (He was one of the last of the Reph′a·im.) Moses defeated them and drove them out.[*] 13 But the Israelites did not drive out[*] the Gesh′ur·ites and the Ma·ac′a·thites, for Gesh′ur and Ma′a·cath live in the midst of Israel to this day.

14 It was only to the tribe of the Levites that he did not give an inheritance. The offerings made by fire to Jehovah the God of Israel are their inheritance, just as he promised them.

15 Then Moses gave an inheritance to the tribe of the Reu′ben·ites by their families, 16 and their territory was from A·ro′er, which is on the rim of the Ar′non Valley,[*] and the city in the middle of the valley, and all the tableland by Med′e·ba; 17 Hesh′bon and all its towns on the tableland, Di′bon, Ba′moth-ba′al, Beth-ba′al-me′on, 18 Ja′haz, Ked′e·moth, Meph′a·ath, 19 Kir·i·a·tha′im, Sib′mah, and Ze′reth-sha′har on the mountain of the valley,[*] 20 Beth-pe′or, the slopes of Pis′gah, Beth-jesh′i·moth, 21 all the cities of the tableland, and all the royal realm of King Si′hon of the Am′or·ites, who reigned in Hesh′bon. Moses defeated him and the Mid′i·an·ite chieftains E′vi, Re′kem, Zur, Hur, and Re′ba, vassals[*] of Si′hon who were dwelling in the land. 22 Ba′laam the son of Be′or, the diviner, was one whom the Israelites killed with the sword along with the rest who were slain. 23 The boundary of the Reu′ben·ites was the Jordan; and this territory was the inheritance of the Reu′ben·ites by their families, with the cities and their settlements.

24 Furthermore, Moses gave an inheritance to the tribe of Gad, the Gad′ites by their families, 25 and their territory included Ja′zer and all the cities of Gil′e·ad and half of the land of the Am′mon·ites as far as A·ro′er, which faces Rab′bah; 26 and from Hesh′bon to Ra′math-miz′peh and Bet′o·nim, and from Ma·ha·na′im to the border of De′bir; 27 and in the valley,[*] Beth-ha′ram, Beth-nim′rah, Suc′coth, and Za′phon, the rest of the royal realm of King Si′hon of Hesh′bon, with the Jordan as the border from the lower end of the Sea of Chin′ne·reth[*] on the east side of the Jordan. 28 This was the inheritance of the Gad′ites by their families, with the cities and their settlements.

29 Further, Moses gave an inheritance to the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, to half of the tribe of Ma·nas′seh by their families. 30 And their territory extended from Ma·ha·na′im and took in all of Ba′shan, all the royal realm of King Og of Ba′shan, and all the tent villages of Ja′ir in Ba′shan, 60 towns. 31 And half of Gil′e·ad, and Ash′ta·roth and Ed′re·i, the cities of the royal realm of Og in Ba′shan, went to the sons of Ma′chir the son of Ma·nas′seh, to half of the sons of Ma′chir by their families.

32 These were the inheritances that Moses gave them on the desert plains of Mo′ab beyond the Jordan, east of Jer′i·cho.

33 But to the tribe of the Levites, Moses did not give an inheritance. Jehovah the God of Israel is their inheritance, just as he promised them.

^ Josh. 13:1 Or “be conquered.”

^ Josh. 13:3 Or “from Shihor.”

^ Josh. 13:3 Lit., “in front of.”

^ Josh. 13:5 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ Josh. 13:6 Or “dispossess them.”

^ Josh. 13:9 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Josh. 13:9 Or “plateau.”

^ Josh. 13:12 Or “dispossessed them.”

^ Josh. 13:13 Or “dispossess.”

^ Josh. 13:16 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ Josh. 13:19 Or “low plain.”

^ Josh. 13:21 That is, kings who were subject to Sihon.

^ Josh. 13:27 Or “low plain.”

^ Josh. 13:27 That is, the lake of Gennesaret, or the Sea of Galilee.

Joshua  16 : 1 - 10

16 And the land that fell by lot[*] to the descendants of Joseph was from the Jordan at Jer′i·cho to the waters east of Jer′i·cho, through the wilderness going up from Jer′i·cho into the mountainous region of Beth′el. 2 It extended from Beth′el belonging to Luz and continued to the boundary of the Ar′chites at At′a·roth, 3 then it went down westward to the boundary of the Japh′le·tites as far as the boundary of Lower Beth-ho′ron and Ge′zer, and it ended at the sea.

4 So Joseph’s descendants, Ma·nas′seh and E′phra·im, took possession of their land. 5 The boundary of the descendants of E′phra·im by their families was as follows: The boundary of their inheritance to the east was At′a·roth-ad′dar, as far as Upper Beth-ho′ron, 6 and the boundary extended to the sea. Mich·me′thath was on the north, and the boundary went around east to Ta′a·nath-shi′loh, and it passed on the east to Ja·no′ah. 7 Then it went down from Ja·no′ah to At′a·roth and Na′a·rah and reached to Jer′i·cho and extended to the Jordan. 8 From Tap′pu·ah the boundary continued westward to the Wadi of Ka′nah, and it ended at the sea. This is the inheritance of the tribe of E′phra·im by their families; 9 the descendants of E′phra·im also had enclave cities in the midst of the inheritance of Ma·nas′seh, all the cities and their settlements.

10 But they did not drive away the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Ge′zer, and the Ca′naan·ites continue to dwell among E′phra·im to this day and have been subjected to forced labor.

^ Josh. 16:1 Or “was allotted.”

Joshua  17 : 1 - 18

17 Then the lot fell for the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, because he was Joseph’s firstborn. Since Ma′chir, the firstborn of Ma·nas′seh and the father of Gil′e·ad, was a man of war, he received Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan. 2 And the lot fell for the rest of the descendants of Ma·nas′seh according to their families, for the sons of Abi-e′zer, the sons of He′lek, the sons of As′ri·el, the sons of She′chem, the sons of He′pher, and the sons of She·mi′da. These were the descendants of Ma·nas′seh the son of Joseph, the males according to their families. 3 But Ze·lo′phe·had the son of He′pher, the son of Gil′e·ad, the son of Ma′chir, the son of Ma·nas′seh, did not have sons, only daughters, and these were the names of his daughters: Mah′lah, Noah, Hog′lah, Mil′cah, and Tir′zah. 4 So they presented themselves before El·e·a′zar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the chieftains, saying: “It was Jehovah who commanded Moses to give us an inheritance among our brothers.” So at the order of Jehovah, he gave them an inheritance among the brothers of their father.

5 There were also ten allotments that fell to Ma·nas′seh apart from the land of Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan, which were on the other side[*] of the Jordan, 6 for the daughters of Ma·nas′seh received an inheritance along with his sons, and the land of Gil′e·ad became the property of the rest of the descendants of Ma·nas′seh.

7 And the boundary of Ma·nas′seh was from Ash′er to Mich·me′thath, which faces She′chem, and the boundary continued toward the south[*] to the land of the inhabitants of En-Tap′pu·ah. 8 The land of Tap′pu·ah became Ma·nas′seh’s, but Tap′pu·ah on Ma·nas′seh’s boundary belonged to the descendants of E′phra·im. 9 And the boundary went down to the Wadi of Ka′nah, southward to the wadi. There were cities of E′phra·im among the cities of Ma·nas′seh, and the boundary of Ma·nas′seh was on the north of the wadi, and it ended at the sea. 10 To the south it belonged to E′phra·im, and to the north it belonged to Ma·nas′seh, and the sea was his boundary, and on the north they[*] reached to Ash′er, and on the east, to Is′sa·char.

11 In the territories of Is′sa·char and Ash′er, Ma·nas′seh was given Beth-she′an and its dependent[*] towns, Ib′le·am and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of En-dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Ta′a·nach and its dependent towns, and the inhabitants of Me·gid′do and its dependent towns, three of the heights.

12 But the descendants of Ma·nas′seh were not able to take possession of these cities; the Ca′naan·ites persisted in dwelling in this land. 13 When the Israelites grew strong, they subjected the Ca′naan·ites to forced labor, but they did not drive them out[*] entirely.

14 The descendants of Joseph said to Joshua: “Why have you given us[*] as an inheritance only one lot and one allotment? We are a numerous people, for Jehovah has blessed us until now.” 15 Joshua replied to them: “If you are such a numerous people, go up to the forest and clear out a place for yourself there in the land of the Per′iz·zites and the Reph′a·im, since the mountainous region of E′phra·im is too cramped for you.” 16 Then the descendants of Joseph said: “The mountainous region is not enough for us, and all the Ca′naan·ites who are dwelling in the land of the valley[*] have war chariots with iron scythes,[*] both those in Beth-she′an and its dependent[*] towns and those in the Valley[*] of Jez′re·el.” 17 So Joshua said this to the house of Joseph, to E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh: “You are a numerous people, and you have great power. You will not receive only one lot, 18 but the mountainous region will also be yours. Although it is a forest, you will clear it, and it will be the extremity of your territory. For you will drive away the Ca′naan·ites, even though they are strong and have war chariots with iron scythes.”[*]

^ Josh. 17:5 That is, the east side.

^ Josh. 17:7 Lit., “to the right.”

^ Josh. 17:10 That is, the people of Manasseh or Manasseh’s territory.

^ Josh. 17:11 Or “surrounding.”

^ Josh. 17:13 Or “not dispossess them.”

^ Josh. 17:14 Lit., “me.”

^ Josh. 17:16 Or “low plain.”

^ Josh. 17:16 Lit., “chariots of iron.”

^ Josh. 17:16 Or “surrounding.”

^ Josh. 17:16 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Josh. 17:18 Lit., “chariots of iron.”

Joshua  18 : 1 - 28

18 Then all the assembly of the Israelites congregated at Shi′loh, and they set up the tent of meeting there, as the land was now subdued before them. 2 But there were still seven tribes left of the Israelites whose inheritance had not been allotted. 3 So Joshua said to the Israelites: “How long will you put off going in to take possession of the land that Jehovah the God of your forefathers has given you? 4 Give me three men from each tribe to send out; they should go out and walk throughout the land and map it out according to their inheritance. Then they should return to me. 5 They must apportion it among themselves into seven shares. Judah will remain in his territory to the south, and the house of Joseph will remain in their territory to the north. 6 As for you, map out the land into seven shares, and bring them here to me, and I will cast lots here for you before Jehovah our God. 7 But the Levites have no share among you, because the priesthood of Jehovah is their inheritance; and Gad, Reu′ben, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh have already taken their inheritance on the east side of the Jordan, which Moses the servant of Jehovah gave them.”

8 The men prepared to go, and Joshua commanded those who were to map out the land: “Go and walk through the land and map it out and return to me, and I will cast lots for you here before Jehovah in Shi′loh.” 9 With that the men went and traveled through the land and mapped it out by cities into seven shares, recording it in a book. After that they returned to Joshua at the camp in Shi′loh. 10 Joshua then cast lots for them in Shi′loh before Jehovah. There Joshua apportioned the land to the Israelites by their shares.

11 The lot came up for the tribe of Benjamin by their families, and the territory of their lot was between the people of Judah and the people of Joseph. 12 On the north side, their boundary started at the Jordan, and the boundary went up to the slope of Jer′i·cho on the north and went up on the mountain westward, and it extended to the wilderness of Beth-a′ven. 13 And the boundary continued from there to Luz, at the southern slope of Luz, that is, Beth′el; the boundary went down to At′a·roth-ad′dar on the mountain that is south of Lower Beth-ho′ron. 14 And the boundary was marked at the western side and went around toward the south from the mountain that faces Beth-ho′ron to the south; it ended at Kir′i·ath-ba′al, that is, Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, a city of Judah. This is the western side.

15 The south side was from the extremity of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, and the boundary extended westward; it went out to the spring of the waters of Neph·to′ah. 16 The boundary went down to the extremity of the mountain that faces the Valley of the Son of Hin′nom, which is in the Valley[*] of Reph′a·im to the north, and it went down to the Valley of Hin′nom, to the slope of the Jeb′u·site on the south, and down to En-ro′gel. 17 And it was marked northward and extended to En-she′mesh and then out to Gel·i′loth, which is in front of the ascent of A·dum′mim, and it went down to the stone of Bo′han the son of Reu′ben. 18 And it continued to the northern slope in front of the Ar′a·bah and went down to the Ar′a·bah. 19 And the boundary continued to the northern slope of Beth-hog′lah, and the boundary ended at the northern bay of the Salt Sea[*] at the southern end of the Jordan. This was the southern boundary. 20 And the Jordan served as its boundary on the eastern side. This was the inheritance of the descendants of Benjamin by their families, according to its boundaries on all sides.

21 And the cities of the tribe of Benjamin by their families were: Jer′i·cho, Beth-hog′lah, E′mek-ke′ziz, 22 Beth-ar′a·bah, Zem·a·ra′im, Beth′el, 23 Av′vim, Pa′rah, Oph′rah, 24 Che′phar-am′mo·ni, Oph′ni, and Ge′ba—12 cities and their settlements.

25 Gib′e·on, Ra′mah, Be·er′oth, 26 Miz′peh, Che·phi′rah, Mo′zah, 27 Re′kem, Ir′pe·el, Tar′a·lah, 28 Ze′lah, Ha-e′leph, Je·bu′si, that is, Jerusalem, Gib′e·ah, and Kir′i·ath—14 cities and their settlements.

This was the inheritance of the descendants of Benjamin by their families.

^ Josh. 18:16 Or “Low Plain.”

^ Josh. 18:19 That is, the Dead Sea.

Joshua  19 : 1 - 51

19 Then the second lot came out for Sim′e·on, for the tribe of Sim′e·on by their families. And their inheritance was within the inheritance of Judah. 2 Their inheritance was Be′er-she′ba with She′ba, Mo·la′dah, 3 Ha′zar-shu′al, Ba′lah, E′zem, 4 El·to′lad, Be′thul, Hor′mah, 5 Zik′lag, Beth-mar′ca·both, Ha′zar-su′sah, 6 Beth-le·ba′oth, and Sha·ru′hen—13 cities and their settlements; 7 A′in, Rim′mon, E′ther, and A′shan—four cities and their settlements; 8 and all the settlements that were around these cities as far as Ba′al·ath-be′er, Ra′mah of the south. This was the inheritance of the tribe of Sim′e·on by their families. 9 The inheritance of the descendants of Sim′e·on was taken out of the allotment of Judah, because the share of Judah was too large for them. So the descendants of Sim′e·on received a possession within their inheritance.

10 Next the third lot came up for the descendants of Zeb′u·lun by their families, and the boundary of their inheritance went as far as Sa′rid. 11 Their boundary went up westward to Mar′e·al and reached to Dab′be·sheth and then to the valley[*] in front of Jok′ne·am. 12 And it went from Sa′rid eastward toward the sunrise, to the border of Chis′loth-ta′bor and out to Dab′e·rath and then up to Ja·phi′a. 13 And from there it continued eastward toward the sunrise to Gath-he′pher, to Eth-ka′zin, and out to Rim′mon, and it extended to Ne′ah. 14 And the boundary went around it on the north to Han′na·thon, and it ended at the Valley of Iph′tah-el, 15 and Kat′tath, Na·hal′al, Shim′ron, I′da·lah, and Beth′le·hem—12 cities and their settlements. 16 This was the inheritance of the descendants of Zeb′u·lun by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

17 The fourth lot came out for Is′sa·char, for the descendants of Is′sa·char by their families. 18 And their boundary was to Jez′re·el, Che·sul′loth, Shu′nem, 19 Haph′a·ra′im, Shi′on, An·a·ha′rath, 20 Rab′bith, Kish′i·on, E′bez, 21 Re′meth, En-gan′nim, En-had′dah, and Beth-paz′zez. 22 And the boundary reached to Ta′bor and Sha·ha·zu′mah and Beth-she′mesh, and the end of their border was at the Jordan—16 cities and their settlements. 23 This was the inheritance of the tribe of Is′sa·char by their families, the cities and their settlements.

24 Then the fifth lot came out for the tribe of Ash′er by their families. 25 And their boundary was Hel′kath, Ha′li, Be′ten, Ach′shaph, 26 Al·lam′me·lech, A′mad, and Mi′shal. It reached westward to Car′mel and to Shi′hor-lib′nath, 27 and it went back toward the east to Beth-da′gon and reached to Zeb′u·lun and the Valley of Iph′tah-el to the north, to Beth-e′mek and Ne·i′el, and it extended to Ca′bul on the left, 28 and to E′bron, Re′hob, Ham′mon, and Ka′nah as far as Great Si′don. 29 And the boundary went back to Ra′mah and as far as the fortified city of Tyre. Then the boundary went back to Ho′sah, and it ended at the sea in the region of Ach′zib, 30 Um′mah, A′phek, and Re′hob—22 cities and their settlements. 31 This was the inheritance of the tribe of Ash′er by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

32 The sixth lot came out for the descendants of Naph′ta·li, for the descendants of Naph′ta·li by their families. 33 Their boundary was from He′leph, from the big tree in Za·a·nan′nim, and Ad′a·mi-ne′keb and Jab′ne·el as far as Lak′kum; and it ended at the Jordan. 34 The boundary went back westward to Az′noth-ta′bor and extended from there to Huk′kok and reached to Zeb′u·lun on the south and to Ash′er on the west and to Judah at the Jordan toward the east. 35 And the fortified cities were Zid′dim, Zer, Ham′math, Rak′kath, Chin′ne·reth, 36 Ad′a·mah, Ra′mah, Ha′zor, 37 Ke′desh, Ed′re·i, En-ha′zor, 38 Yi′ron, Mig′dal-el, Ho′rem, Beth-a′nath, and Beth-she′mesh—19 cities and their settlements. 39 This was the inheritance of the tribe of Naph′ta·li by their families, the cities and their settlements.

40 The seventh lot came out for the tribe of Dan by their families. 41 And the border of their inheritance was Zo′rah, Esh′ta·ol, Ir-she′mesh, 42 Sha·al·ab′bin, Ai′ja·lon, Ith′lah, 43 E′lon, Tim′nah, Ek′ron, 44 El′te·keh, Gib′be·thon, Ba′al·ath, 45 Je′hud, Ben′e-be′rak, Gath-rim′mon, 46 Me-jar′kon, and Rak′kon, with the border facing Jop′pa. 47 But the territory of Dan was too cramped for them. So they went up and fought against Le′shem and captured it and struck it with the sword. Then they took possession of it and settled in it, and they changed the name of Le′shem to Dan, after the name of Dan their forefather. 48 This was the inheritance of the tribe of Dan by their families. These were the cities and their settlements.

49 Thus they finished dividing the land for inheritance by its territories. Then the Israelites gave Joshua the son of Nun an inheritance in their midst. 50 At the order of Jehovah they gave him the city he asked for, Tim′nath-se′rah, in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and he built up the city and settled in it.

51 These were the inheritances that El·e·a′zar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the paternal houses of the tribes of Israel distributed by lot in Shi′loh before Jehovah, at the entrance of the tent of meeting. So they finished apportioning the land.

^ Josh. 19:11 Or “wadi.”

Joshua  20 : 1 - 9

20 Then Jehovah said to Joshua: 2 “Tell the Israelites, ‘Select for yourselves the cities of refuge about which I spoke to you through Moses, 3 so that the manslayer who unintentionally or accidentally[*] kills someone[*] may flee there. And they will serve as a refuge for you from the avenger of blood. 4 He must flee to one of these cities and stand at the entrance of the city gate and present his case in the hearing of the elders of that city. Then they must receive him into the city and give him a place and he will live with them. 5 If the avenger of blood chases after him, they should not surrender the manslayer into his hand, for he killed his fellow man accidentally[*] and he did not previously hate him. 6 He must dwell in that city until he stands trial before the assembly and remain there until the death of the high priest who is in office at that time. Then the manslayer may return to the city from which he fled, and he may enter his city and his house.’”

7 So they gave a sacred status to[*] Ke′desh in Gal′i·lee in the mountainous region of Naph′ta·li, She′chem in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, and Kir′i·ath-ar′ba, that is, Heb′ron, in the mountainous region of Judah. 8 In the region of the Jordan, east of Jer′i·cho, they selected Be′zer in the wilderness on the tableland[*] out of the tribe of Reu′ben, Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad out of the tribe of Gad, and Go′lan in Ba′shan out of the tribe of Ma·nas′seh.

9 These became the cities appointed for all the Israelites and for the foreign residents residing among them, so that anyone who unintentionally killed someone[*] could flee there and not die by the hand of the avenger of blood prior to standing trial before the assembly.

^ Josh. 20:3 Or “unknowingly.”

^ Josh. 20:3 Or “strikes a soul.”

^ Josh. 20:5 Or “unknowingly.”

^ Josh. 20:7 Or “they set apart.”

^ Josh. 20:8 Or “plateau.”

^ Josh. 20:9 Or “a soul.”

Joshua  21 : 1 - 45

21 The heads of the paternal houses of the Levites now approached El·e·a′zar the priest, Joshua the son of Nun, and the heads of the paternal houses of the tribes of Israel, 2 and they spoke to them in Shi′loh in the land of Ca′naan, saying: “Jehovah through Moses commanded that we be given cities in which to dwell, along with their pastures for our livestock.” 3 So at the order of Jehovah, the Israelites gave the Levites these cities and their pastures out of their own inheritance.

4 The lot came out for the families of the Ko′hath·ites, and the Levites who were descendants of Aaron the priest were given by lot[*] 13 cities out of the tribe of Judah, the tribe of Sim′e·on, and the tribe of Benjamin.

5 And for the rest of the Ko′hath·ites, there were allotted[*] ten cities out of the families of the tribe of E′phra·im, the tribe of Dan, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh.

6 And for the Ger′shon·ites, there were allotted 13 cities out of the families of the tribe of Is′sa·char, the tribe of Ash′er, the tribe of Naph′ta·li, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Ba′shan.

7 For the Me·rar′ites by their families, there were 12 cities out of the tribe of Reu′ben, the tribe of Gad, and the tribe of Zeb′u·lun.

8 Thus the Israelites gave the Levites these cities and their pastures by lot, just as Jehovah had commanded through Moses.

9 So from the tribe of Judah and the tribe of Sim′e·on, they gave these cities here mentioned by name, 10 and they were given to the sons of Aaron of the Ko′hath·ite families of the Levites, because they received the first lot. 11 They gave them Kir′i·ath-ar′ba (Ar′ba was the father of A′nak), that is, Heb′ron, in the mountainous region of Judah, and its surrounding pastures. 12 But the field of the city and its settlements they gave to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh as his possession.

13 And to the sons of Aaron the priest, they gave the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Heb′ron with its pastures, also Lib′nah with its pastures, 14 Jat′tir with its pastures, Esh·te·mo′a with its pastures, 15 Ho′lon with its pastures, De′bir with its pastures, 16 A′in with its pastures, Jut′tah with its pastures, and Beth-she′mesh with its pastures—nine cities out of these two tribes.

17 And from the tribe of Benjamin: Gib′e·on with its pastures, Ge′ba with its pastures, 18 An′a·thoth with its pastures, and Al′mon with its pastures—four cities.

19 All the cities given to the descendants of Aaron, the priests, were 13 cities with their pastures.

20 And the rest of the Ko′hath·ite families among the Levites were given by lot cities from the tribe of E′phra·im. 21 They gave them the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, She′chem with its pastures in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, Ge′zer with its pastures, 22 Kib′za·im with its pastures, and Beth-ho′ron with its pastures—four cities.

23 And from the tribe of Dan: El′te·ke with its pastures, Gib′be·thon with its pastures, 24 Ai′ja·lon with its pastures, Gath-rim′mon with its pastures—four cities.

25 And from the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh: Ta′a·nach with its pastures and Gath-rim′mon with its pastures—two cities.

26 All the cities together with their pastures that the rest of the families of the Ko′hath·ites received were ten.

27 And the Ger′shon·ites of the families of the Levites received from the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Go′lan, in Ba′shan, with its pastures and Be·esh′te·rah with its pastures—two cities.

28 And from the tribe of Is′sa·char: Kish′i·on with its pastures, Dab′e·rath with its pastures, 29 Jar′muth with its pastures, and En-gan′nim with its pastures—four cities.

30 And from the tribe of Ash′er: Mi′shal with its pastures, Ab′don with its pastures, 31 Hel′kath with its pastures, and Re′hob with its pastures—four cities.

32 And from the tribe of Naph′ta·li: the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Ke′desh in Gal′i·lee with its pastures, Ham′moth-dor with its pastures, and Kar′tan with its pastures—three cities.

33 All the cities of the Ger′shon·ites by their families were 13 cities with their pastures.

34 And the families of the Me·rar′ites, the rest of the Levites, received from the tribe of Zeb′u·lun: Jok′ne·am with its pastures, Kar′tah with its pastures, 35 Dim′nah with its pastures, and Na·hal′al with its pastures—four cities.

36 And from the tribe of Reu′ben: Be′zer with its pastures, Ja′haz with its pastures, 37 Ked′e·moth with its pastures, and Meph′a·ath with its pastures—four cities.

38 And from the tribe of Gad: the city of refuge for the manslayer, namely, Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad with its pastures, Ma·ha·na′im with its pastures, 39 Hesh′bon with its pastures, and Ja′zer with its pastures—a total of four cities.

40 All the cities that were allotted to the Me·rar′ites by their families, the rest of the families of the Levites, were 12 cities.

41 All the cities of the Levites within the possession of the Israelites were 48 cities together with their pastures. 42 Each of these cities had its pastures all around it—this was the case for all these cities.

43 So Jehovah gave Israel all the land that he had sworn to give to their forefathers, and they took possession of it and settled in it. 44 Furthermore, Jehovah gave them rest on every side, just as he had sworn to their forefathers, and not one of all their enemies could stand against them. Jehovah gave all their enemies into their hand. 45 Not a promise[*] failed out of all the good promises that Jehovah had made to the house of Israel; all of them came true.

^ Josh. 21:4 Or “were allotted.”

^ Josh. 21:5 Or “given by lot.”

^ Josh. 21:45 Or “word.”

Joshua  24 : 1 - 33

24 Joshua then assembled all the tribes of Israel together at She′chem and summoned the elders of Israel, its heads, its judges, and its officers, and they stood before the true God. 2 Joshua said to all the people: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘It was on the other side of the River[*] that your forefathers lived a long time ago—Te′rah the father of Abraham and the father of Na′hor—and they used to serve other gods.

3 “‘In time I took your forefather Abraham from the other side of the River[*] and had him walk through all the land of Ca′naan and made his offspring[*] many. I gave him Isaac; 4 then to Isaac I gave Jacob and E′sau. Later to E′sau I gave Mount Se′ir as his possession; and Jacob and his sons went down to Egypt. 5 I later sent Moses and Aaron, and I plagued Egypt with what I did among them, and then I brought you out. 6 When I was bringing your fathers out of Egypt and you came to the sea, the Egyptians were chasing after your fathers with war chariots and cavalrymen as far as the Red Sea. 7 They began to cry out to Jehovah, so he placed a darkness between you and the Egyptians and brought the sea over them and covered them, and your own eyes saw what I did in Egypt. Then you dwelled in the wilderness many years.[*]

8 “‘And I brought you to the land of the Am′or·ites who were dwelling on the other side[*] of the Jordan, and they fought against you. But I gave them into your hand so that you could take possession of their land, and I annihilated them from before you. 9 Then Ba′lak son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab, rose up and fought against Israel. So he summoned Ba′laam the son of Be′or to curse you. 10 But I would not listen to Ba′laam. So he blessed you repeatedly, and I rescued you from his hand.

11 “‘Then you crossed the Jordan and came to Jer′i·cho. And the leaders[*] of Jer′i·cho, the Am′or·ites, the Per′iz·zites, the Ca′naan·ites, the Hit′tites, the Gir′ga·shites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites fought against you, but I gave them into your hand. 12 So I sent the feeling of dejection[*] ahead of you, and it drove them out from before you—two kings of the Am′or·ites. It was not by your sword and not by your bow. 13 Thus I gave you a land for which you had not toiled and cities that you had not built, and you settled in them. You are eating from vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant.’

14 “Therefore, fear Jehovah and serve him with integrity[*] and faithfulness,[*] and remove the gods that your forefathers served on the other side of the River[*] and in Egypt, and serve Jehovah. 15 Now if it seems bad to you to serve Jehovah, choose for yourselves today whom you will serve, whether the gods that your forefathers served on the other side of the River[*] or the gods of the Am′or·ites in whose land you are dwelling. But as for me and my household, we will serve Jehovah.”

16 At this the people answered: “It is unthinkable for us to abandon Jehovah and to serve other gods. 17 It is Jehovah our God who brought us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery, and who performed these great signs before our eyes and who kept guarding us the entire way in which we walked and among all the peoples through whom we passed. 18 Jehovah drove out all the peoples, including the Am′or·ites, who lived in the land before us. Therefore, we too will serve Jehovah, because he is our God.”

19 Then Joshua said to the people: “You are not able to serve Jehovah, for he is a holy God; he is a God who requires exclusive devotion. He will not pardon your transgressions[*] and your sins. 20 If you abandon Jehovah and serve foreign gods, he will also turn against you and exterminate you after doing good for you.”

21 But the people said to Joshua: “No, but we will serve Jehovah!” 22 So Joshua said to the people: “You are witnesses against yourselves that of your own accord, you have chosen for yourselves to serve Jehovah.” To this they said: “We are witnesses.”

23 “Therefore, remove the foreign gods that are among you, and incline your hearts to Jehovah the God of Israel.” 24 The people said to Joshua: “We will serve Jehovah our God, and we will obey his voice!”

25 So Joshua made a covenant with the people on that day and established a regulation and a ruling for them in She′chem. 26 Then Joshua wrote these words in the book of God’s Law and took a great stone and set it up under the large tree that is by the sanctuary of Jehovah.

27 Joshua went on to say to all the people: “Look! This stone will serve as a witness against us, because it has heard everything Jehovah said to us, and it will serve as a witness against you, so that you may not deny your God.” 28 With that Joshua sent the people away, each one to his inheritance.

29 After these things, Joshua the son of Nun, the servant of Jehovah, died at the age of 110. 30 So they buried him in the territory of his inheritance in Tim′nath-se′rah, which is in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, north of Mount Ga′ash. 31 Israel continued to serve Jehovah all the days of Joshua and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua and who had known all of Jehovah’s deeds in behalf of Israel.

32 The bones of Joseph, which the Israelites had brought up out of Egypt, were buried in She′chem in the portion of the field that Jacob had acquired from the sons of Ha′mor, She′chem’s father, for 100 pieces of money; and it became the inheritance of the sons of Joseph.

33 Also, El·e·a′zar the son of Aaron died. So they buried him in the Hill of Phin′e·has his son, which had been given to him in the mountainous region of E′phra·im.

^ Josh. 24:2 That is, the Euphrates.

^ Josh. 24:3 That is, the Euphrates.

^ Josh. 24:3 Lit., “seed.”

^ Josh. 24:7 Lit., “days.”

^ Josh. 24:8 That is, the east side.

^ Josh. 24:11 Or possibly, “landowners.”

^ Josh. 24:12 Or possibly, “panic; terror.”

^ Josh. 24:14 Or “in a blameless way.”

^ Josh. 24:14 Or “in truth.”

^ Josh. 24:14 That is, the Euphrates.

^ Josh. 24:15 That is, the Euphrates.

^ Josh. 24:19 Or “rebellion.”

Judges  1 : 1 - 36

JUDGES

1 After the death of Joshua, the Israelites[*] inquired of Jehovah: “Who of us will go up first to fight against the Ca′naan·ites?” 2 Jehovah replied: “Judah will go up. Look! I am giving[*] the land into his hand.” 3 Then Judah said to his brother Sim′e·on: “Come up with me into my assigned territory[*] to fight against the Ca′naan·ites. Then I will go with you into your assigned territory.” So Sim′e·on went with him.

4 When Judah went up, Jehovah gave the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites into their hands, and they defeated 10,000 men in Be′zek. 5 They found A·do′ni-be′zek in Be′zek, and there they fought against him and defeated the Ca′naan·ites and the Per′iz·zites. 6 When A·do′ni-be′zek fled, they chased him and caught him and cut off his thumbs and his big toes. 7 Then A·do′ni-be′zek said: “There are 70 kings whose thumbs and big toes were cut off and who are picking up food under my table. Just as I have done, so God has repaid me.” After that they brought him to Jerusalem, and he died there.

8 Furthermore, the men of Judah fought against Jerusalem and captured it; they struck it with the sword and set the city on fire. 9 Afterward, the men of Judah went down to fight against the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the mountainous region and the Neg′eb and the She·phe′lah. 10 So Judah marched against the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Heb′ron (the name of Heb′ron was previously Kir′i·ath-ar′ba), and they struck down She′shai, A·hi′man, and Tal′mai.

11 They marched from there against the inhabitants of De′bir. (The name of De′bir was previously Kir′i·ath-se′pher.) 12 Then Ca′leb said: “To the man who strikes Kir′i·ath-se′pher and captures it, I will give my daughter Ach′sah as a wife.” 13 And Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz, Ca′leb’s younger brother, captured it. So he gave him his daughter Ach′sah as a wife. 14 While she was going home, she urged him to ask her father for a field. Then she dismounted from her donkey.[*] Ca′leb asked her: “What do you want?” 15 She said to him: “Please grant me a blessing, for you have given me a piece of land in the south;[*] give me also Gul′loth-ma′im.”[*] So Ca′leb gave her Upper Gul′loth and Lower Gul′loth.

16 And the descendants of the Ken′ite, Moses’ father-in-law, came up from the city of palm trees with the people of Judah to the wilderness of Judah south of A′rad. They went there and settled among the people. 17 But Judah marched on with his brother Sim′e·on, and they attacked the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting Ze′phath and devoted it to destruction. So they named the city Hor′mah.[*] 18 Then Judah captured Gaz′a and its territory, Ash′ke·lon and its territory, and Ek′ron and its territory. 19 Jehovah was with Judah, and they took possession of the mountainous region, but they could not drive out the inhabitants of the plain,[*] because they had war chariots with iron scythes.[*] 20 They gave Heb′ron to Ca′leb, just as Moses had promised, and he drove out from there the three sons of A′nak.

21 But the Ben′ja·min·ites did not drive out the Jeb′u·sites inhabiting Jerusalem, so the Jeb′u·sites continue dwelling with the Ben′ja·min·ites in Jerusalem down to this day.

22 Meantime, the house of Joseph went up against Beth′el, and Jehovah was with them. 23 The house of Joseph was spying on Beth′el (incidentally, the name of the city was previously Luz), 24 and the spies saw a man going out of the city. So they said to him: “Show us, please, the way into the city, and we will treat you kindly.”[*] 25 So the man showed them the way into the city, and they struck the city with the sword, but they let the man and all his family go free. 26 The man went to the land of the Hit′tites and built a city and named it Luz, which is its name to this day.

27 Ma·nas′seh did not take possession of Beth-she′an and its dependent[*] towns, Ta′a·nach and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Dor and its dependent towns, the inhabitants of Ib′le·am and its dependent towns, and the inhabitants of Me·gid′do and its dependent towns. The Ca′naan·ites persisted in dwelling in this land. 28 When Israel grew stronger, they subjected the Ca′naan·ites to forced labor, but they did not drive them out completely.

29 Nor did E′phra·im drive out the Ca′naan·ites who were dwelling in Ge′zer. The Ca′naan·ites continued to dwell among them in Ge′zer.

30 Zeb′u·lun did not drive out the inhabitants of Kit′ron and the inhabitants of Na′ha·lol. The Ca′naan·ites continued to dwell among them and were subjected to forced labor.

31 Ash′er did not drive out the inhabitants of Ac′co and the inhabitants of Si′don, Ah′lab, Ach′zib, Hel′bah, A′phik, and Re′hob. 32 So the Ash′er·ites continued to dwell among the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the land, because they did not drive them out.

33 Naph′ta·li did not drive out the inhabitants of Beth-she′mesh and the inhabitants of Beth-a′nath, but they continued to dwell among the Ca′naan·ites inhabiting the land. The inhabitants of Beth-she′mesh and Beth-a′nath became forced laborers for them.

34 The Am′or·ites confined the Dan′ites to the mountainous region, for they would not let them come down into the plain.[*] 35 So the Am′or·ites persisted in dwelling in Mount He′res, Ai′ja·lon, and Sha·al′bim. But when the power[*] of the house of Joseph increased,[*] they were forced into hard labor. 36 The territory of the Am′or·ites was from the ascent of A·krab′bim, from Se′la upward.

^ Judg. 1:1 Lit., “sons of Israel.”

^ Judg. 1:2 Or “have given.”

^ Judg. 1:3 Lit., “my lot.”

^ Judg. 1:14 Or possibly, “she clapped her hands while on the donkey.”

^ Judg. 1:15 Or “the Negeb.”

^ Judg. 1:15 Meaning “Basins (Bowls) of Water.”

^ Judg. 1:17 Meaning “A Devoting to Destruction.”

^ Judg. 1:19 Or “low plain.”

^ Judg. 1:19 Lit., “chariots of iron.”

^ Judg. 1:24 Lit., “show you loyal love.”

^ Judg. 1:27 Or “surrounding.”

^ Judg. 1:34 Or “low plain.”

^ Judg. 1:35 Lit., “hand.”

^ Judg. 1:35 Lit., “became heavy.”

Judges  3 : 1 - 31

3 These are the nations that Jehovah allowed to remain so that they could test all those of Israel who had not experienced any of the wars of Ca′naan 2 (this was so that succeeding generations of Israelites would experience war, those who had not experienced such things before): 3 the five lords of the Phi·lis′tines, and all the Ca′naan·ites, the Si·do′ni·ans, and the Hi′vites inhabiting Mount Leb′a·non from Mount Ba′al-her′mon as far as Le′bo-ha′math.[*] 4 They served as a means of testing Israel to determine whether Israel would obey Jehovah’s commandments that he had given their fathers through Moses. 5 So the Israelites lived among the Ca′naan·ites, the Hit′tites, the Am′or·ites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites. 6 They would take their daughters as wives, and their own daughters they gave to their sons, and they began serving their gods.

7 So the Israelites did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and they forgot Jehovah their God and were serving the Ba′als and the sacred poles.[*] 8 At this Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a.[*] The Israelites served Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im for eight years. 9 When the Israelites called to Jehovah for help, Jehovah raised up a savior to rescue the Israelites, Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz, the younger brother of Ca′leb. 10 The spirit of Jehovah came upon him, and he became the judge of Israel. When he went out to battle, Jehovah gave Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im the king of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a[*] into his hand so that he prevailed over Cu′shan-rish·a·tha′im. 11 After that the land had rest[*] for 40 years. Then Oth′ni·el the son of Ke′naz died.

12 And once again the Israelites began doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. So Jehovah let Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab prevail over Israel, because they did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 13 Furthermore, he brought against them the Am′mon·ites and the A·mal′ek·ites. They attacked Israel and captured the city of palm trees. 14 The Israelites served Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab for 18 years. 15 Then the Israelites called to Jehovah for help, so Jehovah raised up for them a savior, E′hud the son of Ge′ra, a Ben′ja·min·ite who was left-handed. In time the Israelites sent tribute through him to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. 16 Meanwhile, E′hud made for himself a two-edged sword, a cubit[*] long, and he strapped it underneath his garment on his right thigh. 17 He then presented the tribute to Eg′lon the king of Mo′ab. Now Eg′lon was a very fat man.

18 When E′hud finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who had carried the tribute. 19 But after reaching the carved images[*] at Gil′gal, he himself went back and said: “I have a secret message for you, O king.” So the king said: “Silence!” With that all his attendants left him. 20 So E′hud came to him as he was sitting alone in his cool roof chamber. Then E′hud said: “I have a message from God for you.” So he rose up from his throne.[*] 21 Then E′hud drew the sword from his right thigh with his left hand and plunged it into his belly. 22 The handle went in after the blade, and the fat closed in over the blade, for he did not draw the sword out of his belly, and the fecal matter came out. 23 E′hud went out through the porch,[*] closing the doors of the roof chamber behind him and locking them. 24 After he left, the servants returned and saw that the doors of the roof chamber were locked. So they said: “He must be relieving himself[*] in the cool interior room.” 25 They kept waiting until they were embarrassed, but when they saw that he was still not opening the doors of the roof chamber, they took the key and opened them and saw their lord fallen to the floor[*] dead!

26 E′hud escaped while they were lingering, and he passed by the carved images[*] and made it safely to Se·i′rah. 27 When he arrived, he sounded the horn in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; and the Israelites went down out of the mountainous region, with him at their head. 28 Then he said to them: “Follow me, because Jehovah has given your enemies, the Mo′ab·ites, into your hand.” So they followed him and captured the fords of the Jordan against the Mo′ab·ites, and they did not allow anyone to cross. 29 At that time they struck down about 10,000 Mo′ab·ites, all strong and valiant men; not a single one escaped. 30 So Mo′ab was subdued on that day under Israel’s hand; and the land had rest[*] for 80 years.

31 After him was Sham′gar the son of A′nath, who struck down 600 Phi·lis′tine men with a cattle goad; he too saved Israel.

^ Judg. 3:3 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ Judg. 3:7 See Glossary.

^ Judg. 3:8 Lit., “Aram-naharaim.”

^ Judg. 3:10 Lit., “Aram.”

^ Judg. 3:11 Or “peace.”

^ Judg. 3:16 Perhaps a short cubit of about 38 cm (15 in.). See App. B14.

^ Judg. 3:19 Or possibly, “the quarries.”

^ Judg. 3:20 Or “seat.”

^ Judg. 3:23 Or possibly, “air vent.”

^ Judg. 3:24 Lit., “covering his feet.”

^ Judg. 3:25 Lit., “earth.”

^ Judg. 3:26 Or possibly, “the quarries.”

^ Judg. 3:30 Or “peace.”

Judges  4 : 1 - 24

4 But after E′hud died, the Israelites again did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 2 So Jehovah sold them into the hand of Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan, who reigned in Ha′zor. The chief of his army was Sis′e·ra, who lived in Ha·ro′sheth of the nations.[*] 3 The Israelites cried out to Jehovah, because Ja′bin[*] had 900 war chariots with iron scythes,[*] and he harshly oppressed the Israelites for 20 years.

4 Now Deb′o·rah, a prophetess, the wife of Lap′pi·doth, was judging Israel at that time. 5 She used to sit under Deb′o·rah’s palm tree between Ra′mah and Beth′el in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; the Israelites would go up to her for judgment. 6 She sent for Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am out of Ke′desh-naph′ta·li and said to him: “Has not Jehovah the God of Israel given the command? ‘Go and march to[*] Mount Ta′bor, and take 10,000 men of Naph′ta·li and Zeb′u·lun with you. 7 I will bring to you Sis′e·ra, the chief of Ja′bin’s army, along with his war chariots and his troops to the stream[*] of Ki′shon, and I will give him into your hand.’”

8 At this Ba′rak said to her: “If you go with me, I will go, but if you do not go with me, I will not go.” 9 To this she said: “I will certainly go with you. However, the campaign you are going on will not bring you glory, for it will be into the hand of a woman that Jehovah will give Sis′e·ra.” Then Deb′o·rah got up and went with Ba′rak to Ke′desh. 10 Ba′rak summoned Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li to Ke′desh, and 10,000 men followed his steps. Deb′o·rah also went up with him.

11 Incidentally, He′ber the Ken′ite had separated from the Ken′ites, the descendants of Ho′bab, Moses’ father-in-law, and his tent was pitched near the big tree in Za·a·nan′nim, which is at Ke′desh.

12 They reported to Sis′e·ra that Ba′rak the son of A·bin′o·am had gone up to Mount Ta′bor. 13 At once Sis′e·ra assembled all his war chariots—900 chariots with iron scythes[*]—and all the troops that were with him from Ha·ro′sheth of the nations to go to the stream[*] of Ki′shon. 14 Deb′o·rah now said to Ba′rak: “Rise up, for this is the day that Jehovah will give Sis′e·ra into your hand. Is Jehovah not going out before you?” And Ba′rak descended from Mount Ta′bor with 10,000 men following him. 15 Then Jehovah threw Sis′e·ra and all his war chariots and all the army into confusion before the sword of Ba′rak. Finally Sis′e·ra got down from his chariot and fled on foot. 16 Ba′rak chased after the war chariots and the army as far as Ha·ro′sheth of the nations. So Sis′e·ra’s whole army fell by the sword; not even one remained.

17 But Sis′e·ra fled on foot to the tent of Ja′el the wife of He′ber the Ken′ite, for there was peace between Ja′bin the king of Ha′zor and the house of He′ber the Ken′ite. 18 Then Ja′el came out to meet Sis′e·ra and said to him: “Come in, my lord, come in here. Do not be afraid.” So he went into her tent, and she covered him with a blanket. 19 Then he said to her: “Give me, please, a little water to drink, for I am thirsty.” So she opened a skin bottle of milk and gave him a drink, after which she again covered him. 20 He told her: “Stand at the entrance of the tent, and if anybody comes and asks you, ‘Is there a man here?’ say, ‘No!’”

21 But Ja′el the wife of He′ber took a tent pin and a hammer in her hand. Then while he was fast asleep and exhausted, she stealthily approached him and drove the pin through his temples and beat it into the ground, and he died.

22 Ba′rak went there in pursuit of Sis′e·ra, and Ja′el now came out to meet him and said: “Come and I will show you the man you are looking for.” He went in with her and saw Sis′e·ra lying dead, with the tent pin through his temples.

23 So on that day, God subdued Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan before the Israelites. 24 The hand of the Israelites came down harder and harder against Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan, until they destroyed Ja′bin the king of Ca′naan.

^ Judg. 4:2 Or “Harosheth-ha-goiim.”

^ Judg. 4:3 Lit., “he.”

^ Judg. 4:3 Lit., “chariots of iron.”

^ Judg. 4:6 Or “Deploy your men on.”

^ Judg. 4:7 Or “wadi.”

^ Judg. 4:13 Lit., “chariots of iron.”

^ Judg. 4:13 Or “wadi.”

Judges  7 : 1 - 25

7 Then Jer·ub·ba′al, that is, Gid′e·on, and all the people with him rose early and encamped at the well of Ha′rod, while the camp of Mid′i·an was north of him at the hill of Mo′reh in the valley plain.[*] 2 Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “There are too many people with you for me to give Mid′i·an into their hand. Otherwise, Israel might brag about itself against me and say, ‘My own hand saved me.’ 3 Now, please, announce in the presence of the people: ‘Whoever is afraid and trembling, let him return home.’” So Gid′e·on put them to the test. With that, 22,000 of the people returned home, and 10,000 remained.

4 Still Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “There are yet too many people. Have them go down to the water so that I may test them for you there. When I say to you, ‘This one will go with you,’ he will go with you, but when I say to you, ‘This one will not go along with you,’ he will not go along.” 5 So he took the people down to the water.

Then Jehovah said to Gid′e·on: “Separate everyone who laps up the water with his tongue just as a dog laps, from those who bend down on their knees to drink.” 6 The number of those lapping up the water, putting their hand to their mouth, was 300 men. The rest of the people bent down on their knees to drink.

7 Jehovah now said to Gid′e·on: “I will save you with the 300 men who lapped the water, and I will give Mid′i·an into your hand. But let all the other people go back home.” 8 So after they took the provisions and the horns from the people, he sent all the other men of Israel back home, and he kept only the 300 men. The camp of Mid′i·an was below him in the valley plain.

9 During that night, Jehovah said to him: “Get up, attack the camp, for I have given it into your hand. 10 But if you are afraid to attack, go down to the camp with Pu′rah your attendant. 11 Listen to what they say, and afterward you will have the courage[*] to attack the camp.” At that he and Pu′rah his attendant went down to the edge of the encamped army.

12 Now Mid′i·an and Am′a·lek and all the Easterners covered the valley plain like a swarm of locusts, and their camels were without number, as many as the grains of sand on the seashore. 13 Gid′e·on now came, and there was a man relating a dream to his companion, and he said: “This is the dream I had. There was a round loaf of barley bread rolling into the camp of Mid′i·an. It came to a tent and struck it so hard that it collapsed. Yes, it turned the tent upside down, and the tent fell flat.” 14 At this his companion said: “This can only be the sword of Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash, a man of Israel. God has given Mid′i·an and all the camp into his hand.”

15 As soon as Gid′e·on heard him relate the dream and its interpretation, he bowed down to worship. After that he returned to the camp of Israel and said: “Get up, for Jehovah has given the camp of Mid′i·an into your hand.” 16 Then he divided the 300 men into three bands and gave all of them horns and large empty jars with torches inside the jars. 17 Then he said to them: “Watch me and do exactly what I do. When I come to the edge of the camp, you should do just as I do. 18 When I blow the horn, I and all who are with me, you also must blow the horns all around the camp and shout, ‘For Jehovah and for Gid′e·on!’”

19 Gid′e·on and the 100 men who were with him came to the edge of the camp at the start of the middle night watch,[*] just after the sentries were posted. They blew the horns and smashed the large water jars that were in their hands. 20 So the three bands blew the horns and shattered the large jars. They held the torches in their left hands and blew the horns in their right hands and they called out: “The sword of Jehovah and of Gid′e·on!” 21 All the while each man stood in his place all around the camp, and the whole army ran away, shouting as they fled. 22 The 300 continued to blow the horns, and Jehovah turned the sword of each one against the other throughout the camp; and the army fled as far as Beth-shit′tah, on to Zer′e·rah, as far as the outskirts of A′bel-me·ho′lah by Tab′bath.

23 And the men of Israel were called together from Naph′ta·li, Ash′er, and all of Ma·nas′seh, and they chased after Mid′i·an. 24 Gid′e·on sent messengers into all the mountainous region of E′phra·im, saying: “Go down to attack Mid′i·an, and capture the access to the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan.” So all the men of E′phra·im were gathered together, and they captured the waters as far as Beth-bar′ah and the Jordan. 25 They also captured the two princes of Mid′i·an, O′reb and Ze′eb; they killed O′reb on the rock of O′reb, and they killed Ze′eb at the winepress of Ze′eb. They kept on pursuing Mid′i·an, and they brought the heads of O′reb and Ze′eb to Gid′e·on in the region of the Jordan.

^ Judg. 7:1 Or “low plain.”

^ Judg. 7:11 Lit., “your hands will grow strong.”

^ Judg. 7:19 From about 10:00 p.m. to about 2:00 a.m.

Judges  8 : 1 - 35

8 Then the men of E′phra·im said to him: “What have you done to us? Why did you not call us when you went to fight against Mid′i·an?” And they quarreled bitterly with him. 2 But he said to them: “What have I done compared with you? Are not the gleanings of E′phra·im better than the grape harvest of Abi-e′zer? 3 It was into your hand that God gave Mid′i·an’s princes O′reb and Ze′eb, and what have I done compared with you?” When he spoke this way,[*] they calmed down.[*]

4 Gid′e·on then came to the Jordan and crossed it. He and the 300 men with him were tired, but they kept up the pursuit. 5 So he said to the men of Suc′coth: “Please give loaves of bread to the people following me, for they are tired and I am chasing after Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na, the kings of Mid′i·an.” 6 But the princes of Suc′coth said: “Are the palms of Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that we should give bread to your army?” 7 At this Gid′e·on said: “Just for that, when Jehovah gives Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na into my hand, I will give you a thrashing with the thorns and the briars of the wilderness.” 8 And he went up from there to Pe·nu′el and made the same request, but the men of Pe·nu′el gave him the same answer as the men of Suc′coth. 9 So he said also to the men of Pe·nu′el: “When I return in peace, I will pull down this tower.”

10 Now Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na were in Kar′kor with their armies, about 15,000 men. These were all who remained of the entire army of the Easterners, for 120,000 men armed with swords had fallen. 11 Gid′e·on continued up by the way of the tent dwellers east of No′bah and Jog′be·hah and attacked the camp, which was off guard. 12 When Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na fled, he pursued and captured the two Mid′i·an·ite kings, Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na, throwing the whole camp into a panic.

13 Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash then returned from the war by way of the pass that goes up to He′res. 14 En route he captured and interrogated a young man from Suc′coth. So the young man wrote out for him the names of the princes and elders of Suc′coth, 77 men. 15 With that he went to the men of Suc′coth and said: “Here are Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na about whom you taunted me, saying, ‘Are the palms of Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na already in your hand so that we should give bread to your exhausted men?’” 16 Then he took the elders of the city and with thorns and briars of the wilderness, he taught the men of Suc′coth a lesson. 17 And he pulled down the tower of Pe·nu′el and killed the men of the city.

18 He asked Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na: “What sort of men did you kill in Ta′bor?” To this they said: “They were like you, each one looked like the son of a king.” 19 At that he said: “They were my brothers, the sons of my mother. As surely as Jehovah lives, if you had spared their lives, I would not have to kill you.” 20 Then he said to Je′ther his firstborn: “Get up, kill them.” But the young man did not draw his sword; he was afraid, for he was still a young man. 21 So Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na said: “Get up yourself and slay us, for a man is judged by his mightiness.”[*] So Gid′e·on got up and killed Ze′bah and Zal·mun′na and took the crescent-shaped ornaments that were on the necks of their camels.

22 Later the men of Israel said to Gid′e·on: “Rule over us, you and your son and your grandson as well, for you saved us out of the hand of Mid′i·an.” 23 But Gid′e·on said to them: “I will not rule over you, nor will my son rule over you. Jehovah is the one who will rule over you.” 24 Gid′e·on continued: “Let me make one request of you: that each of you give me a nose ring from his spoil.” (For they had gold nose rings because they were Ish′ma·el·ites.) 25 They replied: “We will surely give them.” With that they spread out a robe and each man threw a nose ring from his spoil on it. 26 The weight of the gold nose rings that he had requested amounted to 1,700 gold shekels,[*] besides the crescent-shaped ornaments, the pendants, the purple wool garments worn by the kings of Mid′i·an, and the necklaces from the camels.

27 Gid′e·on made it into an eph′od and exhibited it in his city Oph′rah; and all Israel committed spiritual prostitution with it there, and it served as a snare to Gid′e·on and to his household.

28 Thus Mid′i·an was subdued before the Israelites, and they did not challenge them[*] again; and the land had rest[*] for 40 years in the days of Gid′e·on.

29 So Jer·ub·ba′al the son of Jo′ash returned to his home and stayed there.

30 Gid′e·on became father to 70 sons,[*] for he had many wives. 31 His concubine in She′chem also bore him a son, and he named him A·bim′e·lech. 32 And Gid′e·on the son of Jo′ash died at a good old age and was buried in the tomb of Jo′ash his father in Oph′rah of the Abi-ez′rites.

33 As soon as Gid′e·on died, the Israelites again committed spiritual prostitution with the Ba′als, and they appointed Ba′al-be′rith as their god. 34 The Israelites did not remember Jehovah their God, who had rescued them from the hand of all their enemies around them; 35 nor did they show loyal love toward the household of Jer·ub·ba′al, that is Gid′e·on, in return for all the good that he had done for Israel.

^ Judg. 8:3 Lit., “word.”

^ Judg. 8:3 Lit., “their spirit relaxed from against him.”

^ Judg. 8:21 Or “for as a man is, so is his strength.”

^ Judg. 8:26 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Judg. 8:28 Lit., “did not lift up their head.”

^ Judg. 8:28 Or “peace.”

^ Judg. 8:30 Lit., “had 70 sons who came out from his thigh.”

Judges  10 : 1 - 18

10 After A·bim′e·lech, To′la the son of Pu′ah, the son of Do′do, a man of Is′sa·char, rose up to save Israel. He lived in Sha′mir in the mountainous region of E′phra·im. 2 He judged Israel for 23 years. Then he died and was buried in Sha′mir.

3 After him Ja′ir the Gil′e·ad·ite rose up and judged Israel for 22 years. 4 He had 30 sons who rode on 30 donkeys, and they had 30 cities, which to this day are called Hav′voth-ja′ir; they are in the land of Gil′e·ad. 5 After that Ja′ir died and was buried in Ka′mon.

6 Again the Israelites did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and they began to serve the Ba′als, the Ash′to·reth images, the gods of A′ram,[*] the gods of Si′don, the gods of Mo′ab, the gods of the Am′mon·ites, and the gods of the Phi·lis′tines. They abandoned Jehovah and did not serve him. 7 Then Jehovah’s anger blazed against Israel, and he sold them into the hands of the Phi·lis′tines and the Am′mon·ites. 8 So they crushed and greatly oppressed the Israelites in that year—for 18 years they oppressed all the Israelites on the side of the Jordan that had been the land of the Am′or·ites in Gil′e·ad. 9 The Am′mon·ites would also cross the Jordan to fight against Judah and Benjamin and the house of E′phra·im; and Israel was greatly distressed. 10 Then the Israelites called to Jehovah for help, saying: “We have sinned against you, for we abandoned our God and served the Ba′als.”

11 But Jehovah said to the Israelites: “Did I not save you from Egypt and from the Am′or·ites, the Am′mon·ites, the Phi·lis′tines, 12 the Si·do′ni·ans, Am′a·lek, and Mid′i·an when they oppressed you? When you cried out to me, I saved you out of their hand. 13 But you abandoned me and served other gods. That is why I will not save you again. 14 Go to the gods whom you have chosen and call for help. Let them save you in your time of distress.” 15 But the Israelites said to Jehovah: “We have sinned. Do to us whatever is good in your eyes. Only save us, please, this day.” 16 And they removed the foreign gods from their midst and served Jehovah, so that he could no longer tolerate[*] Israel’s suffering.

17 In time the Am′mon·ites were called together, and they pitched camp in Gil′e·ad. So the Israelites gathered together and pitched camp in Miz′pah. 18 The people and the princes of Gil′e·ad said to one another: “Who will take the lead in fighting against the Am′mon·ites? Let him become the chief over all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.”

^ Judg. 10:6 Or “Syria.”

^ Judg. 10:16 Or “and his soul became impatient because of.”

Judges  11 : 1 - 40

11 Now Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite was a mighty warrior; he was the son of a prostitute, and Gil′e·ad was Jeph′thah’s father. 2 But Gil′e·ad’s wife also bore him sons. When the sons of his wife grew up, they drove Jeph′thah out and said to him: “You will have no inheritance in our father’s household, for you are the son of another woman.” 3 So Jeph′thah fled from his brothers and settled in the land of Tob. And idle men joined company with Jeph′thah, and they followed him.

4 After a while, the Am′mon·ites fought against Israel. 5 And when the Am′mon·ites fought against Israel, the elders of Gil′e·ad immediately went to bring Jeph′thah back from the land of Tob. 6 They said to Jeph′thah: “Come and serve as our commander, so that we can fight against the Am′mon·ites.” 7 But Jeph′thah said to the elders of Gil′e·ad: “Was it not you who hated me so much that you drove me out of my father’s house? Why have you come to me now when you are in distress?” 8 At this the elders of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “That is why now we have returned to you. If you go with us and fight against the Am′mon·ites, you will become our leader over all the inhabitants of Gil′e·ad.” 9 So Jeph′thah said to the elders of Gil′e·ad: “If you bring me back to fight against the Am′mon·ites and Jehovah defeats them for me, then I will indeed become your leader!” 10 The elders of Gil′e·ad said to Jeph′thah: “Let Jehovah be the witness[*] between us if we do not do as you say.” 11 So Jeph′thah went with the elders of Gil′e·ad, and the people made him their leader and commander. And Jeph′thah repeated all his words before Jehovah in Miz′pah.

12 Jeph′thah then sent messengers to the king of the Am′mon·ites, saying: “What do you have against me[*] that you have come to attack my land?” 13 So the king of the Am′mon·ites said to the messengers of Jeph′thah: “It is because Israel took my land when they came up out of Egypt, from the Ar′non to the Jab′bok and as far as the Jordan. Now return it peaceably.” 14 But Jeph′thah sent messengers back to the king of the Am′mon·ites 15 to say to him:

“This is what Jeph′thah says: ‘Israel did not take the land of the Mo′ab·ites and the land of the Am′mon·ites, 16 for when they came up out of Egypt, Israel walked through the wilderness as far as the Red Sea and came to Ka′desh. 17 Then Israel sent messengers to the king of E′dom, saying: “Please let us pass through your land,” but the king of E′dom did not listen. Also to the king of Mo′ab they sent word, but he did not consent. So Israel kept dwelling in Ka′desh. 18 When they walked through the wilderness, they bypassed the land of E′dom and the land of Mo′ab. They traveled east of the land of Mo′ab and camped in the region of the Ar′non; they did not come within the boundary of Mo′ab, for the Ar′non was the boundary of Mo′ab.

19 “‘After that Israel sent messengers to Si′hon king of the Am′or·ites, king of Hesh′bon, and Israel said to him: “Please let us pass through your land to our own place.” 20 But Si′hon did not trust Israel to cross through his territory, so Si′hon gathered all his people together and encamped in Ja′haz and fought against Israel. 21 At this Jehovah the God of Israel gave Si′hon and all his people into Israel’s hand, so that they defeated them and Israel took possession of all the land of the Am′or·ites, the inhabitants of that land. 22 Thus they took possession of all the territory of the Am′or·ites from the Ar′non to the Jab′bok and from the wilderness to the Jordan.

23 “‘It was Jehovah the God of Israel who drove out the Am′or·ites from before his people Israel, and now would you drive them out? 24 Do you not possess whatever your god Che′mosh gives you to possess? So everyone whom Jehovah our God has driven out from before us is the one we will drive out. 25 Now are you any better than Ba′lak the son of Zip′por, the king of Mo′ab? Did he ever contend with Israel, or did he ever fight against them? 26 While Israel was dwelling in Hesh′bon and its dependent[*] towns and in A·ro′er and its dependent towns and in all the cities that are by the banks of the Ar′non for 300 years, why did you never try to take them back during that time? 27 I have not sinned against you, but you are wrong to attack me. Let Jehovah the Judge be judge today between the people of Israel and the people of Am′mon.’”

28 But the king of the Am′mon·ites would not listen to the message that Jeph′thah sent to him.

29 Jehovah’s spirit came upon Jeph′thah, and he passed through Gil′e·ad and Ma·nas′seh to go to Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad, and from Miz′peh of Gil′e·ad he continued on to the Am′mon·ites.

30 Then Jeph′thah made a vow to Jehovah and said: “If you give the Am′mon·ites into my hand, 31 then whoever comes out of the door of my house to meet me when I return in peace from the Am′mon·ites will become Jehovah’s, and I will offer that one up as a burnt offering.”

32 So Jeph′thah went to fight against the Am′mon·ites, and Jehovah gave them into his hand. 33 He struck them down with a very great slaughter from A·ro′er all the way to Min′nith—20 cities—and as far as A′bel-ker′a·mim. Thus the Am′mon·ites were subdued before the Israelites.

34 Finally Jeph′thah came to his home in Miz′pah, and look! his daughter was coming out to meet him, playing the tambourine and dancing! Now she was his one and only child. Besides her, he had neither son nor daughter. 35 When he saw her, he ripped his garments and said: “Oh no, my daughter! You have broken my heart,[*] for you have become the one I have banished. Now I have opened my mouth to Jehovah, and I am unable to turn back.”

36 But she said to him: “My father, if you have opened your mouth to Jehovah, do to me as you have promised, since Jehovah has executed vengeance for you upon your enemies, the Am′mon·ites.” 37 She then said to her father: “Let this be done for me: Let me be alone for two months, and let me go away into the mountains, and let me weep over my virginity with my female companions.”[*]

38 At this he said: “Go!” So he sent her away for two months, and she went to the mountains with her companions to weep over her virginity. 39 At the end of two months, she returned to her father, after which he carried out the vow he had made regarding her. She never had relations with a man. And it became a custom[*] in Israel: 40 From year to year, the young women of Israel would go to give commendation to the daughter of Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite four days in the year.

^ Judg. 11:10 Lit., “the one who hears.”

^ Judg. 11:12 Lit., “What to me and to you?”

^ Judg. 11:26 Or “surrounding.”

^ Judg. 11:35 Lit., “You brought me very low.”

^ Judg. 11:37 Or “weep with my friends because I will never marry.”

^ Judg. 11:39 Or “regulation.”

Judges  12 : 1 - 15

12 Then the men of E′phra·im were summoned, and they crossed over to Za′phon[*] and said to Jeph′thah: “Why did you not call us to go with you when you crossed over to fight against the Am′mon·ites? We will burn your house down with you in it.” 2 But Jeph′thah said to them: “Along with my people, I was engaged in a great conflict with the Am′mon·ites. I did call to you for help, but you did not save me from their hand. 3 When I saw that you would not save me, then I decided to risk my life[*] and go against the Am′mon·ites, and Jehovah handed them over to me. So why have you come today to fight against me?”

4 Jeph′thah then gathered all the men of Gil′e·ad, and they fought E′phra·im; the men of Gil′e·ad defeated E′phra·im, who had said: “You are only fugitives from E′phra·im, you Gil′e·ad·ites in E′phra·im and Ma·nas′seh.” 5 Gil′e·ad captured the fords of the Jordan ahead of E′phra·im; and when the men of E′phra·im were trying to escape, they would say, “Let me cross over”; then the men of Gil′e·ad would ask each one, “Are you an E′phra·im·ite?” When he would reply, “No!” 6 they would say to him, “Please say Shib′bo·leth.” But he would say, “Sib′bo·leth,” as he was unable to say the word correctly. Then they would seize him and slay him at the fords of the Jordan. So 42,000 E′phra·im·ites fell at that time.

7 Jeph′thah judged Israel for six years, after which Jeph′thah the Gil′e·ad·ite died and was buried in his city in Gil′e·ad.

8 Ib′zan from Beth′le·hem judged Israel after him. 9 He had 30 sons and 30 daughters. He sent his daughters to marry men outside his clan, and he brought in 30 women to marry his sons. He judged Israel for seven years. 10 Then Ib′zan died and was buried in Beth′le·hem.

11 After him E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite judged Israel; he judged Israel for ten years. 12 Then E′lon the Ze·bu′lu·nite died and was buried in Ai′ja·lon in the land of Zeb′u·lun.

13 After him Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite judged Israel. 14 He had 40 sons and 30 grandsons who rode on 70 donkeys. He judged Israel for eight years. 15 Then Ab′don the son of Hil′lel the Pir′a·thon·ite died and was buried in Pir′a·thon in the land of E′phra·im in the mountain of the A·mal′ek·ite.

^ Judg. 12:1 Or possibly, “crossed over northward.”

^ Judg. 12:3 Or “I put my soul in my hand.”

Judges  15 : 1 - 20

15 After a while, in the days of the wheat harvest, Samson went to visit his wife, bringing a young goat. He said: “I wish to go in to my wife in the bedroom.”[*] But her father did not allow him to go in. 2 Her father said: “I thought, ‘You must surely hate her.’ So I gave her to your groomsman. Is not her younger sister more attractive than she is? Please, take her instead.” 3 However, Samson said to them: “This time I cannot be blamed by the Phi·lis′tines for harming them.”

4 So Samson went and caught 300 foxes. Then he took torches, turned the foxes tail to tail, and put one torch between each pair of tails. 5 Then he set fire to the torches and sent the foxes out into the fields of standing grain of the Phi·lis′tines. He set on fire everything from sheaf to standing grain, as well as the vineyards and the olive groves.

6 The Phi·lis′tines asked: “Who did this?” They were told: “It was Samson, the son-in-law of the Tim′nite, because he took his wife and gave her to his groomsman.” At that the Phi·lis′tines went up and burned her and her father with fire. 7 Then Samson said to them: “If this is how you act, I will not quit until I take revenge on you.” 8 Then he struck them down one after the other[*] with a great slaughter, after which he went down and stayed in a cave[*] of the crag E′tam.

9 Later the Phi·lis′tines came up and camped in Judah and were tramping about in Le′hi. 10 Then the men of Judah said: “Why have you come up against us?” to which they answered: “We have come up to capture[*] Samson, to do to him just as he did to us.” 11 So 3,000 men of Judah went down to the cave[*] of the crag E′tam and said to Samson: “Do you not know that the Phi·lis′tines are ruling over us? So why have you done this to us?” He said to them: “As they did to me, so I did to them.” 12 But they said to him: “We have come to capture[*] you and to hand you over to the Phi·lis′tines.” Then Samson said: “Swear to me that you yourselves will not assault me.” 13 They said to him: “No, we will only tie you and hand you over to them, but we will not put you to death.”

So they bound him with two new ropes and brought him up from the crag. 14 When he came to Le′hi, the Phi·lis′tines shouted triumphantly at meeting him. Then Jehovah’s spirit empowered him, and the ropes on his arms became like linen threads that were scorched with fire, and his fetters melted off his hands. 15 He now found a fresh jawbone of a male donkey; he reached out and grabbed it and struck down 1,000 men with it. 16 Then Samson said:

“With the jawbone of a donkey—one heap, two heaps!

With the jawbone of a donkey I struck down 1,000 men.”

17 When he finished speaking, he threw the jawbone away and called that place Ra′math-le′hi.[*] 18 Then he became very thirsty, and he called on Jehovah and said: “It was you who gave this great salvation into the hand of your servant. But now am I to die of thirst and fall into the hands of the uncircumcised?” 19 So God split open a hollow that was in Le′hi, and water flowed from it. When he drank, his spirit[*] returned and he revived. That is why he named the place En-hak·kor′e,[*] which is in Le′hi to this day.

20 And he judged Israel in the days of the Phi·lis′tines for 20 years.

^ Judg. 15:1 Or “the interior room.”

^ Judg. 15:8 Lit., “struck them leg on thigh.”

^ Judg. 15:8 Or “cleft.”

^ Judg. 15:10 Or “tie.”

^ Judg. 15:11 Or “cleft.”

^ Judg. 15:12 Or “tie.”

^ Judg. 15:17 Meaning “Lofty Place of the Jawbone.”

^ Judg. 15:19 Or “strength.”

^ Judg. 15:19 Meaning “Spring of the One Calling.”

Judges  18 : 1 - 31

18 In those days there was no king in Israel. And in those days the tribe of the Dan′ites was looking for an inheritance to dwell in, because until then they had not received an inheritance among the tribes of Israel.

2 The Dan′ites sent five men from among their family, capable men from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol, to spy out the land and to explore it. They said to them: “Go, explore the land.” When they came to the mountainous region of E′phra·im, to the house of Mi′cah, they spent the night there. 3 While they were near the house of Mi′cah, they recognized the voice[*] of the young Levite man, so they went over to him and asked: “Who brought you here? What are you doing in this place? What is keeping you here?” 4 He replied to them: “Thus and so Mi′cah did for me, and he hired me to serve as priest for him.” 5 Then they said to him: “Please ask God whether our journey will be successful.” 6 The priest said to them: “Go in peace. Jehovah is with you on your journey.”

7 So the five men went on and came to La′ish. They saw how the people in it were dwelling in self-reliance in the manner of the Si·do′ni·ans. They were quiet and unsuspecting, and no oppressive conqueror was in the land to disturb them. They were far away from the Si·do′ni·ans, and they had no dealings with anyone else.

8 When they returned to their brothers at Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol, their brothers said to them: “How did it go?” 9 They replied: “Let us go up against them, for we have seen that the land is very good. Why are you hesitant? Do not delay to go in to take possession of the land. 10 When you arrive, you will find an unsuspecting people, and the land is spacious. God has given it into your hand, a place where there is no lack of anything on the earth.”

11 Then 600 men armed for battle from the family of the Dan′ites departed from Zo′rah and Esh′ta·ol. 12 They went up and camped at Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim in Judah. That is why that place, which is west of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, is called Ma′ha·neh-dan[*] to this day. 13 They went from there to the mountainous region of E′phra·im and came to the house of Mi′cah.

14 Then the five men who had gone to spy out the land of La′ish said to their brothers: “Did you know that there are in these houses an eph′od, teraphim statues,[*] a carved image, and a metal statue?[*] Think about what you should do.” 15 So they stopped there and came to the house of the young Levite man at the house of Mi′cah and asked how he was. 16 All the while the 600 men of Dan, armed for battle, stood at the entrance of the gate. 17 The five men who had gone to spy out the land went inside to take the carved image, the eph′od, the teraphim statues,[*] and the metal image.[*] (The priest was standing at the entrance of the gate with the 600 men armed for battle.) 18 They went into the house of Mi′cah and took the carved image, the eph′od, the teraphim statues,[*] and the metal image.[*] The priest said to them: “What are you doing?” 19 But they said to him: “Be quiet. Put your hand over your mouth, and come with us to be a father[*] and a priest for us. Which is better—for you to be a priest to the house of one man or to become a priest to a tribe and family in Israel?” 20 So the priest was satisfied, and he took the eph′od, the teraphim statues,[*] and the carved image and went off with the people.

21 Then they turned to go on their way, putting the children, the livestock, and the valuable things ahead of them. 22 They had gone some distance away from the house of Mi′cah when the men who lived in the houses near the house of Mi′cah gathered together and caught up with the Dan′ites. 23 When they cried out to the Dan′ites, they turned to face them and said to Mi′cah: “What is the matter? Why have you been gathered together?” 24 So he said: “You have taken my gods that I made, and you have gone off with the priest too. What do I have left? How, then, can you ask me, ‘What is the matter with you?’” 25 The Dan′ites replied: “Do not raise your voice against us; otherwise, angry men[*] may assault you, and that would cost you your life[*] and the lives[*] of your household.” 26 So the Dan′ites went on their way; and Mi′cah, seeing that they were stronger than he was, turned and went back to his house.

27 After they took what Mi′cah had made, as well as his priest, they went to La′ish, to a people quiet and unsuspecting. They struck them down with the sword and burned the city with fire. 28 There was no one to rescue it, for it was far from Si′don and they had no dealings with anyone else and it was in the valley plain[*] that belonged to Beth-re′hob. Then they rebuilt the city and settled in it. 29 Furthermore, they named the city Dan after the name of their father, Dan, who was born to Israel. But La′ish was the city’s former name. 30 After that the Dan′ites set up the carved image for themselves, and Jon′a·than the son of Ger′shom, the son of Moses, and his sons became priests to the tribe of the Dan′ites until the day that the inhabitants of the land went into exile. 31 And they set up the carved image that Mi′cah had made, and it remained there all the days that the house of the true God was in Shi′loh.

^ Judg. 18:3 Or “accent.”

^ Judg. 18:12 Meaning “Camp of Dan.”

^ Judg. 18:14 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ Judg. 18:14 Or “molten statue.”

^ Judg. 18:17 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ Judg. 18:17 Or “molten statue.”

^ Judg. 18:18 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ Judg. 18:18 Or “molten statue.”

^ Judg. 18:19 Or “an adviser.”

^ Judg. 18:20 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ Judg. 18:25 Or “men bitter of soul.”

^ Judg. 18:25 Or “soul.”

^ Judg. 18:25 Or “souls.”

^ Judg. 18:28 Or “low plain.”

Ruth  1 : 1 - 22

RUTH

1 Now in the days when the judges administered justice,[*] a famine occurred in the land; and a man went from Beth′le·hem in Judah to reside as a foreigner in the fields[*] of Mo′ab, he along with his wife and his two sons. 2 The man’s name was E·lim′e·lech,[*] his wife’s name was Na·o′mi,[*] and the names of his two sons were Mah′lon[*] and Chil′i·on.[*] They were Eph′rath·ites from Beth′le·hem in Judah. And they came to the fields of Mo′ab and remained there.

3 After some time E·lim′e·lech, Na·o′mi’s husband, died, and she was left with her two sons. 4 The men later married Mo′ab·ite women; one was named Or′pah, and the other was named Ruth. They remained there for about ten years. 5 Then the two sons, Mah′lon and Chil′i·on, also died, and the woman was left without her two children and her husband. 6 So she started out with her daughters-in-law to return from the fields of Mo′ab, for she had heard in Mo′ab that Jehovah had turned his attention to his people by giving them food.[*]

7 She left the place where she had been living with both of her daughters-in-law. As they were walking on the road to return to the land of Judah, 8 Na·o′mi said to both of her daughters-in-law: “Go, return, each of you to your mother’s home. May Jehovah show loyal love to you, just as you have shown it to the men who have died and to me. 9 May Jehovah grant[*] that each of you finds security[*] in the home of your husband.” Then she kissed them, and they wept loudly. 10 They kept saying to her: “No, but we will go with you to your people.” 11 But Na·o′mi said: “Return, my daughters. Why should you go with me? Can I still give birth to sons who could become your husbands? 12 Return, my daughters. Go, for I have grown too old to marry. Even if I could hope to find a husband tonight and could also bear sons, 13 would you keep waiting for them until they could grow up? Would you refrain from getting remarried for their sakes? No, my daughters, I feel very bitter for you, because the hand of Jehovah has turned against me.”

14 Again they wept loudly, after which Or′pah kissed her mother-in-law and departed. But Ruth stuck with her. 15 So Na·o′mi said: “Look! Your widowed sister-in-law has returned to her people and her gods. Return with your sister-in-law.”

16 But Ruth said: “Do not plead with me to abandon you, to turn back from accompanying you; for where you go I will go, and where you spend the night, I will spend the night. Your people will be my people, and your God my God. 17 Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May Jehovah do so to me and add to it if anything but death should separate me from you.”

18 When Na·o′mi saw that Ruth insisted on going with her, she stopped trying to convince her. 19 And they both continued on their way until they came to Beth′le·hem. As soon as they arrived in Beth′le·hem, the whole city became stirred up over them, and women were saying: “Is this Na·o′mi?” 20 She would say to the women: “Do not call me Na·o′mi.[*] Call me Ma′ra,[*] for the Almighty has made life very bitter for me. 21 I was full when I went, but Jehovah made me return empty-handed. Why should you call me Na·o′mi, when it is Jehovah who opposed me and the Almighty who caused me calamity?”

22 This is how Na·o′mi returned from the fields of Mo′ab, along with her Mo′ab·ite daughter-in-law Ruth. They came to Beth′le·hem at the beginning of the barley harvest.

^ Ruth 1:1 Or “ruled.”

^ Ruth 1:1 Or “region.”

^ Ruth 1:2 Meaning “My God Is King.”

^ Ruth 1:2 Meaning “My Pleasantness.”

^ Ruth 1:2 Possibly from a Hebrew word meaning “grow weak; fall sick.”

^ Ruth 1:2 Meaning “One Failing; One Coming to an End.”

^ Ruth 1:6 Lit., “bread.”

^ Ruth 1:9 Or “make a gift.”

^ Ruth 1:9 Lit., “a resting-place.”

^ Ruth 1:20 Meaning “My Pleasantness.”

^ Ruth 1:20 Meaning “Bitter.”

1 Samuel  1 : 1 - 28

THE FIRST OF SAMUEL

1 Now there was a man of Ra·math·a′im-zo′phim[*] of the mountainous region of E′phra·im whose name was El·ka′nah, the son of Je·ro′ham, the son of E·li′hu, the son of To′hu, the son of Zuph, an E′phra·im·ite. 2 He had two wives; one was named Han′nah, and the other was named Pe·nin′nah. Pe·nin′nah had children, but Han′nah had no children. 3 That man went up from his city year after year to worship[*] and to sacrifice to Jehovah of armies in Shi′loh. That is where the two sons of E′li, Hoph′ni and Phin′e·has, served as priests to Jehovah.

4 One day when El·ka′nah offered a sacrifice, he gave portions to his wife Pe·nin′nah as well as to all her sons and her daughters, 5 but to Han′nah he gave a special portion, because Han′nah was the one he loved; but Jehovah had not given her children.[*] 6 Moreover, her rival wife taunted her relentlessly in order to upset her because Jehovah had not given her children. 7 That is what she would do year after year; whenever Han′nah went up to the house of Jehovah, her rival would taunt her so much that she would weep and not eat. 8 But her husband El·ka′nah said to her: “Han′nah, why do you weep, and why do you not eat, and why are you so sad?[*] Am I not better to you than ten sons?”

9 Then Han′nah got up after they had finished eating and drinking in Shi′loh. At the time, E′li the priest was sitting on the seat by the doorpost of the temple[*] of Jehovah. 10 Han′nah was extremely bitter,[*] and she began to pray to Jehovah and to weep uncontrollably. 11 And she made this vow: “O Jehovah of armies, if you look upon the affliction of your servant and remember me and you do not forget your servant and give to your servant a male child, I will give him to Jehovah all the days of his life, and no razor will touch his head.”

12 While she prayed for a long time before Jehovah, E′li was watching her mouth. 13 Han′nah was speaking in her heart, only her lips were trembling, but her voice was not heard. So E′li thought she was drunk. 14 E′li said to her: “How long will you stay drunk? Stop drinking your wine.” 15 At this Han′nah answered: “No, my lord! I am a woman under great stress;[*] I have not drunk wine or anything alcoholic, but I am pouring out my soul[*] before Jehovah. 16 Do not take your servant for a worthless woman, for I have been speaking until now out of my great anguish and distress.” 17 Then E′li answered: “Go in peace, and may the God of Israel grant your petition that you have asked of him.” 18 To this she said: “Let your servant find favor in your eyes.” And the woman went on her way and ate, and her face was no longer downcast.

19 Then they got up early in the morning and bowed before Jehovah, after which they returned to their house in Ra′mah. El·ka′nah had sexual relations with his wife Han′nah, and Jehovah gave attention to[*] her. 20 Within a year[*] Han′nah became pregnant and gave birth to a son and named him Samuel,[*] because, as she said, “it is from Jehovah that I have asked him.”

21 In time El·ka′nah went up with all his household to offer the yearly sacrifice to Jehovah and to present his vow offering. 22 But Han′nah did not go up, for she said to her husband: “As soon as the boy is weaned, I will bring him; then he will appear before Jehovah and remain there from then on.” 23 El·ka′nah her husband then said to her: “Do what you think is best.[*] Stay at home until you wean him. May Jehovah carry out what you have said.” So the woman stayed at home and nursed her son until she weaned him.

24 As soon as she had weaned him, she took him up to Shi′loh, along with a three-year-old bull, one e′phah[*] of flour, and a large jar of wine, and she came to the house of Jehovah in Shi′loh and brought the young boy with her. 25 Then they slaughtered the bull and brought the boy to E′li. 26 With that she said: “Pardon me, my lord! As surely as you live,[*] my lord, I am the woman who was standing with you in this place to pray to Jehovah. 27 It was for this boy that I prayed, and Jehovah granted my petition that I asked of him. 28 I, in turn, now lend him to Jehovah. For all his days, he is lent to Jehovah.”

And he[*] bowed down there to Jehovah.

^ 1 Sam. 1:1 Or “of Ramah, a Zuphite.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:3 Or “bow down.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:5 Lit., “had closed her womb.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:8 Or “why does your heart feel bad?”

^ 1 Sam. 1:9 That is, the tabernacle.

^ 1 Sam. 1:10 Or “bitter of soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:15 Or “a woman hard-pressed in spirit.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:15 See Glossary.

^ 1 Sam. 1:19 Lit., “remembered.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:20 Or possibly, “In due time.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:20 Meaning “Name of God.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:23 Lit., “what is good in your eyes.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:24 About 22 L (20 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 1:26 Or “By the life of your soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 1:28 Evidently referring to Elkanah.

1 Samuel  7 : 1 - 17

7 So the men of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim came and took the Ark of Jehovah up into the house of A·bin′a·dab on the hill, and they sanctified his son El·e·a′zar to guard the Ark of Jehovah.

2 A long time elapsed, 20 years in all, from the day of the Ark’s coming to Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, and all the house of Israel began to seek[*] after Jehovah. 3 Samuel then said to all the house of Israel: “If you are returning to Jehovah with all your heart, put away the foreign gods and the Ash′to·reth images from among you, and direct your heart unswervingly to Jehovah and serve only him, and he will rescue you from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.” 4 At that the Israelites got rid of the Ba′als and the Ash′to·reth images and served only Jehovah.

5 Then Samuel said: “Gather all Israel together at Miz′pah, and I will pray to Jehovah in your behalf.” 6 So they gathered together at Miz′pah, and they drew water and poured it out before Jehovah and kept a fast on that day. There they said: “We have sinned against Jehovah.” And Samuel began serving as judge over the Israelites in Miz′pah.

7 When the Phi·lis′tines heard that the Israelites had gathered together at Miz′pah, the lords of the Phi·lis′tines went up against Israel. When the Israelites heard of it, they were afraid because of the Phi·lis′tines. 8 So the Israelites said to Samuel: “Do not stop calling to Jehovah our God to help us and to save us from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.” 9 Then Samuel took a suckling lamb and offered it up as a whole burnt offering to Jehovah; and Samuel called to Jehovah for help in behalf of Israel, and Jehovah answered him. 10 As Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Phi·lis′tines advanced for battle against Israel. Jehovah now caused it to thunder loudly on that day against the Phi·lis′tines, and He threw them into confusion, and they were defeated before Israel. 11 At that the men of Israel went out from Miz′pah and pursued the Phi·lis′tines, striking them down as far as south of Beth-car. 12 Then Samuel took a stone and set it between Miz′pah and Jesh′a·nah and named it Eb·en·e′zer,[*] for he said: “Until now Jehovah has helped us.” 13 Thus the Phi·lis′tines were subdued, and they did not come again into the territory of Israel; and the hand of Jehovah continued against the Phi·lis′tines all the days of Samuel. 14 Also, the cities that the Phi·lis′tines had taken from Israel were returned to Israel, from Ek′ron to Gath, and Israel recovered their territory from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines.

There was also peace between Israel and the Am′or·ites.

15 Samuel kept on judging Israel throughout his life. 16 Each year he traveled in a circuit to Beth′el, Gil′gal, and Miz′pah, and he judged Israel in all these places. 17 But he would return to Ra′mah, because his house was there, and there he also judged Israel. He built an altar there to Jehovah.

^ 1 Sam. 7:2 Or “mourn.”

^ 1 Sam. 7:12 Meaning “Stone of Help.”

1 Samuel  17 : 1 - 58

17 And the Phi·lis′tines assembled their armies[*] for war. They assembled at So′coh, which belongs to Judah, and they camped between So′coh and A·ze′kah, in E′phes-dam′mim. 2 Saul and the men of Israel assembled and camped in the Valley[*] of E′lah, and they drew up in battle formation to meet the Phi·lis′tines. 3 The Phi·lis′tines occupied the mountain on one side, and the Israelites occupied the mountain on the other side, with the valley between them.

4 Then a champion came out from the camps of the Phi·lis′tines; his name was Go·li′ath, from Gath, and his height was six cubits and a span.[*] 5 He had a helmet of copper on his head, and he was wearing a coat of mail of overlapping scales. The weight of the copper coat of mail was 5,000 shekels.[*] 6 He had shin guards of copper on his legs and a javelin of copper slung between his shoulders. 7 The wooden shaft of his spear was like the beam of loom workers, and the iron blade of his spear weighed 600 shekels;[*] and his shield-bearer was marching ahead of him. 8 Then he stood and called out to the battle line of Israel and said to them: “Why have you come out to draw up in battle formation? Am I not the Phi·lis′tine, and are you not the servants of Saul? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him come down to me. 9 If he is able to fight with me and strike me down, we will then become your servants. But if I prevail against him and strike him down, you will become our servants and serve us.” 10 The Phi·lis′tine then said: “I do taunt[*] the battle line of Israel this day. Give me a man, and let us fight it out!”

11 When Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Phi·lis′tine, they became terrified and greatly afraid.

12 Now David was the son of the Eph′rath·ite from Beth′le·hem of Judah named Jes′se, who had eight sons and who in the days of Saul was already an old man. 13 The three oldest sons of Jes′se had followed Saul to the war. The names of his three sons who went to war were E·li′ab the firstborn, his second son A·bin′a·dab, and the third Sham′mah. 14 David was the youngest, and the three oldest followed Saul.

15 David was going back and forth from Saul to tend the sheep of his father at Beth′le·hem. 16 Meanwhile, the Phi·lis′tine would come forward and take his position each morning and each evening for 40 days.

17 Then Jes′se said to his son David: “Take, please, this e′phah[*] of roasted grain and these ten loaves of bread, and carry them quickly to your brothers in the camp. 18 And take these ten portions of cheese[*] to the chief of the thousand; also, you should check on the welfare of your brothers and bring back some token from them.” 19 They were with Saul and all the other men of Israel in the Valley[*] of E′lah, fighting against the Phi·lis′tines.

20 So David got up early in the morning and left someone in charge of the sheep; then he packed up and went just as Jes′se had commanded him. When he came to the camp enclosure, the army was going out to the battle line, shouting a battle cry. 21 Israel and the Phi·lis′tines drew up so that one battle line faced the other battle line. 22 David immediately left his baggage in the care of the baggage keeper and ran to the battle line. When he arrived, he began asking about the welfare of his brothers.

23 While he was speaking with them, there came the champion named Go·li′ath, the Phi·lis′tine from Gath. He came out from the battle line of the Phi·lis′tines, and he spoke the same words as before, and David heard him. 24 When all the men of Israel saw the man, they fled from him, terrified. 25 The men of Israel were saying: “Have you seen this man who is coming out? He comes to taunt[*] Israel. The king will give great riches to the man who strikes him down, he will give him his own daughter, and he will give the house of his father exemption in Israel.”

26 David began to say to the men who were standing near him: “What will be done for the man who strikes down that Phi·lis′tine over there and takes away reproach from Israel? For who is this uncircumcised Phi·lis′tine that he should taunt[*] the battle line of the living God?” 27 Then the people told him the same thing as before: “This is what will be done for the man who strikes him down.” 28 When his oldest brother E·li′ab heard him speak to the men, he became angry with David and said: “Why have you come down? And with whom did you leave those few sheep in the wilderness? I well know your presumptuousness and the bad intentions of your heart; you came down just to see the battle.” 29 To this David said: “What have I done now? I was only asking a question!” 30 So he turned from him toward someone else and asked the same thing as before, and the people gave him the same reply as before.

31 The words that David had spoken were overheard and reported to Saul. So he sent for him. 32 David said to Saul: “Let no one lose heart[*] because of him. Your servant will go and fight with this Phi·lis′tine.” 33 But Saul said to David: “You are not able to go fight against this Phi·lis′tine, for you are but a boy, and he has been a soldier[*] from his youth.” 34 David then said to Saul: “Your servant became a shepherd of his father’s flock, and a lion came, also a bear, and each carried off a sheep from the flock. 35 I went out after it and struck it down and rescued it from its mouth. When it rose up against me, I grabbed it by its fur[*] and struck it down and put it to death. 36 Your servant struck down both the lion and the bear, and this uncircumcised Phi·lis′tine will become like one of them, for he has taunted[*] the battle lines of the living God.” 37 Then David added: “Jehovah, who rescued me from the claws of the lion and the bear, he is the one who will rescue me from the hand of this Phi·lis′tine.” At this Saul said to David: “Go, and may Jehovah be with you.”

38 Saul now clothed David with his garments. He put a copper helmet on his head, after which he clothed him with a coat of mail. 39 Then David strapped on his sword over his garments and tried to go but could not, for he was not used to them. David said to Saul: “I am unable to go in these things, for I am not used to them.” So David took them off. 40 He then took his staff in his hand and chose five smooth stones from the streambed[*] and placed them in the pouch of his shepherd’s bag, and his sling was in his hand. And he began approaching the Phi·lis′tine.

41 The Phi·lis′tine came closer and closer to David, and his shield-bearer was ahead of him. 42 When the Phi·lis′tine looked and saw David, he sneered at him in contempt because he was just a ruddy and handsome boy. 43 So the Phi·lis′tine said to David: “Am I a dog, so that you are coming against me with sticks?” With that the Phi·lis′tine cursed David by his gods. 44 The Phi·lis′tine said to David: “Just come to me, and I will give your flesh to the birds of the heavens and to the beasts of the field.”

45 David replied to the Phi·lis′tine: “You are coming against me with sword and spear and javelin, but I am coming against you in the name of Jehovah of armies, the God of the battle line of Israel, whom you have taunted.[*] 46 This very day Jehovah will surrender you into my hand, and I will strike you down and cut off your head; and on this day I will give the corpses of the camp of the Phi·lis′tines to the birds of the heavens and to the wild beasts of the earth; and people of all the earth will know that there is a God in Israel. 47 And all those gathered here[*] will know that it is not with the sword or the spear that Jehovah saves, for the battle belongs to Jehovah, and he will give all of you into our hand.”

48 Then the Phi·lis′tine rose and drew steadily closer to meet David, but David ran quickly toward the battle line to meet the Phi·lis′tine. 49 David thrust his hand into his bag and took a stone from there and slung it. He struck the Phi·lis′tine in the forehead, and the stone sank into his forehead and he fell facedown on the ground. 50 So David prevailed over the Phi·lis′tine with a sling and a stone; he struck down the Phi·lis′tine and put him to death, though there was no sword in David’s hand. 51 David continued running and stood over him. Then he took hold of the Phi·lis′tine’s sword and pulled it out of its sheath and made sure that he was dead by cutting off his head with it. When the Phi·lis′tines saw that their mighty one had died, they fled.

52 At that the men of Israel and of Judah rose and broke into shouting and pursued the Phi·lis′tines all the way from the valley to the gates of Ek′ron, and the slain of the Phi·lis′tines lay fallen along the road from Sha′a·ra′im, as far as Gath and Ek′ron. 53 After the Israelites returned from hotly pursuing the Phi·lis′tines, they pillaged their camps.

54 Then David took the head of the Phi·lis′tine and brought it to Jerusalem, but he put the Phi·lis′tine’s weapons in his own tent.

55 At the moment that Saul saw David go out to meet the Phi·lis′tine, he said to Ab′ner, the chief of the army: “Whose son is this boy, Ab′ner?” Ab′ner replied: “As surely as you live,[*] O king, I do not know!” 56 The king said: “Find out whose son the young man is.” 57 So as soon as David returned from striking down the Phi·lis′tine, Ab′ner took him and brought him before Saul with the head of the Phi·lis′tine in his hand. 58 Saul now said to him: “Whose son are you, boy?” to which David said: “The son of your servant Jes′se the Beth′le·hem·ite.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:1 Lit., “camps.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:2 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:4 His height was about 2.9 m (9 ft 5.75 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:5 About 57 kg (125 lb). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:7 About 6.84 kg (15 lb). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:10 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:17 About 22 L (20 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:18 Lit., “milk.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:19 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:25 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:26 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:32 Or “courage.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:33 Or “a man of war.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:35 Or “by the jaw.” Lit., “by its beard.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:36 Or “challenged.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:40 Or “wadi.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:45 Or “challenged.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:47 Lit., “all this congregation.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:55 Or “By the life of your soul.”

1 Samuel  25 : 1 - 44

25 In time Samuel died; and all Israel gathered together to mourn for him and to bury him at his house in Ra′mah. Then David rose and went down to the wilderness of Pa′ran.

2 Now there was a man in Ma′on whose work was in Car′mel.[*] The man was very wealthy; he had 3,000 sheep and 1,000 goats, and he was then shearing his sheep at Car′mel. 3 The man’s name was Na′bal, and his wife’s name was Ab′i·gail. The wife was discerning and beautiful, but the husband, a Ca′leb·ite, was harsh, and he behaved badly. 4 David heard in the wilderness that Na′bal was shearing his sheep. 5 So David sent ten young men to him, and David told the young men: “Go up to Car′mel, and when you come to Na′bal, ask him in my name about his welfare. 6 Then say, ‘May you live long and may you be well[*] and may your household be well and may all that you have be well. 7 Now I hear that you are doing your shearing. When your shepherds were with us, we did not harm them, and they found nothing missing the whole time they were in Car′mel. 8 Ask your young men, and they will tell you. May my young men find favor in your eyes, because we have come at a joyous time.[*] Please give to your servants and to your son David whatever you can spare.’”

9 So David’s young men went and told all of this to Na′bal in David’s name. When they finished, 10 Na′bal answered David’s servants: “Who is David, and who is the son of Jes′se? Nowadays many servants are breaking away from their masters. 11 Do I have to take my bread and my water and the meat that I butchered for my shearers and give it to men who come from who knows where?”

12 At that David’s young men returned and reported all these words to him. 13 David immediately said to his men: “Everyone strap on your sword!” So they all strapped on their swords, and David also strapped on his own sword, and about 400 men went up with David, while 200 men stayed with the baggage.

14 Meanwhile, one of the servants reported to Ab′i·gail, Na′bal’s wife: “Look! David sent messengers from the wilderness to wish our master well, but he screamed insults at them. 15 Those men were very good to us. They never harmed us, and we did not miss a single thing the whole time we were together with them in the fields. 16 They were like a protective wall around us, both by night and by day, the whole time we were with them shepherding the flock. 17 Now decide what you are going to do, for disaster has been determined against our master and against all his house, and he is such a worthless[*] man that no one can speak to him.”

18 So Ab′i·gail quickly took 200 loaves of bread, two large jars of wine, five dressed sheep, five seah measures[*] of roasted grain, 100 cakes of raisins, and 200 cakes of pressed figs and put all of it on the donkeys. 19 Then she said to her servants: “Go on ahead of me; I will follow you.” But she said nothing to her husband Na′bal.

20 While she was riding on the donkey and going down under cover of the mountain, just then David and his men were coming down toward her, and she met them. 21 Now David had been saying: “It was for nothing that I guarded everything that belongs to this fellow in the wilderness. Not a single thing belonging to him went missing, and yet he repays me evil for good. 22 May God do the same and more to the enemies of David[*] if I allow a single male[*] of his to survive until the morning.”

23 When Ab′i·gail caught sight of David, she hurried down off the donkey and threw herself facedown before David, bowing to the ground. 24 She then fell at his feet and said: “My lord, let the blame be on me; let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl. 25 Please, do not let my lord pay attention to this worthless Na′bal, for he is just like his name. Na′bal[*] is his name, and senselessness is with him. But I, your servant girl, did not see my lord’s young men whom you sent. 26 And now, my lord, as surely as Jehovah is living and as you are[*] living, it is Jehovah who has held you back from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge[*] with your own hand. May your enemies and those seeking injury to my lord become like Na′bal. 27 Now let this gift[*] that your servant girl has brought to my lord be given to the young men who are following my lord. 28 Pardon, please, the transgression of your servant girl, for Jehovah will without fail make for my lord a lasting house, because my lord is fighting the wars of Jehovah, and no evil has been found in you all your days. 29 When someone rises up to pursue you and seeks your life,[*] the life[*] of my lord will be wrapped securely in the bag of life with Jehovah your God, but the lives[*] of your enemies he will hurl away like stones from a sling.[*] 30 And when Jehovah has done for my lord all the good things he has promised and he appoints you as leader over Israel, 31 you will have no remorse or regret[*] in your heart for shedding blood without cause and for letting the hand of my lord take revenge.[*] When Jehovah confers good upon my lord, remember your servant girl.”

32 At this David said to Ab′i·gail: “Praise Jehovah the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me! 33 And blessed be your good sense! May you be blessed for restraining me this day from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge[*] with my own hands. 34 Otherwise, as surely as Jehovah the God of Israel who held me back from harming you is living, if you had not come quickly to meet me, by morning there would not have remained a single male[*] belonging to Na′bal.” 35 With that David accepted from her what she had brought him and said to her: “Go up in peace to your house. See, I have listened to you, and I will grant your request.”

36 Ab′i·gail later went back to Na′bal, who was feasting like a king in his house, and Na′bal[*] was in a good mood and was as drunk as could be. She did not tell him a single thing until the morning light. 37 In the morning, when Na′bal was sober, his wife told him these things. And his heart became like a dead man’s, and he lay paralyzed like a stone. 38 About ten days later, Jehovah struck Na′bal, and he died.

39 When David heard that Na′bal had died, he said: “Praise Jehovah, who has pleaded my case of reproach from Na′bal and has kept his servant from doing anything bad, and Jehovah has brought the badness of Na′bal back on his own head!” Then David sent word to propose to Ab′i·gail to take her as his wife. 40 So David’s servants came to Ab′i·gail at Car′mel and said to her: “David has sent us to you to take you as his wife.” 41 She immediately rose up and bowed with her face to the ground and said: “Here is your slave as a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.” 42 Then Ab′i·gail quickly rose up and rode on her donkey with five of her female servants walking behind her; she accompanied the messengers of David and became his wife.

43 David had also married A·hin′o·am from Jez′re·el, and both women became his wives.

44 But Saul had given his daughter Mi′chal, David’s wife, to Pal′ti the son of La′ish, who was from Gal′lim.

^ 1 Sam. 25:2 A city in Judah; not the same as Mount Carmel.

^ 1 Sam. 25:6 Or “may you have peace.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:8 Lit., “a good day.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:17 Or “good-for-nothing.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:18 A seah equaled 7.33 L (6.66 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 25:22 Or possibly, “to David.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:22 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Sam. 25:25 Meaning “Senseless; Stupid.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:26 Or “your soul is.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:26 Or “bringing salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:27 Lit., “blessing.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “as from the hollow of a sling.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:31 Lit., “staggering or stumbling.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:31 Or “bring salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:33 Or “bringing salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:34 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Sam. 25:36 Lit., “Nabal’s heart.”

2 Samuel  2 : 1 - 32

2 Afterward David inquired of Jehovah, saying: “Should I go up into one of the cities of Judah?” Jehovah said to him: “Go up.” David then asked: “Where should I go?” He replied: “To Heb′ron.” 2 So David went up there with his two wives, A·hin′o·am of Jez′re·el and Ab′i·gail the widow of Na′bal the Car′mel·ite. 3 David also brought the men who were with him, each with his household, and they settled in the cities around Heb′ron. 4 Then the men of Judah came, and there they anointed David as king over the house of Judah.

They told David: “The men of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad were the ones who buried Saul.” 5 So David sent messengers to the men of Ja′besh-gil′e·ad and said to them: “May you be blessed by Jehovah, because you showed loyal love to your lord Saul by burying him. 6 May Jehovah show loyal love and faithfulness to you. I will also show you kindness because you have done this. 7 Now let your hands be strong and be courageous men, for your lord Saul is dead, and the house of Judah has anointed me as king over them.”

8 But Ab′ner the son of Ner, the chief of Saul’s army, had taken Saul’s son Ish-bo′sheth and brought him across to Ma·ha·na′im 9 and made him king over Gil′e·ad, the Ash′ur·ites, Jez′re·el, E′phra·im, Benjamin, and over all Israel. 10 Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, was 40 years old when he became king over Israel, and he reigned for two years. The house of Judah, however, supported David. 11 The time[*] that David was king in Heb′ron over the house of Judah was seven years and six months.

12 In time Ab′ner the son of Ner and the servants of Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, went out from Ma·ha·na′im to Gib′e·on. 13 Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah and the servants of David also went out and encountered them at the pool of Gib′e·on; and one group sat on this side of the pool, and the other group on that side of the pool. 14 Finally Ab′ner said to Jo′ab: “Let the young men get up and engage in combat[*] before us.” To this Jo′ab said: “Let them get up.” 15 So they got up and crossed over by number, 12 for Benjamin and Saul’s son Ish-bo′sheth and 12 from the servants of David. 16 They grabbed one another by the head and each of them thrust his sword into the side of his opponent, and they all fell down together. So that place, which is in Gib′e·on, was called Hel′kath-haz·zu′rim.

17 The fighting that ensued was extremely fierce that day, and Ab′ner and the men of Israel were finally defeated before the servants of David. 18 Now the three sons of Ze·ru′iah were there—Jo′ab, A·bish′ai, and As′a·hel; and As′a·hel was as swift on his feet as a gazelle in the open field. 19 As′a·hel chased after Ab′ner, and he would not veer to the right or to the left in his pursuit of Ab′ner. 20 When Ab′ner looked behind, he asked, “Is that you, As′a·hel?” to which he replied, “Yes, it is.” 21 Then Ab′ner said to him: “Veer to your right or to your left and capture one of the young men, and take whatever you strip off him for yourself.” But As′a·hel did not want to stop chasing him. 22 So Ab′ner said to As′a·hel once again: “Stop chasing me. Why should I strike you down? How could I look your brother Jo′ab in the face?” 23 But he kept refusing to stop, so Ab′ner struck him in the abdomen with the butt end of the spear, and the spear came out from his back; and he fell there and died on the spot. Everyone who came to the place where As′a·hel fell and died would stop and pause there.

24 Then Jo′ab and A·bish′ai went in pursuit of Ab′ner. As the sun was setting, they came to the hill of Am′mah, which faces Gi′ah on the way to the wilderness of Gib′e·on. 25 There the Ben′ja·min·ites gathered together behind Ab′ner, and they formed one company and made a stand on the top of a certain hill. 26 Then Ab′ner called out to Jo′ab: “Is the sword going to devour endlessly? Do you not know that the outcome will only be bitterness? How long, then, will it be before you tell the people to turn back from pursuing their brothers?” 27 At that Jo′ab said: “As surely as the true God is living, if you had not spoken, then only by the morning would the people have stopped pursuing their brothers.” 28 Jo′ab now blew the horn, and his men stopped chasing after Israel, and the fighting ceased.

29 Ab′ner and his men then marched through the Ar′a·bah all that night and crossed the Jordan and marched through the entire ravine[*] and finally came to Ma·ha·na′im. 30 After Jo′ab turned back from pursuing Ab′ner, he gathered all the people together. Of David’s servants, 19 were missing, in addition to As′a·hel. 31 But the servants of David had defeated the Ben′ja·min·ites and the men of Ab′ner, and 360 of their men had died. 32 They took As′a·hel and buried him in his father’s tomb, which is at Beth′le·hem. Then Jo′ab and his men marched all night long, and they reached Heb′ron at daybreak.

^ 2 Sam. 2:11 Lit., “The number of days.”

^ 2 Sam. 2:14 Or “put on a competition.”

^ 2 Sam. 2:29 Or possibly, “through all of Bithron.”

2 Samuel  3 : 1 - 39

3 The war between the house of Saul and the house of David dragged on; and David kept getting stronger, and the house of Saul grew steadily weaker.

2 Meanwhile, sons were born to David in Heb′ron. His firstborn was Am′non by A·hin′o·am of Jez′re·el. 3 His second was Chil′e·ab by Ab′i·gail, the widow of Na′bal the Car′mel·ite; and the third was Ab′sa·lom the son of Ma′a·cah, the daughter of Tal′mai the king of Gesh′ur. 4 The fourth was Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith, and the fifth was Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of A·bi′tal. 5 The sixth was Ith′re·am by David’s wife Eg′lah. These were born to David in Heb′ron.

6 While the war between the house of Saul and the house of David continued, Ab′ner kept strengthening his position in the house of Saul. 7 Now Saul had had a concubine whose name was Riz′pah, the daughter of A′iah. Ish-bo′sheth later said to Ab′ner: “Why did you have relations with the concubine of my father?” 8 Ab′ner grew very angry over the words of Ish-bo′sheth and said: “Am I a dog’s head from Judah? Until this very day, I have shown loyal love toward the house of your father Saul and to his brothers and his friends, and I have not betrayed you into the hand of David; yet today you call me to account for an error concerning a woman. 9 May God do so to Ab′ner and add to it if I do not do for David just as Jehovah swore to him: 10 to transfer the kingdom from the house of Saul and to establish the throne of David over Israel and over Judah, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba.” 11 He was not able to say one more word in reply to Ab′ner, for he was afraid of him.

12 Ab′ner immediately sent messengers to David, saying: “To whom does the land belong?” He added: “Make a covenant with me, and I will do whatever I can[*] to turn all Israel to your side.” 13 To this he replied: “Good! I will make a covenant with you. The only thing I ask of you is that you do not try to see my face unless first you bring Mi′chal, Saul’s daughter, when you come to see me.” 14 Then David sent messengers to Ish-bo′sheth, Saul’s son, saying: “Give me my wife Mi′chal, to whom I became engaged for 100 foreskins of the Phi·lis′tines.” 15 So Ish-bo′sheth sent to take her from her husband, Pal′ti·el the son of La′ish. 16 But her husband kept walking with her, weeping as he followed her as far as Ba·hu′rim. Then Ab′ner said to him: “Go, return!” At that he returned.

17 Meanwhile, Ab′ner sent word to the elders of Israel, saying: “For some time you wanted to have David as king over you. 18 Now act, for Jehovah said to David: ‘By the hand of my servant David I will save my people Israel from the hand of the Phi·lis′tines and from the hand of all their enemies.’” 19 Then Ab′ner spoke to the people of Benjamin. Ab′ner also went to speak privately to David at Heb′ron to tell him what Israel and the whole house of Benjamin had agreed upon.

20 When Ab′ner came to David at Heb′ron with 20 men, David held a feast for Ab′ner and for the men with him. 21 Then Ab′ner said to David: “Let me go and gather all Israel together to my lord the king, so that they may make a covenant with you, and you will become king over all that you desire.”[*] So David sent Ab′ner off, and he went his way in peace.

22 Just then, David’s servants and Jo′ab returned from a raid, bringing a great quantity of spoil back with them. Ab′ner was no longer with David in Heb′ron, for he had sent him on his way in peace. 23 When Jo′ab and all the army that was with him arrived, Jo′ab was told: “Ab′ner the son of Ner came to the king, and he sent him off, and he went his way in peace.” 24 So Jo′ab went in to the king and said: “What have you done? Here Ab′ner came to you. Why did you send him off so that he successfully got away? 25 You know Ab′ner the son of Ner! He came here to fool you and to get to know your every move and to find out everything that you are doing.”

26 So Jo′ab left David and sent messengers after Ab′ner, and they brought him back from the cistern of Si′rah; but David did not know anything about it. 27 When Ab′ner returned to Heb′ron, Jo′ab took him aside inside the gate to speak with him privately. However, there he stabbed him in the abdomen, and he died; this was for killing[*] his brother As′a·hel. 28 When David heard about it later, he said: “I and my kingdom are forever innocent before Jehovah of the bloodguilt for Ab′ner the son of Ner. 29 May it turn back on the head of Jo′ab and on the entire house of his father. May Jo′ab’s house never be without a man suffering from a discharge or a leper or a man working at the spindle[*] or one falling by the sword or one in need of food!” 30 So Jo′ab and his brother A·bish′ai killed Ab′ner because he had put As′a·hel their brother to death in the battle at Gib′e·on.

31 Then David said to Jo′ab and all the people with him: “Rip your garments apart and tie on sackcloth and wail over Ab′ner.” King David himself was walking behind the funeral bier. 32 They buried Ab′ner in Heb′ron; and the king wept loudly at Ab′ner’s tomb, and all the people gave way to weeping. 33 The king chanted over Ab′ner and said:

“Should Ab′ner die the death of a senseless person?

34 Your hands had not been bound,

And your feet were not in fetters.[*]

You fell like one falling before criminals.”[*]

At that all the people wept over him again.

35 Later all the people came to give David bread for consolation[*] while it was still daytime, but David swore: “May God do so to me and add to it if before the sun sets I taste bread or anything at all!” 36 All the people took notice, and it pleased them. Like everything that the king did, it pleased all the people. 37 So all the people and all Israel knew on that day that the king was not responsible for having Ab′ner the son of Ner put to death. 38 Then the king said to his servants: “Do you not know that a prince and a great man has fallen this day in Israel? 39 Today I am weak, although anointed as king, and these men, the sons of Ze·ru′iah, are too brutal for me. May Jehovah repay the evildoer according to his own evil.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:12 Lit., “and look! my hand is with you.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:21 Or “your soul desires.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:27 Lit., “for the blood of.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:29 Perhaps referring to a crippled man required to do women’s work.

^ 2 Sam. 3:34 Lit., “copper.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:34 Lit., “the sons of unrighteousness.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:35 Or “bread of mourning.”

2 Samuel  8 : 1 - 18

8 Some time later, David defeated the Phi·lis′tines and subdued them, and David took Meth′eg-am′mah out of the hands of the Phi·lis′tines.

2 He defeated the Mo′ab·ites and made them lie down on the ground and measured them with a line. He measured out two lines to be put to death, and one full line to be kept alive. And the Mo′ab·ites became David’s servants and brought tribute.

3 David defeated Had·ad·e′zer the son of Re′hob the king of Zo′bah as he was on his way to restore his authority at the Eu·phra′tes River. 4 David captured 1,700 horsemen and 20,000 foot soldiers from him. Then David hamstrung all but 100 of the chariot horses.

5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help King Had·ad·e′zer of Zo′bah, David struck down 22,000 of the Syrians. 6 David then established garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians became David’s servants and brought tribute. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. 7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold from the servants of Had·ad·e′zer and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 From Be′tah and Be·ro′thai, cities of Had·ad·e′zer, King David took a great quantity of copper.

9 Now King To′i of Ha′math heard that David had defeated the entire army of Had·ad·e′zer. 10 So To′i sent his son Jo′ram to King David to ask about his welfare and to congratulate him because he had fought and defeated Had·ad·e′zer (for Had·ad·e′zer had often fought against To′i), and he brought articles of silver, gold, and copper. 11 King David sanctified these to Jehovah, along with the silver and the gold that he had sanctified from all the nations that he had subdued: 12 from Syria and Mo′ab, from the Am′mon·ites, the Phi·lis′tines, the A·mal′ek·ites, and from the spoil of Had·ad·e′zer the son of Re′hob the king of Zo′bah. 13 David also made a name for himself when he came back from striking down 18,000 E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt. 14 He established garrisons in E′dom. In all E′dom he established garrisons, and all the E′dom·ites became David’s servants. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went.

15 David kept reigning over all Israel, and David was administering justice and righteousness for all his people. 16 Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah was over the army, and Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was recorder. 17 Za′dok the son of A·hi′tub and A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar were priests, and Se·rai′ah was secretary. 18 Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites. And David’s sons became chief ministers.[*]

^ 2 Sam. 8:6 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 8:14 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 8:18 Lit., “became priests.”

2 Samuel  10 : 1 - 19

10 Later the king of the Am′mon·ites died, and his son Ha′nun became king in his place. 2 At that David said: “I will show loyal love toward Ha′nun the son of Na′hash as his father showed loyal love toward me.” So David sent his servants to offer him comfort over the loss of his father. But when David’s servants came into the land of the Am′mon·ites, 3 the princes of the Am′mon·ites said to Ha′nun their lord: “Do you think that David is honoring your father by sending comforters to you? Is it not to search through the city and to spy it out and to overthrow it that David has sent his servants to you?” 4 So Ha′nun took the servants of David and shaved off half their beards and cut their garments in half at their buttocks and sent them away. 5 When David was told, he at once sent men to meet them, because the men had been deeply humiliated; and the king told them: “Stay in Jer′i·cho until your beards grow back, and then return.”

6 In time the Am′mon·ites saw that they had become a stench to David, so the Am′mon·ites sent and hired Syrians of Beth-re′hob and Syrians of Zo′bah, 20,000 foot soldiers; and the king of Ma′a·cah, with 1,000 men; and from Ish′tob,[*] 12,000 men. 7 When David heard about it, he sent Jo′ab and the entire army, including his mightiest warriors. 8 And the Am′mon·ites went out and drew up in battle formation at the entrance of the city gate while the Syrians of Zo′bah and of Re′hob, along with Ish′tob[*] and Ma′a·cah, were by themselves in the open field.

9 When Jo′ab saw that the battle charges were coming against him from the front and the rear, he chose some of the best troops in Israel and drew them up in battle formation to meet the Syrians. 10 He put the rest of the men under the command[*] of his brother A·bish′ai, in order to draw them up in battle formation to meet the Am′mon·ites. 11 Then he said: “If the Syrians become too strong for me, then you must come to my rescue; but if the Am′mon·ites become too strong for you, I will come to your rescue. 12 We must be strong and courageous for our people and for the cities of our God, and Jehovah will do what is good in his eyes.”

13 Then Jo′ab and his men advanced to meet the Syrians in battle, and they fled from before him. 14 When the Am′mon·ites saw that the Syrians had fled, they fled from A·bish′ai and went into the city. After that Jo′ab returned from the Am′mon·ites and came to Jerusalem.

15 When the Syrians saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they regrouped. 16 So Had·ad·e′zer sent for the Syrians in the region of the River,[*] and then they came to He′lam, with Sho′bach the chief of the army of Had·ad·e′zer leading them.

17 When the report was made to David, he immediately gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan and came to He′lam. The Syrians then drew up in battle formation to meet David and fought against him. 18 But the Syrians fled from Israel; and David killed 700 charioteers and 40,000 horsemen of the Syrians, and he struck down Sho′bach the chief of their army, who died there. 19 When all the kings, the servants of Had·ad·e′zer, saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they promptly made peace with Israel and became their subjects; and the Syrians were afraid to help the Am′mon·ites anymore.

^ 2 Sam. 10:6 Or “the men of Tob.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:8 Or “the men of Tob.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:10 Lit., “in the hand.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:16 That is, the Euphrates.

2 Samuel  13 : 1 - 39

13 Now David’s son Ab′sa·lom had a beautiful sister named Ta′mar, and David’s son Am′non fell in love with her. 2 Am′non was so distressed that he became sick because of his sister Ta′mar, for she was a virgin and it seemed impossible for Am′non to do anything to her. 3 Now Am′non had a companion named Je·hon′a·dab, the son of Shim′e·ah, David’s brother; and Je·hon′a·dab was a very clever man. 4 So he said to him: “Why are you, the king’s son, so depressed every morning? Why not tell me?” Am′non replied to him: “I am in love with Ta′mar, the sister of my brother Ab′sa·lom.” 5 Je·hon′a·dab replied to him: “Lie down on your bed and pretend to be sick. When your father comes to see you, say to him, ‘Please, let my sister Ta′mar come and serve me some food. If she prepares the food given to the sick[*] before my eyes, I will eat it from her hand.’”

6 So Am′non lay down and pretended to be sick, and the king came in to see him. Then Am′non said to the king: “Please, let my sister Ta′mar come in and bake two heart-shaped cakes before my eyes so that I may take food from her hand.” 7 At that David sent a message to Ta′mar at the house, saying: “Please go to the house of your brother Am′non and prepare food[*] for him.” 8 So Ta′mar went to the house of her brother Am′non, where he was lying down. She took the dough and kneaded it into cakes before his eyes and cooked the cakes. 9 Then she took the pan and served him. But Am′non refused to eat and said: “Have everybody leave me!” So everybody left him.

10 Am′non now said to Ta′mar: “Bring the food[*] into the bedroom, so that I may eat it from your hand.” So Ta′mar took the heart-shaped cakes that she had made and brought them to her brother Am′non in the bedroom. 11 When she brought them for him to eat, he grabbed her and said: “Come, lie down with me, my sister.” 12 But she said to him: “No, my brother! Do not humiliate me, for such a thing is not done in Israel. Do not do this disgraceful thing. 13 How could I live down my shame? And you will be regarded as one of the disgraceful men in Israel. Now speak, please, to the king, for he will not withhold me from you.” 14 But he refused to listen to her, and he overpowered her and humiliated her by raping her. 15 Then Am′non began hating her with a very intense hatred, so that his hatred for her became greater than the love he had felt for her. Am′non said to her: “Get up; go away!” 16 At this she said to him: “No, my brother, for sending me away now is worse than what you have done with me!” But he refused to listen to her.

17 With that he called his young attendant and said: “Get this person out of my presence, please, and lock the door behind her.” 18 (Now she was wearing a special[*] robe, for those were the garments that the virgin daughters of the king wore.) So his attendant led her outside, and he locked the door behind her. 19 Then Ta′mar put ashes on her head, and she ripped apart the fine robe she was wearing; and she kept her hands on her head and walked off, crying out as she walked.

20 At this her brother Ab′sa·lom asked her: “Was it your brother Am′non who was with you? And now keep silent, my sister. He is your brother. Do not let your heart dwell on this matter.” Then Ta′mar lived in isolation at the house of her brother Ab′sa·lom. 21 When King David heard about all these things, he became very angry. But he would not hurt the feelings of Am′non his son, because he loved him, for he was his firstborn. 22 And Ab′sa·lom said nothing to Am′non, either bad or good; for Ab′sa·lom hated Am′non because he had humiliated his sister Ta′mar.

23 After two full years, Ab′sa·lom’s sheepshearers were at Ba′al-ha′zor, near E′phra·im, and Ab′sa·lom invited all the sons of the king. 24 So Ab′sa·lom came in to the king and said: “Your servant is having his sheep sheared. Please let the king and his servants go with me.” 25 But the king said to Ab′sa·lom: “No, my son. If all of us go, we will be a burden to you.” Although he kept urging him, he did not consent to go, but he blessed him. 26 Ab′sa·lom then said: “If not you, please let my brother Am′non go with us.” The king replied to him: “Why should he go with you?” 27 But Ab′sa·lom urged him, so he sent Am′non and all the king’s sons with him.

28 Then Ab′sa·lom ordered his attendants: “Watch, and when Am′non’s heart is in a cheerful mood from the wine, I will say to you, ‘Strike down Am′non!’ You must then put him to death. Do not be afraid. Is it not I who commands you? Be strong and courageous.” 29 So Ab′sa·lom’s attendants did to Am′non exactly as Ab′sa·lom had ordered; then all the other sons of the king got up, and each one mounted his mule and fled. 30 While they were on the way, the report reached David: “Ab′sa·lom has struck down all the sons of the king, and not one of them survived.” 31 At this the king got up and ripped his clothes apart and lay on the ground, and all his servants were standing by with their garments ripped apart.

32 However, Je·hon′a·dab the son of Shim′e·ah, David’s brother, said: “Do not let my lord think that they have killed all the young sons of the king, for only Am′non has died. This is by the order of Ab′sa·lom, who decided to do this from the day that Am′non humiliated his sister Ta′mar. 33 Now do not let my lord the king pay attention to[*] the report that says, ‘All the king’s sons have died’; only Am′non has died.”

34 Meanwhile, Ab′sa·lom ran away. Later the watchman raised his eyes and saw that there were many people coming from the road behind him next to the mountain. 35 At this Je·hon′a·dab said to the king: “Look! The king’s sons have returned. It is just as your servant said.” 36 As he finished speaking, the king’s sons came in, weeping loudly; also the king and all his servants wept very bitterly. 37 But Ab′sa·lom fled and went to Tal′mai the son of Am·mi′hud the king of Gesh′ur. David mourned his son for many days. 38 After Ab′sa·lom fled and went to Gesh′ur, he stayed there for three years.

39 Finally King David longed to go to Ab′sa·lom, for he had become reconciled to[*] the death of Am′non.

^ 2 Sam. 13:5 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:7 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:10 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:18 Or “an ornamented.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:33 Lit., “take to his heart.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:39 Or “had found consolation over.”

2 Samuel  15 : 1 - 37

15 After all these things, Ab′sa·lom acquired for himself a chariot and horses and 50 men to run before him. 2 Ab′sa·lom would rise up early and stand at the side of the road to the city gate. Whenever any man had a legal case that was to come to the king for judgment, Ab′sa·lom would call him and say: “From what city are you?” and he would say: “Your servant is from one of the tribes of Israel.” 3 Ab′sa·lom would say to him: “See, your claims are right and proper, but there is no one from the king to hear your case.” 4 Ab′sa·lom would say: “If only I were appointed judge in the land! Then every man who has a legal case or judgment could come to me, and I would see that he receives justice.”

5 And when a man came near to bow down to him, Ab′sa·lom would extend his hand and grab hold of him and kiss him. 6 Ab′sa·lom would do this to all the Israelites who would come in to the king for judgment; so Ab′sa·lom kept stealing the hearts of the men of Israel.

7 At the end of four years,[*] Ab′sa·lom said to the king: “Let me go, please, to Heb′ron to pay my vow that I made to Jehovah. 8 For your servant made this solemn vow when I was dwelling in Gesh′ur in Syria: ‘If Jehovah will bring me back to Jerusalem, I will make an offering to[*] Jehovah.’” 9 So the king said to him: “Go in peace.” With that he rose up and went to Heb′ron.

10 Ab′sa·lom now sent spies through all the tribes of Israel, saying: “As soon as you hear the sound of the horn, announce, ‘Ab′sa·lom has become king in Heb′ron!’” 11 Now 200 men from Jerusalem had gone there with Ab′sa·lom; they were invited and went unsuspectingly, unaware of what was happening. 12 Further, when he offered the sacrifices, Ab′sa·lom sent for A·hith′o·phel the Gi′lon·ite, David’s adviser,[*] from his city Gi′loh. The conspiracy kept gaining momentum, and the people who supported Ab′sa·lom were growing in number.

13 In time an informer came to David, saying: “The heart of the men of Israel has turned to Ab′sa·lom.” 14 At once David said to all his servants with him in Jerusalem: “Get up, and let us run away, for none of us will escape from Ab′sa·lom! Hurry, for fear he may quickly overtake us and bring disaster on us and strike the city with the sword!” 15 The king’s servants replied to the king: “Whatever my lord the king decides, your servants are ready to do.” 16 So the king went out with all his household following him, but the king left ten concubines to take care of the house.[*] 17 And the king continued on his way out with all the people following, and they stopped at Beth-mer′hak.

18 All his servants leaving with him[*] and all the Cher′e·thites, the Pel′e·thites, and the Git′tites, 600 men who had followed him from Gath, were passing by as the king reviewed them.[*] 19 Then the king said to It′tai the Git′tite: “Why should you also go with us? Go back and dwell with the new king, for you are a foreigner and also an exile from your place. 20 Yesterday you came, so today should I make you wander with us, to go when I must go and where I must go? Go back and take your brothers with you, and may Jehovah show you loyal love and faithfulness!” 21 But It′tai answered the king: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as surely as my lord the king is living, wherever my lord the king may be, whether for death or for life, there your servant will be!” 22 At that David said to It′tai: “Go and cross over.” So It′tai the Git′tite crossed over, together with all his men and children.

23 Everyone in the land was weeping loudly while all these people crossed over, and the king was standing by the Kid′ron Valley; all the people were crossing over to the road leading to the wilderness. 24 Za′dok was also there and with him were all the Levites carrying the ark of the covenant of the true God; and they set the Ark of the true God down; and A·bi′a·thar went up, while all the people completed crossing over from the city. 25 But the king said to Za′dok: “Take the Ark of the true God back to the city. If I find favor in the eyes of Jehovah, he will also bring me back and let me see it and its dwelling place. 26 But if he should say, ‘I have found no pleasure in you,’ then let him do to me whatever seems good in his eyes.” 27 The king said to Za′dok the priest: “Are you not a seer? Return to the city in peace, and take the two sons of you men with you, A·him′a·az your own son and Jon′a·than the son of A·bi′a·thar. 28 See, I will linger by the fords of the wilderness until word comes from you to inform me.” 29 So Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar took the Ark of the true God back to Jerusalem, and they remained there.

30 As David was going up the Mount[*] of Olives, he was weeping as he went up; his head was covered, and he was walking barefoot. All the people with him also covered their heads and were weeping as they went up. 31 David was then told: “A·hith′o·phel is among those conspiring with Ab′sa·lom.” At this David said: “Turn, please, the advice[*] of A·hith′o·phel into foolishness, O Jehovah!”

32 When David came to the summit where people used to bow down to God, Hu′shai the Ar′chite was there to meet him, with his robe ripped apart and dirt on his head. 33 However, David said to him: “If you go across with me, you will be a load on me. 34 But if you return to the city and you say to Ab′sa·lom, ‘I am your servant, O King. I was the servant of your father in the past, but now I am your servant,’ you can then frustrate the advice of A·hith′o·phel for me. 35 Are not Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests there with you? You must tell Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests everything that you hear from the house of the king. 36 Look! There with them are their two sons, A·him′a·az the son of Za′dok and Jon′a·than the son of A·bi′a·thar, and through them send to me everything that you hear.” 37 So Hu′shai, David’s friend,[*] went into the city as Ab′sa·lom was entering into Jerusalem.

^ 2 Sam. 15:7 Or possibly, “40 years.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:8 Or “worship.” Lit., “render service to.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:12 Or “counselor.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:16 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:18 Or “crossing at his side.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:18 Or “crossing before the king’s face.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:30 Or “ascent.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:31 Or “counsel.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:37 Or “confidant.”

2 Samuel  17 : 1 - 29

17 A·hith′o·phel then said to Ab′sa·lom: “Please let me choose 12,000 men and rise up and chase after David tonight. 2 I will come upon him when he is weary and powerless,[*] and I will throw him into a panic; and all the people who are with him will flee, and I will strike down only the king. 3 Then I will bring all the people back to you. The return of all the people depends on what happens with the man you are seeking. Then all the people will be at peace.” 4 The proposal was just right in the eyes of Ab′sa·lom and all the elders of Israel.

5 However, Ab′sa·lom said: “Please call Hu′shai the Ar′chite as well, and let us hear what he has to say.” 6 So Hu′shai came in to Ab′sa·lom. Then Ab′sa·lom said to him: “This is the advice A·hith′o·phel gave. Should we act on his advice? If not, you tell us.” 7 At this Hu′shai said to Ab′sa·lom: “The advice that A·hith′o·phel gave is not good in this instance!”

8 Hu′shai continued: “You well know that your father and his men are mighty, and they are desperate,[*] like a bear that has lost her cubs in the field. Moreover, your father is a warrior, and he will not spend the night with the people. 9 At this very moment he is hiding in one of the caves[*] or in some other place; and if he attacks first, those hearing of it will say, ‘The people following Ab′sa·lom have been defeated!’ 10 Even the courageous man whose heart is like that of a lion will surely melt in fear, for all Israel knows that your father is a mighty man and that the men with him are courageous. 11 I give this advice: Let all Israel be gathered to you, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, as many as the grains of sand by the sea, and you should lead them into the fight. 12 We will come against him wherever he is found, and we will come upon him just like the dew that falls on the ground; and not one of them will survive, not he nor any of the men with him. 13 If he retreats into a city, all Israel will carry ropes to that city, and we will drag it down into the valley until not even a pebble is left.”

14 Then Ab′sa·lom and all the men of Israel said: “The advice of Hu′shai the Ar′chite is better than the advice of A·hith′o·phel!” For Jehovah had determined[*] to frustrate the sound advice of A·hith′o·phel, so that Jehovah could bring disaster on Ab′sa·lom.

15 Hu′shai later said to Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar the priests: “This is what A·hith′o·phel has advised Ab′sa·lom and the elders of Israel, and this is what I have advised. 16 Now quickly send word to David and warn him: ‘Do not stay at the fords[*] of the wilderness tonight, but cross over without fail, or the king and all the people with him may be wiped out.’”[*]

17 Jon′a·than and A·him′a·az were staying at En-ro′gel; so a servant girl went off and told them and they went to tell King David, for they did not dare to be seen entering the city. 18 However, a young man saw them and told Ab′sa·lom. So the two of them quickly went off and came to the house of a man in Ba·hu′rim who had a well in his courtyard. They went down into it, 19 and the man’s wife spread a covering over the top of the well and covered it with cracked grain; no one knew about it. 20 The servants of Ab′sa·lom came to the woman at her house and asked: “Where are A·him′a·az and Jon′a·than?” The woman replied: “They passed by toward the water.” Then the men searched for them but did not find them, so they returned to Jerusalem.

21 After the men were gone, they came up out of the well and went and informed King David. They said to him: “Rise up and quickly cross the water, for this is what A·hith′o·phel advised against you.” 22 Immediately David and all the people with him rose up and crossed the Jordan. By daybreak, there was no one left who had not crossed the Jordan.

23 When A·hith′o·phel saw that his advice had not been acted on, he saddled a donkey and went to his house in his hometown. After he gave instructions to his household, he hanged[*] himself. So he died and was buried in the burial place of his forefathers.

24 Meanwhile, David went to Ma·ha·na′im, and Ab′sa·lom crossed the Jordan with all the men of Israel. 25 Ab′sa·lom put A·ma′sa in charge of the army in place of Jo′ab; A·ma′sa was the son of a man named Ith′ra the Israelite, who had relations with Ab′i·gail the daughter of Na′hash, the sister of Ze·ru′iah, Jo′ab’s mother. 26 Israel and Ab′sa·lom camped in the land of Gil′e·ad.

27 As soon as David came to Ma·ha·na′im, Sho′bi the son of Na′hash from Rab′bah of the Am′mon·ites, Ma′chir the son of Am′mi·el from Lo-de′bar, and Bar·zil′lai the Gil′e·ad·ite from Ro·ge′lim 28 brought beds, basins, clay pots, wheat, barley, flour, roasted grain, broad beans, lentils, parched grain, 29 honey, butter, sheep, and cheese.[*] They brought all of this out for David and the people with him to eat, for they said: “The people are hungry and tired and thirsty in the wilderness.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:2 Or “feeble in both hands.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:8 Or “bitter of soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:9 Or “pits; ravines.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:14 Or “commanded.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:16 Or possibly, “the desert plains.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:16 Lit., “swallowed up.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:23 Or “strangled.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:29 Lit., “curds of cattle.”

2 Samuel  20 : 1 - 26

20 Now there was a troublemaker named She′ba the son of Bich′ri, a Ben′ja·min·ite. He blew the horn and said: “We have no share in David, and we have no inheritance in the son of Jes′se. Everyone to his gods,[*] O Israel!” 2 At that all the men of Israel quit following David to follow She′ba the son of Bich′ri; but the men of Judah stuck to their king, from the Jordan to Jerusalem.

3 When David came to his house[*] at Jerusalem, the king took the ten concubines he had left behind to take care of the house, and he put them in a house under guard. He supplied food to them, but he did not have any relations with them. They remained in confinement until the day of their death, living as if they were widows, even though they had a living husband.

4 The king now said to A·ma′sa: “Call the men of Judah together to me within three days, and you also should be here.” 5 So A·ma′sa went to call Judah together, but he came later than the set time that had been appointed for him. 6 Then David said to A·bish′ai: “She′ba the son of Bich′ri may do us more harm than Ab′sa·lom did. Take the servants of your lord and chase after him, so that he may not find fortified cities and escape from us.” 7 So the men of Jo′ab, the Cher′e·thites, the Pel′e·thites, and all the mighty men went out after him; they left Jerusalem to chase after She′ba the son of Bich′ri. 8 When they were near the great stone in Gib′e·on, A·ma′sa came to meet them. Now Jo′ab was wearing his battle clothing, and he had a sword in its sheath strapped to his hip. When he stepped forward, the sword fell out.

9 Jo′ab said to A·ma′sa: “Are you all right, my brother?” Then with his right hand, Jo′ab took hold of A·ma′sa’s beard as if to kiss him. 10 A·ma′sa was not on guard against the sword that was in Jo′ab’s hand, and Jo′ab stabbed him with it in the abdomen, and his intestines spilled out on the ground. He did not have to stab him again; once was enough to kill him. Then Jo′ab and his brother A·bish′ai chased after She′ba the son of Bich′ri.

11 One of Jo′ab’s young men stood by him and was saying: “Whoever is on Jo′ab’s side and whoever belongs to David, let him follow Jo′ab!” 12 All the while A·ma′sa was wallowing in his blood in the middle of the road. When the man saw that all the people were stopping, he moved A·ma′sa from the road to the field. Then he threw a garment over him, because he saw that everyone was stopping when they came up to him. 13 After he had removed him from the road, all the men followed Jo′ab to chase after She′ba the son of Bich′ri.

14 She′ba passed through all the tribes of Israel to Abel of Beth-ma′a·cah. The Bich′rites gathered together and also went in after him.

15 Joab and his men[*] came and besieged him in Abel of Beth-ma′a·cah and raised up a siege rampart against the city, as it was standing within a rampart. And all the men with Jo′ab were undermining the wall to knock it down. 16 And a wise woman called out from the city: “Listen, men, listen! Please tell Jo′ab, ‘Come here, and let me speak to you.’” 17 So he went near to her, and the woman said: “Are you Jo′ab?” He replied: “I am.” At this she said to him: “Listen to the words of your servant.” He said: “I am listening.” 18 She continued: “They would always say in the past, ‘Let them inquire in Abel, and that was the end of the matter.’ 19 I represent the peaceable and faithful ones of Israel. You are seeking to destroy a city that is like a mother in Israel. Why should you do away with[*] the inheritance of Jehovah?” 20 Jo′ab answered: “It is unthinkable for me to do away with it and destroy it. 21 That is not the case at all. Rather, a man named She′ba the son of Bich′ri from the mountainous region of E′phra·im has rebelled[*] against King David. If you hand over this one man, I will withdraw from the city.” Then the woman said to Jo′ab: “Look! His head will be thrown over the wall to you!”

22 At once the wise woman went in to all the people, and they cut off the head of She′ba the son of Bich′ri and threw it to Jo′ab. At that he blew the horn, and they dispersed from the city, each one to his home; and Jo′ab returned to Jerusalem to the king.

23 Now Jo′ab was in charge of all the army of Israel; Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites. 24 A·do′ram was over those conscripted for forced labor; Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was the recorder. 25 She′va was the secretary; Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar were priests. 26 And I′ra the Ja′ir·ite also became a chief minister[*] for David.

^ 2 Sam. 20:1 Or possibly, “tents.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:3 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:15 Lit., “They.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:19 Lit., “swallow up.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:21 Lit., “lifted up his hand.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:26 Lit., “became a priest.”

2 Samuel  23 : 1 - 39

23 These are the last words of David:

“The word of David the son of Jes′se,

And the word of the man who was raised on high,

The anointed of the God of Jacob,

The pleasant singer[*] of the songs of Israel.

 2 The spirit of Jehovah spoke through me;

His word was on my tongue.

 3 The God of Israel spoke;

To me the Rock of Israel said:

‘When the one ruling over mankind is righteous,

Ruling in the fear of God,

 4 It is like the morning light when the sun shines,

A morning without clouds.

It is like the brightness after the rain,

Making grass sprout from the earth.’

 5 Is not my house like that before God?

For he has made an eternal covenant with me,

Arranged in every detail and secured.

Because it means my complete salvation and all my delight,

Is that not why he makes it flourish?

 6 But worthless men are all thrown away like thornbushes,

For they cannot be taken with the hand.

 7 When a man touches them,

He should be fully armed with iron and the shaft of a spear,

And they should be completely burned up with fire in their place.”

8 These are the names of David’s mighty warriors: Jo′sheb-bas·she′beth a Tah·che′mo·nite, the head of the three. He brandished his spear over 800 slain at one time. 9 Next to him, El·e·a′zar the son of Do′do the son of A·ho′hi was among the three mighty warriors with David when they taunted the Phi·lis′tines. They had gathered there for the battle, and when the men of Israel retreated, 10 he stood his ground and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines until his arm grew weary and his hand became stiff from gripping the sword. So Jehovah brought about a great victory[*] on that day; and the people returned behind him to strip the slain.

11 Next to him was Sham′mah the son of A′gee the Har′a·rite. The Phi·lis′tines gathered together at Le′hi, where there was a plot of land full of lentils; and the people fled because of the Phi·lis′tines. 12 But he took his stand in the middle of the field and defended it and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines, so that Jehovah brought about a great victory.[*]

13 Three of the 30 headmen went down during the harvest to David at the cave of A·dul′lam, and a company[*] of the Phi·lis′tines was camped in the Valley[*] of Reph′a·im. 14 David was then in the stronghold, and an outpost of the Phi·lis′tines was in Beth′le·hem. 15 Then David expressed his longing: “If only I could have a drink of the water from the cistern by the gate of Beth′le·hem!” 16 At that the three mighty warriors forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lis′tines and drew water from the cistern by the gate of Beth′le·hem and brought it to David; but he refused to drink it and poured it out to Jehovah. 17 He said: “It is unthinkable on my part, O Jehovah, that I should do this! Should I drink the blood of the men going at the risk of their lives?”[*] So he refused to drink it. These are the things that his three mighty warriors did.

18 A·bish′ai the brother of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah was the head of another three; he brandished his spear over 300 slain, and he had a reputation like the three. 19 Although he was the most distinguished of the other three and he was their chief, he did not attain to the rank of the first three.

20 Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was a courageous man[*] who performed many exploits in Kab′ze·el. He struck down the two sons of Ar′i·el of Mo′ab, and he descended into a waterpit on a snowy day and killed a lion. 21 He also struck down an Egyptian man of extraordinary size. Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand, he went against him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. 22 These things Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da did, and he had a reputation like that of the three mighty warriors. 23 Although he was distinguished even more than the thirty, he did not attain to the rank of the three. However, David appointed him over his own bodyguard.

24 As′a·hel the brother of Jo′ab was among the thirty: El·ha′nan the son of Do′do of Beth′le·hem, 25 Sham′mah the Ha′rod·ite, E·li′ka the Ha′rod·ite, 26 He′lez the Pal′tite, I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, 27 Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite, Me·bun′nai the Hu′shath·ite, 28 Zal′mon the A·ho′hite, Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite, 29 He′leb the son of Ba′a·nah the Ne·toph′a·thite, It′tai the son of Ri′bai of Gib′e·ah of the Ben′ja·min·ites, 30 Be·nai′ah a Pir′a·thon·ite, Hid′dai of the wadis[*] of Ga′ash, 31 A′bi-al′bon the Ar′bath·ite, Az′ma·veth the Bar-hu′mite, 32 E·li′ah·ba the Sha·al′bo·nite, the sons of Ja′shen, Jon′a·than, 33 Sham′mah the Har′a·rite, A·hi′am the son of Sha′rar the Har′a·rite, 34 E·liph′e·let the son of A·has′bai the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, E·li′am the son of A·hith′o·phel the Gi′lon·ite, 35 Hez′ro the Car′mel·ite, Pa′a·rai the Ar′bite, 36 I′gal the son of Nathan of Zo′bah, Ba′ni the Gad′ite, 37 Ze′lek the Am′mon·ite, Na′ha·rai the Be·er′oth·ite, the armor-bearer of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah, 38 I′ra the Ith′rite, Ga′reb the Ith′rite, 39 and U·ri′ah the Hit′tite—37 in all.

^ 2 Sam. 23:1 Or “The pleasant one.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:10 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:12 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:13 Or “tent village.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:13 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:17 Or “souls?”

^ 2 Sam. 23:20 Lit., “the son of a man of valor.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:30 See Glossary.

1 Kings  1 : 1 - 53

THE FIRST OF KINGS

1 Now King David was old, advanced in years,[*] and although they would cover him with garments, he could not get warm. 2 So his servants said to him: “Let a girl, a virgin, be found for my lord the king, and she will wait on the king as his nurse. She will lie in your arms so that my lord the king may feel warm.” 3 They searched throughout all the territory of Israel for a beautiful girl, and they found Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite and brought her in to the king. 4 The girl was extremely beautiful, and she became the king’s nurse and waited on him, but the king did not have sexual relations with her.

5 Meanwhile, Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith was exalting himself, saying: “I am going to be king!” He had a chariot made for himself with horsemen and 50 men to run before him. 6 But his father had never confronted him[*] by saying: “Why have you done this?” He was also very handsome, and his mother had given birth to him after Ab′sa·lom. 7 He conferred with Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah and A·bi′a·thar the priest, and they offered Ad·o·ni′jah help and support. 8 But Za′dok the priest, Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, Nathan the prophet, Shim′e·i, Re′i, and David’s mighty warriors did not support Ad·o·ni′jah.

9 Eventually Ad·o·ni′jah held a sacrifice of sheep, cattle, and fattened animals by the stone of Zo′he·leth, which is near En-ro′gel, and he invited all his brothers the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah the king’s servants. 10 But he did not invite Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah and the mighty warriors, or Sol′o·mon his brother. 11 Nathan then said to Bath-she′ba, Sol′o·mon’s mother: “Have you not heard that Ad·o·ni′jah the son of Hag′gith has become king, and our lord David does not know anything about it? 12 So now come, please, and let me advise you, so that you may save your own life and the life of[*] your son Sol′o·mon. 13 Go in to King David and say to him, ‘Was it not you, my lord the king, who swore to your servant, saying: “Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne”? So why has Ad·o·ni′jah become king?’ 14 While you are still there speaking with the king, I will come in after you and confirm your words.”

15 So Bath-she′ba went in to the king, into his private room. The king was very old, and Ab′i·shag the Shu′nam·mite was waiting on the king. 16 Then Bath-she′ba bowed low and prostrated herself to the king, and the king said: “What is your request?” 17 She replied: “My lord, it was you who swore by Jehovah your God to your servant, ‘Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne.’ 18 But look! Ad·o·ni′jah has become king, and my lord the king does not know anything about it. 19 He sacrificed bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity and invited all the sons of the king and A·bi′a·thar the priest and Jo′ab the chief of the army; but he did not invite your servant Sol′o·mon. 20 And now, my lord the king, the eyes of all Israel are upon you to tell them who will sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. 21 Otherwise, as soon as my lord the king is laid to rest with his forefathers, I and also my son Sol′o·mon will be considered traitors.”

22 And while she was still speaking to the king, Nathan the prophet came in. 23 At once the king was told: “Here is Nathan the prophet!” He came in before the king and prostrated himself to the king with his face to the ground. 24 Then Nathan said: “My lord the king, did you say, ‘Ad·o·ni′jah will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne’? 25 For today he has gone down to sacrifice bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity, and he has invited all the sons of the king and the chiefs of the army and A·bi′a·thar the priest. They are there eating and drinking with him, and they keep saying, ‘Long live King Ad·o·ni′jah!’ 26 But he did not invite me, your servant, or Za′dok the priest, or Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, or your servant Sol′o·mon. 27 Has my lord the king authorized this without telling your servant who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?”

28 King David now answered: “Call Bath-she′ba for me.” At that she came in and stood before the king. 29 The king then swore an oath: “As surely as Jehovah is living, the one who rescued me[*] out of all distress, 30 just as I swore to you by Jehovah the God of Israel, saying, ‘Your son Sol′o·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne in my place!’ that is what I will bring about this day.” 31 Then Bath-she′ba bowed low with her face to the ground and prostrated herself to the king and said: “May my lord King David live forever!”

32 Immediately King David said: “Call for me Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da.” So they came in before the king. 33 The king said to them: “Take with you the servants of your lord, and have my son Sol′o·mon ride on my own mule,[*] and lead him down to Gi′hon. 34 Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet will anoint him there as king over Israel; then blow the horn and say, ‘Long live King Sol′o·mon!’ 35 Then follow him back, and he will come in and sit on my throne; and he will be king in my place, and I will commission him as leader over Israel and over Judah.” 36 At once Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da said to the king: “Amen! May Jehovah the God of my lord the king confirm it. 37 Just as Jehovah was with my lord the king, so let him be with Sol′o·mon, and may He make his throne greater than the throne of my lord King David.”

38 Then Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites went down and had Sol′o·mon ride on the mule of King David, and they brought him to Gi′hon. 39 Za′dok the priest now took the horn of oil out of the tent and anointed Sol′o·mon, and they began to blow the horn, and all the people began shouting: “Long live King Sol′o·mon!” 40 After that all the people followed him and went up, playing flutes and rejoicing greatly, so that the earth was split open by their noise.

41 Ad·o·ni′jah and all those invited by him heard it when they had finished eating. As soon as Jo′ab heard the sound of the horn, he said: “Why is there such a noisy uproar in the city?” 42 While he was still speaking, Jon′a·than the son of A·bi′a·thar the priest came. Then Ad·o·ni′jah said: “Come in, for you are a good[*] man, and you must bring good news.” 43 But Jon′a·than answered Ad·o·ni′jah: “No! Our lord King David has made Sol′o·mon king. 44 The king sent with him Za′dok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da, and the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites, and they had him ride on the mule of the king. 45 Then Za′dok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him as king in Gi′hon. After that they came up from there rejoicing, and the city is in an uproar. That was the noise that you heard. 46 Moreover, Sol′o·mon has sat down on the royal throne. 47 Another thing, the servants of the king have come in to congratulate our lord King David, saying, ‘May your God make Sol′o·mon’s name more splendid than your name, and may He make his throne greater than your throne!’ At that the king bowed down on the bed. 48 And the king also said, ‘May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, who today has granted someone to sit on my throne and has allowed my own eyes to see it!’”

49 And all those invited by Ad·o·ni′jah became terrified, and each of them rose up and went his own way. 50 Ad·o·ni′jah was also afraid because of Sol′o·mon, so he got up and went and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar. 51 The report was made to Sol′o·mon: “Here Ad·o·ni′jah has become afraid of King Sol′o·mon; and he has taken hold of the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let King Sol′o·mon first swear to me that he will not put his servant to death by the sword.’” 52 To this Sol′o·mon said: “If he behaves in a worthy manner, not a single hair of his will fall to the ground; but if what is bad is found in him, he will have to die.” 53 So King Sol′o·mon sent for him to be brought down from the altar. Then he came in and bowed down to King Sol′o·mon, after which Sol′o·mon said to him: “Go to your own house.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:1 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:6 Or “hurt his feelings; rebuked him.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:12 Or “your own soul and the soul of.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:29 Or “redeemed my soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:33 Or “she-mule.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:42 Or “worthy.”

1 Kings  4 : 1 - 34

4 King Sol′o·mon ruled over all Israel. 2 These were his high officials:[*] Az·a·ri′ah the son of Za′dok was the priest; 3 El·i·hor′eph and A·hi′jah the sons of Shi′sha were secretaries; Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was the recorder; 4 Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was in charge of the army; Za′dok and A·bi′a·thar were priests; 5 Az·a·ri′ah the son of Nathan was over the deputies; Za′bud the son of Nathan was a priest and the king’s friend; 6 A·hi′shar was over the household; and Ad·o·ni′ram the son of Ab′da was over those conscripted for forced labor.

7 Sol′o·mon had 12 deputies in charge of all Israel who provided the king and his household with food. Each one was responsible for providing the food for one month of the year. 8 These were their names: The son of Hur, in the mountainous region of E′phra·im; 9 the son of De′ker, in Ma′kaz, Sha·al′bim, Beth-she′mesh, and E′lon-beth-ha′nan; 10 the son of He′sed, in A·rub′both (he had So′coh and all the land of He′pher); 11 the son of A·bin′a·dab, in all the slopes of Dor (Sol′o·mon’s daughter Ta′phath became his wife); 12 Ba′a·na the son of A·hi′lud, in Ta′a·nach, Me·gid′do, and all Beth-she′an, which is beside Zar′e·than below Jez′re·el, from Beth-she′an to A′bel-me·ho′lah to the region of Jok′me·am; 13 the son of Ge′ber, in Ra′moth-gil′e·ad (he had the tent villages of Ja′ir the son of Ma·nas′seh, which are in Gil′e·ad; he also had the region of Ar′gob, which is in Ba′shan: 60 large cities with walls and copper bars); 14 A·hin′a·dab the son of Id′do, in Ma·ha·na′im; 15 A·him′a·az, in Naph′ta·li (he took Bas′e·math, another of Sol′o·mon’s daughters, as his wife); 16 Ba′a·na the son of Hu′shai, in Ash′er and Be·a′loth; 17 Je·hosh′a·phat the son of Pa·ru′ah, in Is′sa·char; 18 Shim′e·i the son of E′la, in Benjamin; 19 Ge′ber the son of U′ri, in the land of Gil′e·ad, the land of Si′hon king of the Am′or·ites and of Og king of Ba′shan. There was also one deputy in charge of all these other deputies in the land.

20 Judah and Israel were as numerous as the grains of sand by the sea; they were eating and drinking and rejoicing.

21 Sol′o·mon ruled over all the kingdoms from the River[*] to the land of the Phi·lis′tines and to the boundary of Egypt. They brought tribute and served Sol′o·mon all the days of his life.

22 Sol′o·mon’s food for each day was 30 cor measures[*] of fine flour and 60 cor measures of flour, 23 10 fattened cattle, 20 pastured cattle, and 100 sheep, besides some stags, gazelles, roebucks, and fattened cuckoos. 24 For he controlled everything this side of the River,[*] from Tiph′sah to Gaz′a, including all the kings on this side of the River; and he enjoyed peace in every region, all around him. 25 Judah and Israel lived in security, everyone under his own vine and under his own fig tree, from Dan to Be′er-she′ba, all the days of Sol′o·mon.

26 And Sol′o·mon had 4,000[*] stalls of horses for his chariots and 12,000 horses.[*]

27 These deputies supplied food to King Sol′o·mon and to everyone who ate at the table of King Sol′o·mon. Each was responsible for his month and saw to it that nothing was lacking. 28 They also brought barley and straw wherever it was needed for the horses and for the teams of horses, each according to his quota.

29 And God gave Sol′o·mon wisdom and discernment in very great measure and a broadness of heart[*] like the sand on the seashore. 30 Sol′o·mon’s wisdom surpassed the wisdom of all the people of the East and all the wisdom of Egypt. 31 He was wiser than any other man, wiser than E′than the Ez′ra·hite and He′man, Cal′col, and Dar′da, the sons of Ma′hol; his fame spread among all the surrounding nations. 32 He composed[*] 3,000 proverbs and his songs numbered 1,005. 33 He would speak about the trees, from the cedar in Leb′a·non to the hyssop that grows on the wall; he would speak about the animals, the birds,[*] the creeping things,[*] and the fish. 34 People from all the nations came to hear Sol′o·mon’s wisdom, including kings from all over the earth who had heard about his wisdom.

^ 1 Ki. 4:2 Or “his princes.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:21 That is, the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 4:22 A cor equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 4:24 That is, west of the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 4:26 This figure is found in some manuscripts and in the parallel account. Other manuscripts say 40,000.

^ 1 Ki. 4:26 Or “horsemen.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:29 Or “heart with understanding.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:32 Or “spoke.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:33 Or “flying creatures.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:33 Possibly including reptiles and insects.

1 Kings  7 : 1 - 51

7 And it took Sol′o·mon 13 years to build his own house,[*] until his whole house was completed.

2 And he built the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non 100 cubits[*] long, 50 cubits wide, and 30 cubits high on four rows of cedar pillars; and there were cedar beams on the pillars. 3 It was paneled above with cedar on the girders that rested on the pillars; they numbered 45, with 15 to a row. 4 There were three rows of framed windows, and each window was opposite another window in three tiers. 5 All the entrances and the doorposts had square[*] frames, as did the front of the windows that were opposite each other in three tiers.

6 And he built the Hall[*] of Pillars 50 cubits long and 30 cubits wide, and there was a porch in front of it with pillars and a canopy.

7 He also built the Hall[*] of the Throne, where he would judge—the Hall of Judgment—and they paneled it with cedar from the floor to the rafters.

8 The house[*] where he was to live, at the other courtyard, was set back from the Hall,[*] and it was similar in workmanship. He also built a house similar to this Hall for Phar′aoh’s daughter, whom Sol′o·mon had taken as a wife.

9 All of these were made of expensive stones hewn according to measure, trimmed with stonesaws inside and out, from the foundation up to the coping, and outside as far as the great courtyard. 10 And the foundation was laid with very large, expensive stones; some stones measured ten cubits, and other stones, eight cubits. 11 And above these were expensive stones, hewn according to measure, as well as cedar. 12 Around the great courtyard were three rows of hewn stone and a row of cedar beams, like that for the inner courtyard of the house of Jehovah and the porch of the house.

13 King Sol′o·mon sent for Hi′ram and brought him from Tyre. 14 He was the son of a widow from the tribe of Naph′ta·li, and his father was a Tyr′i·an coppersmith; and he had great skill, understanding, and experience for all kinds of work in copper.[*] So he came to King Sol′o·mon and did all his work.

15 He cast the two pillars of copper; each pillar was 18 cubits high, and it took a measuring cord 12 cubits long to encircle each of the two pillars.[*] 16 And he made two capitals cast in copper to put on the tops of the pillars. One capital was five cubits high, and the other capital was five cubits high. 17 The capital on top of each pillar had mesh network with wreathed chains; seven for the one capital and seven for the other capital. 18 And he made pomegranates in two rows around the one network to cover the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; he did the same for both capitals. 19 The capitals on top of the pillars at the porch were of a lily pattern four cubits high. 20 The capitals were on the two pillars, just above the rounded portion adjoining the network; and there were 200 pomegranates in rows all around on each capital.

21 He set up the pillars of the porch of the temple.[*] He set up the right-hand[*] pillar and named it Ja′chin,[*] and then he set up the left-hand[*] pillar and named it Bo′az.[*] 22 And the top of the pillars were of a lily pattern. So the work of the pillars was completed.

23 Then he made the Sea[*] of cast metal. It was circular in shape, 10 cubits from brim to brim and 5 cubits high, and it took a measuring line 30 cubits long to encircle it.[*] 24 And there were ornamental gourds below its brim, completely encircling it, ten to a cubit all around the Sea, with two rows of the gourds cast in one piece with it. 25 It stood on 12 bulls, 3 facing north, 3 facing west, 3 facing south, and 3 facing east; and the Sea rested on them, and all their hindquarters were toward the center. 26 And its thickness was a handbreadth;[*] and its brim was made like the brim of a cup, like a lily blossom. It would hold 2,000 bath measures.[*]

27 Then he made the ten carriages[*] of copper. Each carriage was four cubits long, four cubits wide, and three cubits high. 28 And this was how the carriages were constructed: They had side panels, and the side panels were between the crossbars. 29 And on the side panels between the crossbars were lions, bulls, and cherubs, and the same design was above the crossbars. Above and beneath the lions and the bulls were wreaths in relief. 30 And each carriage had four copper wheels and copper axles, and its four cornerpieces served as supports for them. Beneath the basin were the supports, cast with wreaths at the side of each. 31 Its opening was inside the crown, extending upward one cubit; and its opening was round, making up a stand of one and a half cubits, and on its mouth were engravings. And their side panels were square, not round. 32 The four wheels were below the side panels, and the supports of the wheels were attached to the carriage, and the height of each wheel was one and a half cubits. 33 And the wheels were made like chariot wheels. Their supports, rims,[*] spokes, and hubs were all of cast metal. 34 There were four supports on the four corners of each carriage; its supports were cast as part of[*] the carriage. 35 On top of the carriage was a circular band half a cubit high, and on the top of the carriage, its framing pieces and its side panels were cast as part of[*] it. 36 On the surfaces of its framing pieces and on its side panels he engraved cherubs, lions, and palm trees according to the amount of space on each, with wreaths all around. 37 This is how he made the ten carriages; they were all cast alike, with the same measure and shape.

38 He made ten copper basins; each could hold 40 bath measures. Each basin measured four cubits.[*] There was one basin for each of the ten carriages. 39 Then he put five carriages on the right side of the house and five on the left side of the house, and he placed the Sea on the right side of the house, toward the southeast.

40 Hi′ram also made the basins, the shovels, and the bowls. So Hi′ram finished all the work that he did for King Sol′o·mon on the house of Jehovah: 41 the two pillars and the bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the two pillars; the two networks to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the pillars; 42 the 400 pomegranates for the two networks, two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on the two pillars; 43 the ten carriages and the ten basins on the carriages; 44 the Sea and the 12 bulls beneath the Sea; 45 and the cans, the shovels, the bowls, and all the utensils, which Hi′ram made of polished copper for King Sol′o·mon for the house of Jehovah. 46 The king cast them in clay molds in the district of the Jordan, between Suc′coth and Zar′e·than.

47 Sol′o·mon left all the utensils unweighed because they were in such great quantities. The weight of the copper was not ascertained. 48 Sol′o·mon made all the utensils for the house of Jehovah: the altar of gold; the gold table on which to put the showbread; 49 the lampstands of pure gold, five on the right and five on the left before the innermost room; and the blossoms, the lamps, and the snuffers,[*] of gold; 50 the basins, the extinguishers, the bowls, the cups, and the fire holders, of pure gold; and the sockets for the doors of the inner house, that is, the Most Holy, and for the doors of the house of the temple, of gold.

51 So King Sol′o·mon completed all the work he had to do for the house of Jehovah. Sol′o·mon then brought in the things that David his father had made holy, and he put the silver, the gold, and the articles into the treasuries of the house of Jehovah.

^ 1 Ki. 7:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:2 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:5 Or “four-sided; rectangular.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:6 Or “Porch.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:7 Or “Porch.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:8 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:8 Lit., “house of the Hall.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:14 Or “bronze,” here and in subsequent occurrences in this chapter.

^ 1 Ki. 7:15 Or “each of the two pillars was 12 cubits in circumference.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Here referring to the Holy.

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Or “southern.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Meaning “May He [that is, Jehovah] Firmly Establish.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Or “northern.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Possibly meaning “In Strength.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:23 Or “reservoir.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:23 Or “it was 30 cubits in circumference.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:26 About 7.4 cm (2.9 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:26 A bath equaled 22 L (5.81 gal). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:27 Or “water carts.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:33 Or “fellies.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:34 Or “were one piece with.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:35 Or “were one piece with.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:38 Or “four cubits in diameter.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:49 Or “tongs.”

1 Kings  9 : 1 - 28

9 As soon as Sol′o·mon had finished building the house of Jehovah, the house[*] of the king, and everything Sol′o·mon desired to make, 2 Jehovah appeared to Sol′o·mon a second time, just as he had appeared to him in Gib′e·on. 3 Jehovah said to him: “I have heard your prayer and your request for favor that you made before me. I have sanctified this house that you built by permanently putting my name there, and my eyes and my heart will always be there. 4 And you, if you walk before me as your father David walked, with integrity of heart and with uprightness, by doing everything I have commanded you, and you obey my regulations and my judgments, 5 then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, just as I promised your father David, saying, ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line sitting on the throne of Israel.’ 6 But if you and your sons turn away from following me and do not keep my commandments and my statutes that I have put before you, and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, 7 I will cut Israel off from the surface of the land that I have given to them, and the house that I have sanctified for my name I will cast out of my sight, and Israel will become an object of scorn[*] and a cause for ridicule among all the peoples. 8 And this house will become heaps of ruins. Everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and will whistle and say, ‘Why did Jehovah do that to this land and this house?’ 9 Then they will say, ‘It was because they abandoned Jehovah their God, who had brought their forefathers out of the land of Egypt, and they embraced other gods and bowed down to them and served them. That is why Jehovah brought all this calamity on them.’”

10 At the end of 20 years, during which Sol′o·mon built the two houses, the house of Jehovah and the house[*] of the king, 11 Hi′ram the king of Tyre had supplied Sol′o·mon with cedar and juniper timbers and with as much gold as he desired, and King Sol′o·mon gave to Hi′ram 20 cities in the land of Gal′i·lee. 12 So Hi′ram went out from Tyre to see the cities that Sol′o·mon had given him, but he was not satisfied with them.[*] 13 He said: “What sort of cities are these that you have given me, my brother?” So they came to be called the Land of Ca′bul[*] down to this day. 14 In the meantime, Hi′ram sent to the king 120 talents[*] of gold.

15 This is the account of those whom King Sol′o·mon conscripted for forced labor to build the house of Jehovah, his own house,[*] the Mound,[*] the wall of Jerusalem, Ha′zor, Me·gid′do, and Ge′zer. 16 (Phar′aoh king of Egypt had come up and captured Ge′zer and had burned it with fire, and he had also killed the Ca′naan·ites dwelling in the city. So he gave it as a parting gift[*] to his daughter, the wife of Sol′o·mon.) 17 Sol′o·mon built up[*] Ge′zer, Lower Beth-ho′ron, 18 Ba′al·ath, and Ta′mar in the wilderness, within the land, 19 as well as all of Sol′o·mon’s storage cities, the chariot cities, the cities for the horsemen, and whatever Sol′o·mon desired to build in Jerusalem, in Leb′a·non, and in all the land of his dominion. 20 As for all the people who were left from the Am′or·ites, the Hit′tites, the Per′iz·zites, the Hi′vites, and the Jeb′u·sites, who were not part of the people of Israel, 21 their descendants who were left in the land—those whom the Israelites had been unable to devote to destruction—were conscripted by Sol′o·mon for forced labor as slaves until this day. 22 But Sol′o·mon did not make any of the Israelites slaves, for they were his warriors, servants, princes, adjutants, and the chiefs of his charioteers and horsemen. 23 There were 550 chiefs of the deputies who were over the work of Sol′o·mon, the foremen over the people who were doing the work.

24 But Phar′aoh’s daughter came up from the City of David to her own house that he had built for her; then he built the Mound.[*]

25 Three times a year Sol′o·mon offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices on the altar that he had built for Jehovah, also making sacrificial smoke on the altar, which was before Jehovah, so he completed the house.

26 King Sol′o·mon also made a fleet of ships in E′zi·on-ge′ber, which is by E′loth, on the shore of the Red Sea in the land of E′dom. 27 Hi′ram sent his own servants with the fleet of ships, experienced seamen, to serve along with the servants of Sol′o·mon. 28 They went to O′phir and took from there 420 talents of gold and brought it to King Sol′o·mon.

^ 1 Ki. 9:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:7 Lit., “a proverb.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:10 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:12 Lit., “they were not right in his eyes.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:13 Or possibly, “the Land as Good as Nothing.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:14 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 9:15 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:15 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:16 Or “a wedding gift; a dowry.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:17 Or “fortified.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:24 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

1 Kings  11 : 1 - 43

11 But King Sol′o·mon loved many foreign women besides the daughter of Phar′aoh: Mo′ab·ite, Am′mon·ite, E′dom·ite, Si·do′ni·an, and Hit′tite women. 2 They were from the nations about whom Jehovah had said to the Israelites: “You must not go in among them,[*] and they should not come in among you, for they will surely incline your heart to follow their gods.” But Sol′o·mon clung to them and loved them. 3 And he had 700 wives who were princesses and 300 concubines, and his wives gradually inclined his heart.[*] 4 In Sol′o·mon’s old age, his wives inclined[*] his heart to follow other gods, and his heart was not complete with[*] Jehovah his God like the heart of David his father. 5 And Sol′o·mon followed after Ash′to·reth, the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans, and Mil′com, the disgusting god of the Am′mon·ites. 6 And Sol′o·mon did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not follow Jehovah completely[*] as David his father had done.

7 It was then that Sol′o·mon built a high place to Che′mosh, the disgusting god of Mo′ab, on the mountain in front of Jerusalem and to Mo′lech, the disgusting god of the Am′mon·ites. 8 That was what he did for all his foreign wives who were making sacrificial smoke and sacrificing to their gods.

9 Jehovah became furious at Sol′o·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice 10 and had warned him about this very thing, that he should not go after other gods. But he did not obey what Jehovah had commanded. 11 Jehovah now said to Sol′o·mon: “Because you have done this and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes as I commanded you, I will surely rip the kingdom away from you, and I will give it to one of your servants. 12 However, for the sake of your father David, I will not do it in your lifetime. I will rip it out of the hand of your son, 13 but I will not rip away the entire kingdom. One tribe I will give to your son, for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem, which I have chosen.”

14 Jehovah then raised up a resister against Sol′o·mon, Ha′dad the E′dom·ite, of the royal family of E′dom. 15 When David defeated E′dom, Jo′ab the chief of the army went up to bury the slain, and he tried to strike down every male in E′dom. 16 (For Jo′ab and all Israel stayed there for six months until he had done away with[*] every male in E′dom.) 17 But Ha′dad fled with some of his father’s E′dom·ite servants, and they went to Egypt; Ha′dad was then a young boy. 18 So they set out from Mid′i·an and came to Pa′ran. They took men with them from Pa′ran and came to Egypt, to Phar′aoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, assigned him a food allowance, and gave him land. 19 Ha′dad found favor in the eyes of Phar′aoh, so much so that he gave him in marriage the sister of his own wife, Tah′pe·nes the queen.[*] 20 In time the sister of Tah′pe·nes bore him a son, Ge·nu′bath, and Tah′pe·nes brought him up[*] in the house of Phar′aoh, and Ge·nu′bath remained in the house of Phar′aoh among the sons of Phar′aoh.

21 Ha′dad heard in Egypt that David had been laid to rest with his forefathers and that Jo′ab the chief of the army had died. So Ha′dad said to Phar′aoh: “Send me away, so that I may go to my own land.” 22 But Phar′aoh said to him: “What have you lacked with me that you now seek to go to your own land?” To this he said: “Nothing, but please send me away.”

23 God also raised up against Sol′o·mon another resister, Re′zon the son of E·li′a·da, who had fled from his lord, Had·ad·e′zer the king of Zo′bah. 24 He gathered men to himself and became chief of a marauder band when David defeated[*] them. So they went to Damascus and settled there and began reigning in Damascus. 25 And he became a resister of Israel all the days of Sol′o·mon, adding to the harm done by Ha′dad, and he abhorred Israel while he reigned over Syria.

26 And there was Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, an E′phra·im·ite from Zer′e·dah, a servant of Sol′o·mon’s whose mother’s name was Ze·ru′ah, a widow. He too began to rebel[*] against the king. 27 This is why he rebelled against the king: Sol′o·mon had built the Mound[*] and had closed up the gap of the City of David his father. 28 Now this Jer·o·bo′am was a capable man. When Sol′o·mon saw that the young man was a hard worker, he made him overseer over all the compulsory service of the house of Joseph. 29 During that time Jer·o·bo′am went out from Jerusalem, and the prophet A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite found him on the road. A·hi′jah was wearing a new garment, and the two of them were by themselves in the field. 30 A·hi′jah took hold of the new garment he was wearing and ripped it into 12 pieces. 31 Then he said to Jer·o·bo′am:

“Take ten pieces for yourself, for this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Here I am ripping the kingdom out of the hand of Sol′o·mon, and I will give you ten tribes. 32 But one tribe will remain his for the sake of my servant David and for the sake of Jerusalem, the city I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel. 33 I will do this because they have left me and are bowing down to Ash′to·reth the goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans, to Che′mosh the god of Mo′ab, and to Mil′com the god of the Am′mon·ites, and they have not walked in my ways by doing what is right in my eyes and observing my statutes and my judgments as his father David did. 34 But I will not take the entire kingdom out of his hand, and I will keep him as a chieftain for all the days of his life, for the sake of David my servant whom I chose, because he obeyed my commandments and my statutes. 35 But I will take the kingship out of the hand of his son and give it to you, that is, ten tribes. 36 To his son I will give one tribe, so that David my servant may always have a lamp before me in Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen for myself as the place to put my name. 37 I will take you, and you will reign over all that you desire,[*] and you will become king over Israel. 38 And if you obey all that I command you and walk in my ways and do what is right in my eyes by obeying my statutes and my commandments, just as David my servant did, I will also be with you. I will build you a lasting house, just as I have built for David, and I will give you Israel. 39 And I will humiliate the offspring of David because of this, but not always.’”

40 So Sol′o·mon tried to put Jer·o·bo′am to death, but Jer·o·bo′am fled to Egypt, to Shi′shak the king of Egypt, and he remained in Egypt until Sol′o·mon’s death.

41 As for the rest of the history of Sol′o·mon, all that he did and his wisdom, is it not written in the book of the history of Sol′o·mon? 42 The length[*] of Sol′o·mon’s reign in Jerusalem over all Israel was 40 years. 43 Then Sol′o·mon was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David his father; and his son Re·ho·bo′am became king in his place.

^ 1 Ki. 11:2 Or “You must not intermarry with them.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:3 Or “his wives had a powerful influence over him.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:4 Or “turned away.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:4 Or “completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:6 Lit., “fully.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:16 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:19 Not a ruling queen.

^ 1 Ki. 11:20 Or possibly, “weaned him.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:24 Lit., “killed.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:26 Lit., “lift his hand.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:27 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:37 Or “your soul desires.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:42 Lit., “The days.”

1 Kings  14 : 1 - 31

14 At that time A·bi′jah the son of Jer·o·bo′am fell sick. 2 So Jer·o·bo′am said to his wife: “Rise up, please, and disguise yourself so that they will not know that you are Jer·o·bo′am’s wife, and go to Shi′loh. Look! A·hi′jah the prophet is there. He is the one who spoke of me becoming king over this people. 3 Take with you ten loaves of bread, sprinkled cakes, and a flask of honey, and go to him. He will then tell you what is going to happen to the boy.”

4 Jer·o·bo′am’s wife did what he said. She rose up and went to Shi′loh and came to the house of A·hi′jah. A·hi′jah’s eyes stared straight ahead, and he could not see because of his age.

5 But Jehovah had told A·hi′jah: “Here is the wife of Jer·o·bo′am coming to inquire of you regarding her son, for he is sick. I will tell you what to say to her.[*] When she arrives, she will conceal her identity.”

6 As soon as A·hi′jah heard the sound of her footsteps as she was coming into the entrance, he said: “Come in, wife of Jer·o·bo′am. Why are you concealing your identity? I have been assigned to give you a harsh message. 7 Go, tell Jer·o·bo′am, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “I raised you up from among your people to make you a leader over my people Israel. 8 Then I ripped the kingdom away from the house of David and gave it to you. But you have not become like my servant David, who kept my commandments and who walked after me with all his heart, doing only what was right in my eyes. 9 But you have done worse than all those who were prior to you, and you made for yourself another god and metal images[*] to offend me, and it is I whom you have turned your back on. 10 For that reason I am bringing calamity on the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and I will annihilate[*] from Jer·o·bo′am every male,[*] including the helpless and weak in Israel, and I will make a clean sweep of the house of Jer·o·bo′am, just as one clears away the dung until it is all gone! 11 Anyone belonging to Jer·o·bo′am who dies in the city, the dogs will eat; and anyone who dies in the field, the birds of the heavens will eat, for Jehovah has spoken it.”’

12 “Now rise up; go to your house. When you set foot in the city, the child will die. 13 All Israel will mourn him and bury him, for he alone of Jer·o·bo′am’s family will be laid in a grave, because he is the only one of the house of Jer·o·bo′am in whom Jehovah the God of Israel has found something good. 14 Jehovah will raise up for himself a king over Israel who will do away with[*] the house of Jer·o·bo′am from that day forward, yes, even now. 15 Jehovah will strike Israel down like a reed that sways in the water, and he will uproot Israel off this good land that he gave to their forefathers, and he will scatter them beyond the River,[*] because they made their sacred poles,[*] offending Jehovah. 16 And he will abandon Israel because of the sins that Jer·o·bo′am has committed and has caused Israel to commit.”

17 At that Jer·o·bo′am’s wife rose up and went on her way and came to Tir′zah. As she came to the threshold of the house, the boy died. 18 So they buried him, and all Israel mourned him, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hi′jah the prophet.

19 And the rest of the history of Jer·o·bo′am, how he waged war and how he reigned, is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. 20 And the length[*] of Jer·o·bo′am’s reign was 22 years, after which he was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Na′dab became king in his place.

21 Meanwhile, Re·ho·bo′am the son of Sol′o·mon had become king in Judah. Re·ho·bo′am was 41 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 17 years in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel as the place to put his name. The name of Re·ho·bo′am’s mother was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess. 22 And Judah was doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and by the sins they committed they provoked him more than their forefathers had done. 23 They too kept building for themselves high places, sacred pillars, and sacred poles[*] on every high hill and under every luxuriant tree. 24 There were also male temple prostitutes in the land. They acted according to all the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out before the Israelites.

25 In the fifth year of King Re·ho·bo′am, King Shi′shak of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. 26 He took the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.[*] He took everything, including all the gold shields that Sol′o·mon had made. 27 So King Re·ho·bo′am made copper shields to replace them, and he entrusted them to the chiefs of the guard,[*] who guarded the entrance of the king’s house. 28 Whenever the king came to the house of Jehovah, the guards would carry them, and then they would return them to the guard chamber.

29 And the rest of the history of Re·ho·bo′am, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 30 There was constant warfare between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am. 31 Then Re·ho·bo′am was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. His mother’s name was Na′a·mah the Am′mon·it·ess. And his son A·bi′jam[*] became king in his place.

^ 1 Ki. 14:5 Or “You should tell her such and such.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:9 Or “molten statues.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:10 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:10 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Ki. 14:14 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:15 That is, the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 14:15 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 14:20 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:23 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 14:26 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:27 Lit., “runners.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:31 Also called Abijah.

1 Kings  15 : 1 - 34

15 In the 18th year of King Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, A·bi′jam became king over Judah. 2 He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. 3 He went on walking in all the sins that his father committed prior to him, and his heart was not complete with[*] Jehovah his God like the heart of David his forefather. 4 However, on account of David, Jehovah his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem by raising up his son after him and keeping Jerusalem in existence. 5 For David did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not turn aside from anything that He had commanded him all the days of his life, except in the matter of U·ri′ah the Hit′tite. 6 And there was warfare between Re·ho·bo′am and Jer·o·bo′am all the days of his life.

7 As for the rest of the history of A·bi′jam, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? There was also war between A·bi′jam and Jer·o·bo′am. 8 Then A·bi′jam was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the City of David; and his son A′sa became king in his place.

9 In the 20th year of King Jer·o·bo′am of Israel, A′sa began to reign over Judah. 10 He reigned in Jerusalem for 41 years. His grandmother’s name was Ma′a·cah the granddaughter of A·bish′a·lom. 11 A′sa did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his forefather. 12 He expelled the male temple prostitutes from the land and removed all the disgusting idols[*] that his forefathers had made. 13 He even removed Ma′a·cah his grandmother from her position as queen mother,[*] because she had made an obscene idol for the worship of the sacred pole.[*] A′sa cut down her obscene idol and burned it in the Kid′ron Valley. 14 But the high places were not removed. Nevertheless, A′sa’s heart was complete with[*] Jehovah all his life.[*] 15 And he brought the things that he and his father had made holy into the house of Jehovah—silver, gold, and various utensils.

16 There was constant warfare between A′sa and Ba′a·sha the king of Israel. 17 So King Ba′a·sha of Israel came up against Judah and began to build up[*] Ra′mah to prevent anyone from going out or coming in to[*] King A′sa of Judah. 18 At that A′sa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah and the treasuries of the house[*] of the king and handed them over to his servants. King A′sa then sent them to Ben-ha′dad the son of Tab·rim′mon the son of He′zi·on, the king of Syria, who was dwelling in Damascus, saying: 19 “There is a treaty[*] between me and you and between my father and your father. I am sending you a gift of silver and gold. Come, break your treaty[*] with King Ba′a·sha of Israel, so that he will withdraw from me.” 20 Ben-ha′dad listened to King A′sa and sent the chiefs of his armies against the cities of Israel, and they struck down I′jon, Dan, A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah, all Chin′ne·reth, and all the land of Naph′ta·li. 21 When Ba′a·sha heard of it, he immediately quit building[*] Ra′mah and continued dwelling in Tir′zah. 22 King A′sa then summoned all Judah—no one was exempt—and they carried off the stones and timbers of Ra′mah that Ba′a·sha had been building with, and with them King A′sa built up[*] Ge′ba in Benjamin, and Miz′pah.

23 As for all the rest of the history of A′sa, all his mightiness and all that he did and the cities that he built,[*] is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? But in his old age he suffered from a disease in his feet. 24 Then A′sa was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with them in the City of David his forefather; and his son Je·hosh′a·phat became king in his place.

25 Na′dab the son of Jer·o·bo′am became king over Israel in the second year of King A′sa of Judah, and he reigned over Israel for two years. 26 He kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and walked in the way of his father and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit. 27 Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah of the house of Is′sa·char conspired against him, and Ba′a·sha struck him down at Gib′be·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines, while Na′dab and all Israel were besieging Gib′be·thon. 28 So Ba′a·sha put him to death in the third year of King A′sa of Judah and became king in his place. 29 And as soon as he became king, he struck down all the house of Jer·o·bo′am. He did not let remain anyone breathing who belonged to Jer·o·bo′am; he had them annihilated according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite. 30 This was because of the sins that Jer·o·bo′am had committed and had caused Israel to commit and because he had greatly offended Jehovah the God of Israel. 31 As for the rest of the history of Na′dab, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 32 And there was constant warfare between A′sa and King Ba′a·sha of Israel.

33 In the third year of King A′sa of Judah, Ba′a·sha the son of A·hi′jah became king in Tir′zah over all Israel and reigned for 24 years. 34 But he kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he walked in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit.

^ 1 Ki. 15:3 Or “not completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:12 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 1 Ki. 15:13 Or “as lady.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:13 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 15:14 Or “was completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:14 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:17 Or “fortify; rebuild.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:17 Or “leaving or entering the territory of.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:18 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:19 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:19 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:21 Or “fortifying; rebuilding.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:22 Or “fortified; rebuilt.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:23 Or “fortified; rebuilt.”

1 Kings  16 : 1 - 34

16 The word of Jehovah against Ba′a·sha then came to Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni, saying: 2 “I raised you up out of the dust and made you leader over my people Israel, but you kept walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and caused my people Israel to sin so that they offended me with their sins. 3 So I am making a clean sweep of Ba′a·sha and his house, and I will make his house like the house of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat. 4 Anyone belonging to Ba′a·sha who dies in the city the dogs will eat; and anyone belonging to him who dies in the field the birds of the heavens will eat.”

5 As for the rest of the history of Ba′a·sha, what he did and his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 6 Then Ba′a·sha was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Tir′zah; and E′lah his son became king in his place. 7 Also through the prophet Je′hu the son of Ha·na′ni, Jehovah’s word came against Ba′a·sha and his house, both because of all the badness that he committed in the eyes of Jehovah by offending him with the work of his hands, becoming like the house of Jer·o·bo′am, and also because of his striking him[*] down.

8 In the 26th year of King A′sa of Judah, E′lah the son of Ba′a·sha became king over Israel in Tir′zah, and he reigned for two years. 9 His servant Zim′ri, the chief of half of his chariot forces, conspired against him while he was in Tir′zah drinking himself drunk at the house of Ar′za, who was over the household in Tir′zah. 10 Zim′ri came in and struck him down and put him to death in the 27th year of King A′sa of Judah, and he became king in his place. 11 When he became king, as soon as he sat down on his throne, he struck down all the house of Ba′a·sha. He did not spare a single male,[*] whether of his relatives[*] or of his friends. 12 Thus Zim′ri annihilated the whole house of Ba′a·sha, according to the word that Jehovah had spoken against Ba′a·sha through Je′hu the prophet. 13 This was for all the sins that Ba′a·sha and his son E′lah had committed and the sins they had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols. 14 As for the rest of the history of E′lah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?

15 In the 27th year of King A′sa of Judah, Zim′ri became king for seven days in Tir′zah while the troops were camped against Gib′be·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lis′tines. 16 In time the troops who were encamped heard it being said: “Zim′ri has conspired and has also struck down the king.” So all Israel made Om′ri, the chief of the army, king over Israel on that day in the camp. 17 Om′ri and all Israel with him went up from Gib′be·thon and laid siege to Tir′zah. 18 When Zim′ri saw that the city had been captured, he went into the fortified tower of the king’s house[*] and burned the house down over himself, and he died. 19 This was for his own sins that he had committed by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah by walking in the way of Jer·o·bo′am and for the sin he had caused Israel to commit. 20 As for the rest of the history of Zim′ri and his conspiracy, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?

21 It was then that the people of Israel were divided into two factions. One part of the people became followers of Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath, wanting to make him king, and the other part followed Om′ri. 22 But the people who were following Om′ri prevailed over the people following Tib′ni the son of Gi′nath. So Tib′ni died, and Om′ri became king.

23 In the 31st year of King A′sa of Judah, Om′ri became king over Israel, and he reigned for 12 years. In Tir′zah he reigned for six years. 24 He bought the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a from She′mer for two talents[*] of silver, and he built a city on the mountain. He named the city that he built Sa·mar′i·a,[*] after She′mer the owner[*] of the mountain. 25 Om′ri kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he was worse than all who were prior to him. 26 He walked in all the ways of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat and in the sin he had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols. 27 As for the rest of the history of Om′ri, what he did and his mighty exploits, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 28 Then Om′ri was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a; and his son A′hab became king in his place.

29 A′hab the son of Om′ri became king over Israel in the 38th year of King A′sa of Judah, and A′hab the son of Om′ri reigned over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a for 22 years. 30 A′hab the son of Om′ri was worse in the eyes of Jehovah than all those who were prior to him. 31 As if it were a trivial thing for him to walk in the sins of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat, he also took as wife Jez′e·bel the daughter of Eth·ba′al, the king of the Si·do′ni·ans, and began to serve Ba′al and to bow down to him. 32 Further, he set up an altar to Ba′al at the house[*] of Ba′al that he built in Sa·mar′i·a. 33 A′hab also made the sacred pole.[*] A′hab did more to offend Jehovah the God of Israel than all the kings of Israel prior to him.

34 In his days, Hi′el the Beth′el·ite rebuilt Jer′i·cho. At the cost of A·bi′ram his firstborn he laid its foundation, and at the cost of Se′gub his youngest he put up its doors, according to the word of Jehovah spoken through Joshua the son of Nun.

^ 1 Ki. 16:7 That is, Nadab, the son of Jeroboam.

^ 1 Ki. 16:11 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Ki. 16:11 Or “his avengers of blood.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:18 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 Meaning “Belonging to the Clan Shemer.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 Lit., “lord.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:32 Or “temple.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:33 See Glossary.

2 Kings  8 : 1 - 29

8 E·li′sha said to the woman whose son he had restored to life:[*] “Rise up and go, you with your household, and live as a foreigner wherever you can, for Jehovah has declared a famine, and it will come on the land for seven years.” 2 So the woman got up and did what the man of the true God said. She went with her household and settled in the land of the Phi·lis′tines for seven years.

3 At the end of seven years, the woman returned from the land of the Phi·lis′tines and went to appeal to the king for her house and her field. 4 Now the king was speaking to Ge·ha′zi the attendant of the man of the true God, saying: “Relate to me, please, all the great things that E·li′sha has done.” 5 Just as he was relating to the king how he had restored the dead one to life, the woman whose son he had restored to life came to the king, appealing for her house and her field. At once Ge·ha′zi said: “My lord the king, this is the woman, and this is her son, whom E·li′sha restored to life.” 6 At that the king asked the woman, and she related the story to him. Then the king assigned her a court official, telling him: “Return all that belongs to her and all the products of the field from the day she left the land until now.”

7 E·li′sha came to Damascus when Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria was sick. So the report was made to him: “The man of the true God has come here.” 8 At that the king said to Haz′a·el: “Take a gift with you and go and meet the man of the true God. Inquire of Jehovah through him, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” 9 Haz′a·el went to meet him and took a gift with him, every sort of good thing of Damascus, the load of 40 camels. He came and stood before him and said: “Your son, Ben-ha′dad the king of Syria, has sent me to you, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” 10 E·li′sha replied to him: “Go and tell him, ‘You will certainly recover,’ but Jehovah has shown me that he will certainly die.” 11 And he kept staring at him to the point of embarrassment. Then the man of the true God gave way to weeping. 12 Haz′a·el asked: “Why is my lord weeping?” He replied: “Because I know what harm you will do to the people of Israel. Their fortified places you will set on fire, their choice men you will kill with the sword, their children you will dash to pieces, and their pregnant women you will rip open.” 13 Haz′a·el said: “How could your servant, who is a mere dog, do such a deed?” But E·li′sha said: “Jehovah has shown me that you will be king over Syria.”

14 Then he left E·li′sha and returned to his own lord, who said to him: “What did E·li′sha say to you?” He replied: “He told me that you will certainly recover.” 15 But the next day, Haz′a·el took a coverlet, dipped it in water, and held[*] it over his face until he died. And Haz′a·el became king in his place.

16 In the fifth year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel, while Je·hosh′a·phat was king of Judah, Je·ho′ram the son of King Je·hosh′a·phat of Judah became king. 17 He was 32 years old when he became king, and he reigned for eight years in Jerusalem. 18 He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, just as those of the house of A′hab had done, for A′hab’s daughter had become his wife; and he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. 19 But Jehovah did not want to bring Judah to ruin for the sake of David his servant, since he had promised him to give a lamp to him and to his sons always.

20 In his days E′dom revolted against Judah and then set up its own king. 21 So Je·ho′ram crossed over to Za′ir with all his chariots, and he rose up by night and defeated the E′dom·ites who were surrounding him and the chariot commanders; and the troops fled to their tents. 22 But E′dom has kept up its revolt against Judah to this day. Lib′nah also revolted at that time.

23 And the rest of the history of Je·ho′ram, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 24 Then Je·ho′ram was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. And his son A·ha·zi′ah became king in his place.

25 In the 12th year of Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab the king of Israel, A·ha·zi′ah the son of King Je·ho′ram of Judah became king. 26 A·ha·zi′ah was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ath·a·li′ah the granddaughter[*] of King Om′ri of Israel. 27 He walked in the way of the house of A′hab and kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of A′hab, for he was related to the house of A′hab by marriage. 28 So he went with Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab to wage war against King Haz′a·el of Syria at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, but the Syrians wounded Je·ho′ram. 29 So King Je·ho′ram returned to Jez′re·el to recover from the wounds that the Syrians had inflicted on him at Ra′mah when he fought against King Haz′a·el of Syria. A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah went down to Jez′re·el to see Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab, because he had been wounded.[*]

^ 2 Ki. 8:1 Or “had revived.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:15 Or “placed.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:26 Lit., “daughter.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:29 Or “he was sick.”

2 Kings  10 : 1 - 36

10 Now A′hab had 70 sons in Sa·mar′i·a. So Je′hu wrote letters and sent them to Sa·mar′i·a, to the princes of Jez′re·el, the elders, and the guardians of A′hab’s children,[*] saying: 2 “Now when this letter comes to you, the sons of your lord will be with you, as well as the war chariots, the horses, a fortified city, and weapons. 3 Select the best and most suitable[*] of the sons of your lord and put him on the throne of his father. Then fight for the house of your lord.”

4 But they were overcome with fear and said: “Look! If two kings could not stand before him, how can we stand?” 5 So the overseer of the palace,[*] the governor of the city, the elders, and the guardians sent this message to Je′hu: “We are your servants, and we will do everything that you tell us. We will not make anyone king. Do whatever seems good in your eyes.”

6 Then he wrote them a second letter, saying: “If you belong to me and are willing to obey me, bring the heads of the sons of your lord and come to me tomorrow at this time at Jez′re·el.”

Now the 70 sons of the king were with the distinguished men of the city who were raising them. 7 As soon as the letter came to them, they took the sons of the king and slaughtered them, 70 men, and they put their heads in baskets and sent them to him at Jez′re·el. 8 The messenger came in and told him: “They have brought the heads of the sons of the king.” So he said: “Put them in two heaps at the entrance of the city gate until morning.” 9 When he went out in the morning, he stood before all the people and said: “You are innocent.[*] Yes, I conspired against my lord, and I killed him, but who struck down all of these? 10 Know, then, that not a single word of Jehovah’s that Jehovah has spoken against the house of A′hab will go unfulfilled,[*] and Jehovah has done what he spoke through his servant E·li′jah.” 11 Moreover, Je′hu struck down all who were left of the house of A′hab in Jez′re·el, as well as all his distinguished men, his acquaintances, and his priests, until he had left him no survivor.

12 Then he got up and went on his way to Sa·mar′i·a. The binding house[*] of the shepherds was on the way. 13 There Je′hu encountered the brothers of King A·ha·zi′ah of Judah, and he said to them, “Who are you?” They said: “We are the brothers of A·ha·zi′ah, and we are on our way down to ask if all is well with the sons of the king and the sons of the queen mother.”[*] 14 Immediately he said: “Capture them alive!” So they captured them alive and slaughtered them at the cistern of the binding house, 42 men. He did not let a single one of them survive.

15 As he went from there, he encountered Je·hon′a·dab the son of Re′chab, who was coming to meet him. When he greeted[*] him, he said to him: “Is your heart fully[*] with me, just as my heart is with your heart?”

Je·hon′a·dab replied: “It is.”

“If so, give me your hand.”

So he gave him his hand, and Je′hu pulled him up into the chariot with him. 16 Then he said: “Come along with me, and see my toleration of no rivalry toward[*] Jehovah.” So they had him ride with him in his war chariot. 17 Then he came to Sa·mar′i·a, and he struck down all who were left over of A′hab’s house in Sa·mar′i·a until he had annihilated them, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken to E·li′jah.

18 Further, Je′hu collected all the people together and said to them: “A′hab worshipped Ba′al a little, but Je′hu will worship him much more. 19 So summon all the prophets of Ba′al, all his worshippers, and all his priests to me. Do not let a single one be absent, because I have a great sacrifice for Ba′al. Anyone who is absent will not live.” But Je′hu was acting with cunning to destroy the worshippers of Ba′al.

20 Je′hu continued: “Declare[*] a solemn assembly for Ba′al.” So they proclaimed it. 21 After that Je′hu sent word throughout Israel, and all the worshippers of Ba′al came. Not a single one was left out who did not come. They entered the house[*] of Ba′al, and the house of Ba′al was filled from end to end. 22 He said to the one who was in charge of the wardrobe: “Bring out garments for all the worshippers of Ba′al.” So he brought out the clothing for them. 23 Then Je′hu and Je·hon′a·dab the son of Re′chab went into the house of Ba′al. He now said to the worshippers of Ba′al: “Search carefully and see that there are no worshippers of Jehovah here, only worshippers of Ba′al.” 24 Finally they came in to offer up sacrifices and burnt offerings. Je′hu had stationed 80 of his men outside and said: “If any one of the men I am putting into your hands escapes, it will be your life for his.”[*]

25 As soon as he finished offering up the burnt offering, Je′hu said to the guards[*] and the adjutants: “Come in and strike them down! Do not let a single one escape!” So the guards and the adjutants struck them down with the sword and threw them out, and they kept going as far as the inner sanctuary[*] of the house of Ba′al. 26 Then they brought out the sacred pillars of the house of Ba′al and burned each one. 27 They tore down the sacred pillar of Ba′al, and they tore down the house of Ba′al and turned it into latrines, as it remains to this day.

28 Thus Je′hu annihilated Ba′al out of Israel. 29 However, Je′hu did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit as regards the golden calves that were in Beth′el and in Dan. 30 So Jehovah said to Je′hu: “Because you have acted well and have done what is right in my eyes by carrying out all that was in my heart to do to the house of A′hab, four generations of your sons will sit on the throne of Israel.” 31 But Je′hu did not take care to walk in the Law of Jehovah the God of Israel with all his heart. He did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am had caused Israel to commit.

32 In those days Jehovah started to cut off[*] Israel piece by piece. Haz′a·el kept attacking them throughout the territory of Israel, 33 from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gil′e·ad—of the Gad′ites, the Reu′ben·ites, and the Ma·nas′sites—from A·ro′er, which is by the Ar′non Valley,[*] to Gil′e·ad and Ba′shan.

34 And the rest of the history of Je′hu, all that he did and all his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 35 Then Je′hu was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·mar′i·a; and his son Je·ho′a·haz became king in his place. 36 The length[*] of Je′hu’s reign over Israel was 28 years in Sa·mar′i·a.

^ 2 Ki. 10:1 Lit., “the guardians of Ahab.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:3 Or “upright.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:5 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:9 Or “righteous.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:10 Lit., “will fall to the earth.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:12 Apparently a place where sheep were bound in order to be sheared.

^ 2 Ki. 10:13 Or “the lady.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:15 Or “blessed.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:15 Lit., “upright.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:16 Or “my zeal for.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:20 Lit., “Sanctify.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:21 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:24 Or “it will be your soul for his soul.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:25 Lit., “runners.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:25 Lit., “the city,” perhaps a fortresslike structure.

^ 2 Ki. 10:32 Or “reduce.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:33 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:36 Lit., “The days.”

2 Kings  14 : 1 - 29

14 In the second year of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel, Am·a·zi′ah the son of King Je·ho′ash of Judah became king. 2 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ho·ad′din of Jerusalem. 3 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, but not like David his forefather. He did everything as Je·ho′ash his father had done. 4 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. 5 As soon as he had the kingdom firmly in his control, he struck down his servants who had struck down his father the king. 6 But he did not put the sons of the murderers to death, in harmony with Jehovah’s commandment written in the book of Moses’ Law: “Fathers should not be put to death for their sons, and sons should not be put to death for their fathers; but each one should be put to death for his own sin.” 7 He struck down the E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt, 10,000 men, and captured Se′la in the war, and its name became Jok′the·el to this day.

8 Then Am·a·zi′ah sent messengers to Je·ho′ash son of Je·ho′a·haz son of Je′hu the king of Israel, saying: “Come, let us confront each other in battle.”[*] 9 King Je·ho′ash of Israel sent this message to King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah: “The thorny weed in Leb′a·non sent a message to the cedar in Leb′a·non, ‘Give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of Leb′a·non passed by and trampled down the thorny weed. 10 True, you have struck down E′dom, so your heart has become arrogant. Enjoy your glory, but stay in your own house.[*] Why should you provoke disaster and fall, bringing Judah down with you?” 11 But Am·a·zi′ah did not listen.

So King Je·ho′ash of Israel went up, and he and King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah confronted each other in battle at Beth-she′mesh, which belongs to Judah. 12 Judah was defeated by Israel, so each one fled to his home.[*] 13 King Je·ho′ash of Israel captured King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah, son of Je·ho′ash son of A·ha·zi′ah, at Beth-she′mesh. Then they came to Jerusalem, and he made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of E′phra·im to the Corner Gate, 400 cubits.[*] 14 He took all the gold and the silver and all the articles that were found in the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the house[*] of the king, as well as hostages. Then he returned to Sa·mar′i·a.

15 As for the rest of the history of Je·ho′ash, what he did and his mightiness and how he fought against King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 16 Then Je·ho′ash was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·mar′i·a with the kings of Israel; and his son Jer·o·bo′am[*] became king in his place.

17 Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah lived for 15 years after the death of Je·ho′ash the son of Je·ho′a·haz the king of Israel. 18 As for the rest of the history of Am·a·zi′ah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 19 Later a conspiracy was formed against him at Jerusalem, and he fled to La′chish, but they sent men after him to La′chish and put him to death there. 20 So they carried him back on horses, and he was buried in Jerusalem with his forefathers in the City of David. 21 Then all the people of Judah took Az·a·ri′ah,[*] who was 16 years old, and made him king in place of his father Am·a·zi′ah. 22 He rebuilt E′lath and restored it to Judah after the king[*] was laid to rest with his forefathers.

23 In the 15th year of Am·a·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ash the king of Judah, Jer·o·bo′am the son of King Je·ho′ash of Israel became king in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 41 years. 24 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit. 25 He restored the boundary of Israel from Le′bo-ha′math[*] clear to the Sea of the Ar′a·bah,[*] according to the word that Jehovah the God of Israel spoke through his servant Jo′nah the son of A·mit′tai, the prophet from Gath-he′pher. 26 For Jehovah had seen the very bitter affliction of Israel. There was no one left to help Israel, not even the helpless or the weak. 27 But Jehovah had promised not to wipe out the name of Israel from under the heavens. So he saved them by the hand of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Je·ho′ash.

28 As for the rest of the history of Jer·o·bo′am, all that he did and his mightiness, how he fought and how he restored Damascus and Ha′math to Judah in Israel, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 29 Then Jer·o·bo′am was laid to rest with his forefathers, with the kings of Israel; and his son Zech·a·ri′ah became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 14:8 Or “meet face-to-face.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:10 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:12 Lit., “tent.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:13 About 178 m (584 ft). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 14:14 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:16 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 2 Ki. 14:21 Meaning “Jehovah Has Helped.” He is called Uzziah at 2Ki 15:13; 2Ch 26:1-23; Isa 6:1; and Zec 14:5.

^ 2 Ki. 14:22 That is, his father Amaziah.

^ 2 Ki. 14:25 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:25 That is, the Salt Sea, or the Dead Sea.

2 Kings  15 : 1 - 38

15 In the 27th year of King Jer·o·bo′am[*] of Israel, Az·a·ri′ah[*] the son of King Am·a·zi′ah of Judah became king. 2 He was 16 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 52 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·co·li′ah of Jerusalem. 3 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Am·a·zi′ah had done. 4 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. 5 Jehovah afflicted the king, and he remained a leper until the day of his death; and he stayed in a separate house, while the king’s son Jo′tham was in charge of the house,[*] judging the people of the land. 6 As for the rest of the history of Az·a·ri′ah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 7 Then Az·a·ri′ah was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Jo′tham became king in his place.

8 In the 38th year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Jer·o·bo′am became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for six months. 9 He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his forefathers had done. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit. 10 Then Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh conspired against him and struck him down at Ib′le·am. After putting him to death, he became king in his place. 11 As for the rest of the history of Zech·a·ri′ah, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. 12 That fulfilled Jehovah’s word spoken to Je′hu: “Four generations of your sons will sit on the throne of Israel.” And that is how it happened.

13 Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh became king in the 39th year of King Uz·zi′ah of Judah, and he reigned for a full month in Sa·mar′i·a. 14 Then Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di came up from Tir′zah to Sa·mar′i·a and struck down Shal′lum the son of Ja′besh in Sa·mar′i·a. After putting him to death, he became king in his place. 15 As for the rest of the history of Shal′lum and the conspiracy that he formed, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. 16 It was then that Men′a·hem came from Tir′zah and struck down Tiph′sah and all who were in it and its territory, because it did not open its gates to him. He struck it down and ripped open its pregnant women.

17 In the 39th year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Men′a·hem the son of Ga′di became king over Israel, and he reigned for ten years in Sa·mar′i·a. 18 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit, all his days. 19 King Pul of As·syr′i·a came into the land, and Men′a·hem gave Pul 1,000 talents[*] of silver in return for his support in strengthening his hold on the kingdom. 20 So Men′a·hem raised the silver from Israel by exacting it from the prominent, wealthy men. He gave the king of As·syr′i·a 50 silver shekels[*] for each man. Then the king of As·syr′i·a turned back and did not stay in the land. 21 As for the rest of the history of Men′a·hem, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? 22 Then Men′a·hem was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Pek·a·hi′ah became king in his place.

23 In the 50th year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Pek·a·hi′ah the son of Men′a·hem became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for two years. 24 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit. 25 Then his adjutant Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah conspired against him and struck him down in Sa·mar′i·a in the fortified tower of the king’s house[*] with Ar′gob and A·ri′eh. He had 50 men of Gil′e·ad with him; and after he put him to death, he became king in his place. 26 As for the rest of the history of Pek·a·hi′ah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.

27 In the 52nd year of King Az·a·ri′ah of Judah, Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah became king over Israel in Sa·mar′i·a, and he reigned for 20 years. 28 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and he did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had caused Israel to commit. 29 In the days of King Pe′kah of Israel, King Tig′lath-pil·e′ser of As·syr′i·a invaded and captured I′jon, A′bel-beth-ma′a·cah, Ja·no′ah, Ke′desh, Ha′zor, Gil′e·ad, and Gal′i·lee—all the land of Naph′ta·li—and he took the inhabitants into exile in As·syr′i·a. 30 Then Ho·she′a the son of E′lah formed a conspiracy against Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah, and he struck him and put him to death; and he became king in his place in the 20th year of Jo′tham the son of Uz·zi′ah. 31 As for the rest of the history of Pe′kah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.

32 In the second year of Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah the king of Israel, Jo′tham the son of King Uz·zi′ah of Judah became king. 33 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ru′sha the daughter of Za′dok. 34 He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Uz·zi′ah had done. 35 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. He was the one who built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah. 36 As for the rest of the history of Jo′tham, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 37 In those days Jehovah began sending Re′zin the king of Syria and Pe′kah the son of Rem·a·li′ah against Judah. 38 Then Jo′tham was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather. And his son A′haz became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 15:1 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 2 Ki. 15:1 Meaning “Jehovah Has Helped.” He is called Uzziah at 2Ki 15:13; 2Ch 26:1-23; Isa 6:1; and Zec 14:5.

^ 2 Ki. 15:5 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 15:19 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 15:20 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 15:25 Or “palace.”

2 Kings  23 : 1 - 37

23 So the king sent word, and they summoned all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. 2 After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah, all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, and the prophets—all the people, from small to great. He read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant that had been found in the house of Jehovah. 3 The king stood by the pillar and made a covenant[*] before Jehovah, that he would follow Jehovah and keep his commandments, his reminders, and his statutes with all his heart and with all his soul[*] by carrying out the words of this covenant that were written in this book. And all the people agreed to the covenant.

4 The king then ordered Hil·ki′ah the high priest, the priests of the second rank, and the doorkeepers to bring out from the temple of Jehovah all the utensils made for Ba′al, for the sacred pole,[*] and for all the army of the heavens. Then he burned them outside Jerusalem on the terraces of Kid′ron, and he took their ashes to Beth′el. 5 So he put out of business the foreign-god priests, whom the kings of Judah had appointed to make sacrificial smoke on the high places in the cities of Judah and the surroundings of Jerusalem, as well as those making sacrificial smoke to Ba′al, to the sun, to the moon, to the constellations of the zodiac, and to all the army of the heavens. 6 He brought the sacred pole[*] out from the house of Jehovah to the outskirts of Jerusalem, to the Kid′ron Valley, and he burned it in the Kid′ron Valley and ground it to dust and scattered its dust on the graves of the common people. 7 He also tore down the houses of the male temple prostitutes, which were in the house of Jehovah and where the women were weaving tent shrines for the sacred pole.[*]

8 Then he brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and he made unfit for worship the high places where the priests had been making sacrificial smoke, from Ge′ba to Be′er-she′ba. He also tore down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua the chief of the city, which were on the left as one entered the city gate. 9 The priests of the high places did not serve at the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem, but they did eat unleavened bread along with their brothers. 10 He also made unfit for worship To′pheth, which is in the Valley of the Sons of Hin′nom,[*] so that no one could make his son or his daughter pass through the fire to Mo′lech. 11 And he prohibited the horses that the kings of Judah had dedicated[*] to the sun from entering the house of Jehovah by the chamber[*] of Na′than-mel′ech the court official, which was in the porticoes; and he burned the chariots of the sun in the fire. 12 The king also tore down the altars that the kings of Judah had set up on the roof of A′haz’s upper chamber, as well as the altars that Ma·nas′seh had set up in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah. He crushed them and scattered their dust in the Kid′ron Valley. 13 And the king made unfit for worship the high places in front of Jerusalem that were to the south[*] of the Mount of Ruination,[*] which Sol′o·mon the king of Israel had built to Ash′to·reth the disgusting goddess of the Si·do′ni·ans; and to Che′mosh the disgusting god of Mo′ab; and to Mil′com the detestable god of the Am′mon·ites. 14 He broke the sacred pillars to pieces and cut down the sacred poles[*] and filled their places with human bones. 15 He also tore down the altar in Beth′el, the high place that Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat had made that caused Israel to sin. After tearing down that altar and the high place, he burned the high place, ground it to dust, and burned the sacred pole.[*]

16 When Jo·si′ah turned and saw the graves on the mountain, he had the bones taken from the graves and burned them on the altar, making it unfit for worship, according to Jehovah’s word that had been proclaimed by the man of the true God who foretold that these things would happen. 17 Then he said: “What is the gravestone over there that I am looking at?” At this the men of the city said to him: “It is the grave of the man of the true God from Judah who foretold these things that you have done against the altar of Beth′el.” 18 So he said: “Let him rest. Do not let anyone disturb his bones.” So they left his bones undisturbed, as well as the bones of the prophet who had come from Sa·mar′i·a.

19 Jo·si′ah also removed all the houses of worship on the high places that were in the cities of Sa·mar′i·a, which the kings of Israel had built to offend God, and he did the same thing to them that he had done at Beth′el. 20 So he sacrificed on the altars all the priests of the high places who were there, and he burned human bones on them. After that he returned to Jerusalem.

21 The king now commanded all the people: “Hold a Passover to Jehovah your God as is written in this book of the covenant.” 22 No Passover like this had been held since the days when the judges had judged Israel or in all the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah. 23 But in the 18th year of King Jo·si′ah, this Passover to Jehovah was held in Jerusalem.

24 Jo·si′ah also cleared out the spirit mediums, the fortune-tellers, the teraphim statues,[*] the disgusting idols,[*] and all the disgusting things that had appeared in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, in order to carry out the words of the Law that were written in the book that Hil·ki′ah the priest had found in the house of Jehovah. 25 There was no king like him prior to him, who returned to Jehovah with all his heart and with all his soul[*] and with all his strength, according to all the Law of Moses; nor did anyone like him rise up after him.

26 Nevertheless, Jehovah did not turn away from his burning anger that blazed against Judah because of all the offensive things that Ma·nas′seh had done to offend Him. 27 Jehovah said: “I will also remove Judah from my sight, just as I removed Israel; and I will reject this city that I chose, Jerusalem, and the house about which I said, ‘My name will continue there.’”

28 As for the rest of the history of Jo·si′ah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? 29 In his days Phar′aoh Ne′choh the king of Egypt came to meet the king of As·syr′i·a by the Eu·phra′tes River, and King Jo·si′ah went out to confront him; but when Ne′choh saw him, he put him to death at Me·gid′do. 30 So his servants transported his dead body in a chariot from Me·gid′do and brought him to Jerusalem and buried him in his grave. Then the people of the land took Jo·si′ah’s son Je·ho′a·haz and anointed him and made him king in place of his father.

31 Je·ho′a·haz was 23 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal the daughter of Jeremiah from Lib′nah. 32 He began to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his forefathers had done. 33 Phar′aoh Ne′choh imprisoned him at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math, to keep him from reigning in Jerusalem, and then imposed on the land a fine of 100 silver talents[*] and a gold talent. 34 Furthermore, Phar′aoh Ne′choh made Jo·si′ah’s son E·li′a·kim king in place of his father Jo·si′ah and changed his name to Je·hoi′a·kim; but he took Je·ho′a·haz and brought him to Egypt, where he eventually died. 35 Je·hoi′a·kim gave the silver and the gold to Phar′aoh, but he had to tax the land to give the silver that Phar′aoh demanded. He exacted an assessed amount of silver and gold from each of the people of the land to give to Phar′aoh Ne′choh.

36 Je·hoi′a·kim was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ze·bi′dah the daughter of Pe·dai′ah from Ru′mah. 37 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his forefathers had done.

^ 2 Ki. 23:3 Or “renewed the covenant.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:4 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:6 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:10 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:11 Lit., “given.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:11 Or “dining room.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:13 Lit., “right.” That is, south, when one faces east.

^ 2 Ki. 23:13 That is, the Mount of Olives, particularly the southern extremity also known as the Mount of Offense.

^ 2 Ki. 23:14 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:15 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:24 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:24 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 2 Ki. 23:25 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:33 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

2 Kings  25 : 1 - 30

25 In the ninth year of Zed·e·ki′ah’s reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar of Babylon came with all his army against Jerusalem. He camped against it and built a siege wall all around it, 2 and the city was under siege until the 11th year of King Zed·e·ki′ah. 3 On the ninth day of the fourth month the famine was severe in the city, and there was no food for the people of the land. 4 The city wall was broken through, and all the soldiers fled by night through the gate between the double wall near the king’s garden, while the Chal·de′ans were surrounding the city; and the king went by the way of the Ar′a·bah. 5 But the Chal·de′an army pursued the king, and they overtook him in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho, and all his troops were scattered from his side. 6 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah, and they passed sentence on him. 7 They slaughtered Zed·e·ki′ah’s sons before his eyes; then Neb·u·chad·nez′zar blinded Zed·e·ki′ah’s eyes, bound him with copper fetters, and brought him to Babylon.

8 In the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, that is, in the 19th year of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king of Babylon, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard, the servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. 9 He burned down the house of Jehovah, the king’s house,[*] and all the houses of Jerusalem; he also burned down the house of every prominent man. 10 And the walls surrounding Jerusalem were pulled down by the entire Chal·de′an army that was with the chief of the guard. 11 Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took into exile the rest of the people who were left in the city, the deserters who had gone over to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the population. 12 But the chief of the guard left some of the poorest people of the land to serve as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers. 13 And the Chal·de′ans broke into pieces the copper pillars of the house of Jehovah and the carriages and the copper Sea that were in the house of Jehovah, and they carried the copper away to Babylon. 14 They also took the cans, the shovels, the extinguishers, the cups, and all the copper utensils used in the temple service. 15 The chief of the guard took the fire holders and the bowls that were of genuine gold and silver. 16 As for the two pillars, the Sea, and the carriages that Sol′o·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, the copper of all these articles was beyond weighing. 17 Each pillar was 18 cubits[*] high, and the capital on it was of copper; and the height of the capital was three cubits, and the network and pomegranates all around on the capital were all made of copper. The second pillar with its network was like it.

18 The chief of the guard also took Se·rai′ah the chief priest, Zeph·a·ni′ah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. 19 And he took from the city one court official who was the commissioner over the soldiers, five close associates of the king who were found in the city, as well as the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and 60 men of the common people of the land who were yet found in the city. 20 Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah. 21 The king of Babylon struck them down and put them to death at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math. Thus Judah went into exile from its land.

22 King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar of Babylon appointed Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan over the people whom he had left behind in the land of Judah. 23 When all the army chiefs and their men heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Ged·a·li′ah, they immediately came to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah. They were Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah, Se·rai′ah the son of Tan·hu′meth the Ne·toph′a·thite, and Ja·az·a·ni′ah the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, together with their men. 24 Ged·a·li′ah swore an oath to them and their men and said to them: “Do not be afraid of being servants to the Chal·de′ans. Live in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with you.”

25 And in the seventh month, Ish′ma·el son of Neth·a·ni′ah son of E·lish′a·ma, who was of the royal line,[*] came with ten other men, and they struck down Ged·a·li′ah and he died, along with the Jews and the Chal·de′ans who were with him in Miz′pah. 26 After that all the people, from small to great, including the army chiefs, rose up and went to Egypt, for they were afraid of the Chal·de′ans.

27 And in the 37th year of the exile of King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah, in the 12th month, on the 27th day of the month, King E′vil-mer′o·dach of Babylon, in the year he became king, released[*] King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah from prison. 28 He spoke kindly with him and put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. 29 So Je·hoi′a·chin took off his prison garments, and he regularly ate before him all the days of his life. 30 A regular allowance of food was given him from the king, day after day, all the days of his life.

^ 2 Ki. 25:9 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 25:17 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 25:25 Lit., “the seed of the kingdom.”

^ 2 Ki. 25:27 Lit., “raised up the head of.”

1 Chronicles  2 : 1 - 55

2 These were the sons of Israel: Reu′ben, Sim′e·on, Le′vi, Judah, Is′sa·char, Zeb′u·lun, 2 Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naph′ta·li, Gad, and Ash′er.

3 The sons of Judah were Er, O′nan, and She′lah. These three were born to him from Shu′a’s daughter, the Ca′naan·it·ess. But Er, Judah’s firstborn, was displeasing to Jehovah, so He put him to death. 4 Ta′mar, Judah’s daughter-in-law, bore to him Pe′rez and Ze′rah. Judah had five sons in all.

5 The sons of Pe′rez were Hez′ron and Ha′mul.

6 The sons of Ze′rah were Zim′ri, E′than, He′man, Cal′col, and Da′ra. There were five of them in all.

7 The son[*] of Car′mi was A′char,[*] who brought disaster[*] on Israel, who was unfaithful with regard to what had been devoted to destruction.

8 The son[*] of E′than was Az·a·ri′ah.

9 The sons of Hez′ron who were born to him were Je·rah′me·el, Ram, and Che·lu′bai.[*]

10 Ram became father to Am·min′a·dab. Am·min′a·dab became father to Nah′shon the chieftain of the descendants of Judah. 11 Nah′shon became father to Sal′ma. Sal′ma became father to Bo′az. 12 Bo′az became father to O′bed. O′bed became father to Jes′se. 13 Jes′se became father to his firstborn E·li′ab, A·bin′a·dab the second, Shim′e·a the third, 14 Ne·than′el the fourth, Rad′dai the fifth, 15 O′zem the sixth, and David the seventh. 16 Their sisters were Ze·ru′iah and Ab′i·gail. The sons of Ze·ru′iah were A·bish′ai, Jo′ab, and As′a·hel, three. 17 Ab′i·gail gave birth to A·ma′sa, and the father of A·ma′sa was Je′ther the Ish′ma·el·ite.

18 Ca′leb[*] the son of Hez′ron became father to sons by his wife A·zu′bah and by Jer′i·oth; and these were her sons: Je′sher, Sho′bab, and Ar′don. 19 When A·zu′bah died, Ca′leb married Eph′rath, and she bore Hur to him. 20 Hur became father to U′ri. U′ri became father to Bez′al·el.

21 Afterward Hez′ron had relations with the daughter of Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad. He married her when he was 60 years old, and she bore Se′gub to him. 22 Se′gub became father to Ja′ir, who had 23 cities in the land of Gil′e·ad. 23 Later Gesh′ur and Syria took Hav′voth-ja′ir from them, along with Ke′nath and its dependent[*] towns, 60 cities. All of these were the descendants of Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad.

24 After the death of Hez′ron in Ca′leb-eph′ra·thah, A·bi′jah the wife of Hez′ron bore him Ash′hur the father of Te·ko′a.

25 The sons of Je·rah′me·el the firstborn of Hez′ron were Ram the firstborn, Bu′nah, O′ren, O′zem, and A·hi′jah. 26 Je·rah′me·el had another wife, whose name was At′a·rah. She was the mother of O′nam. 27 The sons of Ram the firstborn of Je·rah′me·el were Ma′az, Ja′min, and E′ker. 28 The sons of O′nam were Sham′mai and Ja′da. The sons of Sham′mai were Na′dab and A·bi′shur. 29 The name of A·bi′shur’s wife was Ab′i·ha·il, who bore him Ah′ban and Mo′lid. 30 The sons of Na′dab were Se′led and Ap′pa·im. But Se′led died without sons. 31 The son[*] of Ap′pa·im was Ish′i. And the son[*] of Ish′i was She′shan, and the son[*] of She′shan, Ah′lai. 32 The sons of Ja′da the brother of Sham′mai were Je′ther and Jon′a·than. But Je′ther died without sons. 33 The sons of Jon′a·than were Pe′leth and Za′za. These were the descendants of Je·rah′me·el.

34 She′shan had no sons, only daughters. Now She′shan had an Egyptian servant whose name was Jar′ha. 35 She′shan gave his daughter to be the wife of his servant Jar′ha, and she bore him At′tai. 36 At′tai became father to Nathan. Nathan became father to Za′bad. 37 Za′bad became father to Eph′lal. Eph′lal became father to O′bed. 38 O′bed became father to Je′hu. Je′hu became father to Az·a·ri′ah. 39 Az·a·ri′ah became father to He′lez. He′lez became father to El·e·a′sah. 40 El·e·a′sah became father to Sis′mai. Sis′mai became father to Shal′lum. 41 Shal′lum became father to Jek·a·mi′ah. Jek·a·mi′ah became father to E·lish′a·ma.

42 The sons of Ca′leb[*] the brother of Je·rah′me·el were Me′sha his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph, and the sons of Ma·re′shah the father of Heb′ron. 43 The sons of Heb′ron were Kor′ah, Tap′pu·ah, Re′kem, and She′ma. 44 She′ma became father to Ra′ham the father of Jor′ke·am. Re′kem became father to Sham′mai. 45 The son of Sham′mai was Ma′on. Ma′on was the father of Beth-zur. 46 Ca′leb’s concubine E′phah gave birth to Ha′ran, Mo′za, and Ga′zez. Ha′ran became father to Ga′zez. 47 The sons of Jah′dai were Re′gem, Jo′tham, Ge′shan, Pel′et, E′phah, and Sha′aph. 48 Ca′leb’s concubine Ma′a·cah gave birth to She′ber and Tir′ha·nah. 49 In time she bore Sha′aph the father of Mad·man′nah, She′va the father of Mach·be′nah, and Gib′e·a. Ca′leb’s daughter was Ach′sah. 50 These were the descendants of Ca′leb.

The sons of Hur the firstborn of Eph′ra·thah were Sho′bal the father of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim, 51 Sal′ma the father of Beth′le·hem, and Ha′reph the father of Beth-ga′der. 52 Sho′bal the father of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim had sons: Ha·ro′eh and half of the Me·nu′hoth. 53 The families of Kir′i·ath-je′a·rim were the Ith′rites, the Pu′thites, the Shu′math·ites, and the Mish′ra·ites. It was from these that the Zo′rath·ites and the Esh′ta·ol·ites came. 54 The sons of Sal′ma were Beth′le·hem, the Ne·toph′a·thites, At′roth-beth-jo′ab, half of the Man·a·ha′thites, and the Zor′ites. 55 The families of the scribes dwelling at Ja′bez were the Ti′rath·ites, the Shim′e·ath·ites, and the Su′cath·ites. These were the Ken′ites who came from Ham′math the father of the house of Re′chab.

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Meaning “Bringer of Disaster; Bringer of Ostracism.” In Jos 7:1, also called Achan.

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Or “trouble; ostracism.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:8 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:9 Also called Caleb in vss. 18, 19, 42.

^ 1 Chron. 2:18 Also called Chelubai in vs. 9.

^ 1 Chron. 2:23 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:42 Also called Chelubai in vs. 9.

1 Chronicles  4 : 1 - 43

4 The sons of Judah were Pe′rez, Hez′ron, Car′mi, Hur, and Sho′bal. 2 Re·a′iah the son of Sho′bal became father to Ja′hath; Ja′hath became father to A·hu′mai and La′had. These were the families of the Zo′rath·ites. 3 These were the sons of the father of E′tam: Jez′re·el, Ish′ma, and Id′bash (and the name of their sister was Haz·ze·lel·po′ni), 4 and Pe·nu′el was the father of Ge′dor, and E′zer was the father of Hu′shah. These were the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Eph′ra·thah and the father of Beth′le·hem. 5 Ash′hur the father of Te·ko′a had two wives, He′lah and Na′a·rah. 6 Na′a·rah bore to him A·huz′zam, He′pher, Te′me·ni, and Ha·a·hash′ta·ri. These were the sons of Na′a·rah. 7 And the sons of He′lah were Ze′reth, Iz′har, and Eth′nan. 8 Koz became father to A′nub, Zo·be′bah, and the families of A·har′hel the son of Ha′rum.

9 Ja′bez was more honorable than his brothers; and his mother named him Ja′bez,[*] saying: “I gave birth to him in pain.” 10 Ja′bez called on the God of Israel, saying: “O that you would bless me and enlarge my territory and let your hand be with me and preserve me from calamity, so that it may bring no harm to me!” So God brought about what he had asked for.

11 Che′lub the brother of Shu′hah became father to Me′hir, who was the father of Esh′ton. 12 Esh′ton became father to Beth-ra′pha, Pa·se′ah, and Te·hin′nah, the father of Ir-na′hash. These were the men of Re′cah. 13 And the sons of Ke′naz were Oth′ni·el and Se·rai′ah, and the son[*] of Oth′ni·el was Ha′thath. 14 Me·o′no·thai became father to Oph′rah. Se·rai′ah became father to Jo′ab the father of Ge-har′a·shim,[*] so called because they were craftsmen.

15 The sons of Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh were I′ru, E′lah, and Na′am; and the son[*] of E′lah was Ke′naz. 16 The sons of Je·hal′le·lel were Ziph, Zi′phah, Tir′i·a, and As′a·rel. 17 The sons of Ez′rah were Je′ther, Me′red, E′pher, and Ja′lon; she[*] conceived and bore Mir′i·am, Sham′mai, and Ish′bah the father of Esh·te·mo′a. 18 (And his Jewish wife gave birth to Je′red the father of Ge′dor, He′ber the father of So′co, and Je·ku′thi·el the father of Za·no′ah.) These were the sons of Bi·thi′ah, the daughter of Phar′aoh, whom Me′red married.

19 The sons of Ho·di′ah’s wife, the sister of Na′ham, were the fathers of Kei′lah the Gar′mite and Esh·te·mo′a the Ma·ac′a·thite. 20 And the sons of Shi′mon were Am′non, Rin′nah, Ben-ha′nan, and Ti′lon. And the sons of Ish′i were Zo′heth and Ben-zo′heth.

21 The sons of She′lah the son of Judah were Er the father of Le′cah, La′a·dah the father of Ma·re′shah, and the families of the workers of fine fabric of the house of Ash·be′a, 22 and Jo′kim, the men of Co·ze′ba, Jo′ash, and Sa′raph, who became husbands of Mo′ab·ite women, and Jash′u·bi-le′hem. These records are ancient.[*] 23 They were potters who lived in Ne·ta′im and Ge·de′rah. They lived there and worked for the king.

24 The sons of Sim′e·on were Nem′u·el, Ja′min, Ja′rib, Ze′rah, and Sha′ul. 25 Shal′lum was his son, Mib′sam his son, and Mish′ma his son. 26 And the sons of Mish′ma were Ham′mu·el his son, Zac′cur his son, Shim′e·i his son. 27 And Shim′e·i had 16 sons and 6 daughters; but his brothers did not have many sons, and none of their families had as many as the men of Judah had. 28 They lived in Be′er-she′ba, Mo·la′dah, Ha′zar-shu′al, 29 Bil′hah, E′zem, To′lad, 30 Be·thu′el, Hor′mah, Zik′lag, 31 Beth-mar′ca·both, Ha′zar-su′sim, Beth-bir′i, and Sha′a·ra′im. These were their cities until the reign of David.

32 Their settlements were E′tam, A′in, Rim′mon, To′chen, and A′shan, five cities, 33 along with their settlements that were all around these cities as far as Ba′al. These were their genealogical enrollments and the places where they lived. 34 And Me·sho′bab, Jam′lech, Jo′shah the son of Am·a·zi′ah, 35 Joel, Je′hu son of Josh·i·bi′ah son of Se·rai′ah son of As′i·el, 36 and Eli·o·e′nai, Ja·a·ko′bah, Jesh·o·hai′ah, A·sai′ah, Ad′i·el, Je·sim′i·el, Be·nai′ah, 37 and Zi′za son of Shi′phi son of Al′lon son of Je·da′iah son of Shim′ri son of She·mai′ah; 38 these mentioned by name were the chieftains among their families, and the household of their forefathers increased in number. 39 And they went to the entrance of Ge′dor, to the east side of the valley, to look for pastures for their flocks. 40 They eventually found rich and good pastures, and the land was spacious, quiet, and undisturbed. Those who previously lived there were Ham′ites. 41 These whose names are listed came during the days of King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah and struck down the tents of the Ham′ites and the Me·u′nim who were there. They devoted them to destruction down to this day; and they settled in their place because there were pastures for their flocks there.

42 Some of the Sim′e·on·ites, 500 men, went to Mount Se′ir with Pel·a·ti′ah, Ne·a·ri′ah, Re·pha′iah, and Uz′zi·el, the sons of Ish′i who led them. 43 And they struck down the rest of the A·mal′ek·ites who had escaped, and they have lived there down to this day.

^ 1 Chron. 4:9 The name Jabez may be related to a Hebrew word meaning “pain.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:13 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:14 Meaning “Valley of Craftsmen.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:15 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:17 Possibly referring to Bithiah in vs. 18.

^ 1 Chron. 4:22 Or “The sayings are of old tradition.”

1 Chronicles  5 : 1 - 26

5 These are the sons of Reu′ben, Israel’s firstborn. He was the firstborn, but because he defiled[*] the bed of his father, his right as firstborn was given to the sons of Joseph the son of Israel, so he was not enrolled genealogically for the right of the firstborn. 2 Though Judah was superior to his brothers and from him came the one to be the leader, the right as firstborn belonged to Joseph. 3 The sons of Reu′ben the firstborn of Israel were Ha′noch, Pal′lu, Hez′ron, and Car′mi. 4 The sons of Joel were She·mai′ah his son, Gog his son, Shim′e·i his son, 5 Mi′cah his son, Re·a′iah his son, Ba′al his son, 6 and Be·er′ah his son, whom King Til′gath-pil·ne′ser of As·syr′i·a took into exile; he was a chieftain of the Reu′ben·ites. 7 His brothers by their families in the genealogical enrollment by their descendants were, as the head, Je·i′el, Zech·a·ri′ah, 8 and Be′la son of A′zaz son of She′ma son of Joel, who lived in A·ro′er and as far as Ne′bo and Ba′al-me′on. 9 To the east he settled as far as the beginning of the wilderness at the Eu·phra′tes River, for their livestock had become numerous in the land of Gil′e·ad. 10 In the days of Saul, they waged war against the Hag′rites, who were defeated before them, so they dwelled in their tents throughout all the territory east of Gil′e·ad.

11 Now the descendants of Gad lived next to them in the land of Ba′shan as far as Sal′e·cah. 12 Joel was the head, Sha′pham the second, and Ja′nai and Sha′phat in Ba′shan. 13 And their brothers belonging to their paternal houses were Mi′cha·el, Me·shul′lam, She′ba, Jo′rai, Ja′can, Zi′a, and E′ber, seven in all. 14 These were the sons of Ab′i·ha·il son of Hu′ri son of Ja·ro′ah son of Gil′e·ad son of Mi′cha·el son of Je·shish′ai son of Jah′do son of Buz. 15 A′hi son of Ab′di·el son of Gu′ni was head of their paternal house. 16 They lived in Gil′e·ad, in Ba′shan and its dependent[*] towns, and in all the pastures of Shar′on as far as they extended. 17 They were all enrolled genealogically in the days of King Jo′tham of Judah and in the days of King Jer·o·bo′am[*] of Israel.

18 The Reu′ben·ites, the Gad′ites, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh had 44,760 mighty warriors in their army who carried shields and swords and were armed with bows,[*] and they were trained in war. 19 They waged war against the Hag′rites, Je′tur, Na′phish, and No′dab. 20 And they were helped in fighting them, so that the Hag′rites and all who were with them were given into their hand, for they called to God for help in the war, and he responded to their entreaty because they trusted in him. 21 They captured their livestock—50,000 camels, 250,000 sheep, and 2,000 donkeys—as well as 100,000 people.[*] 22 Many had fallen slain, because the war was waged by the true God. And they lived in their place until the time of the exile.

23 The descendants of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh lived in the land from Ba′shan to Ba′al-her′mon and Se′nir and Mount Her′mon. They were numerous. 24 These were the heads of their paternal houses: E′pher, Ish′i, E′li·el, Az′ri·el, Jeremiah, Hod·a·vi′ah, and Jah′di·el; they were mighty warriors, men of fame, and heads of their paternal houses. 25 But they acted unfaithfully toward the God of their forefathers and prostituted themselves to the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God had annihilated from before them. 26 So the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of King Pul of As·syr′i·a (that is, King Til′gath-pil·ne′ser of As·syr′i·a) so that he took into exile those of the Reu′ben·ites, the Gad′ites, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh and brought them to Ha′lah, Ha′bor, Ha′ra, and the river Go′zan, where they are until this day.

^ 1 Chron. 5:1 Or “profaned.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:16 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:17 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 1 Chron. 5:18 Lit., “and tread the bow.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:21 Or “human souls.”

1 Chronicles  6 : 1 - 81

6 The sons of Le′vi were Ger′shon, Ko′hath, and Me·rar′i. 2 The sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram, Iz′har, Heb′ron, and Uz′zi·el. 3 The children[*] of Am′ram were Aaron, Moses, and also Mir′i·am. And the sons of Aaron were Na′dab, A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar, and Ith′a·mar. 4 El·e·a′zar became father to Phin′e·has; Phin′e·has became father to Ab·i·shu′a. 5 Ab·i·shu′a became father to Buk′ki; Buk′ki became father to Uz′zi. 6 Uz′zi became father to Zer·a·hi′ah; Zer·a·hi′ah became father to Me·ra′ioth. 7 Me·ra′ioth became father to Am·a·ri′ah; Am·a·ri′ah became father to A·hi′tub. 8 A·hi′tub became father to Za′dok; Za′dok became father to A·him′a·az. 9 A·him′a·az became father to Az·a·ri′ah; Az·a·ri′ah became father to Jo·ha′nan. 10 Jo·ha′nan became father to Az·a·ri′ah. He served as priest in the house that Sol′o·mon built in Jerusalem.

11 Az·a·ri′ah became father to Am·a·ri′ah; Am·a·ri′ah became father to A·hi′tub. 12 A·hi′tub became father to Za′dok; Za′dok became father to Shal′lum. 13 Shal′lum became father to Hil·ki′ah; Hil·ki′ah became father to Az·a·ri′ah. 14 Az·a·ri′ah became father to Se·rai′ah; Se·rai′ah became father to Je·hoz′a·dak. 15 And Je·hoz′a·dak went into exile when Jehovah took Judah and Jerusalem into exile by the hand of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar.

16 The sons of Le′vi were Ger′shom,[*] Ko′hath, and Me·rar′i. 17 These are the names of the sons of Ger′shom: Lib′ni and Shim′e·i. 18 The sons of Ko′hath were Am′ram, Iz′har, Heb′ron, and Uz′zi·el. 19 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi.

These were the families of the Levites by their forefathers: 20 Of Ger′shom, Lib′ni his son, Ja′hath his son, Zim′mah his son, 21 Jo′ah his son, Id′do his son, Ze′rah his son, Je·ath′e·rai his son. 22 The sons[*] of Ko′hath were Am·min′a·dab his son, Kor′ah his son, As′sir his son, 23 El·ka′nah his son, E·bi′a·saph his son, As′sir his son, 24 Ta′hath his son, U·ri′el his son, Uz·zi′ah his son, and Sha′ul his son. 25 The sons of El·ka′nah were A·ma′sai and A·hi′moth. 26 As for El·ka′nah, the sons of El·ka′nah were Zo′phai his son, Na′hath his son, 27 E·li′ab his son, Je·ro′ham his son, El·ka′nah his son. 28 The sons of Samuel were Joel the firstborn and A·bi′jah the second. 29 The sons[*] of Me·rar′i were Mah′li, Lib′ni his son, Shim′e·i his son, Uz′zah his son, 30 Shim′e·a his son, Hag·gi′ah his son, and A·sai′ah his son.

31 These were the ones whom David appointed to direct the singing at the house of Jehovah after the Ark came to rest there. 32 They were responsible for the singing at the tabernacle of the tent of meeting until Sol′o·mon built the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem, and they carried out their service as prescribed for them. 33 These are the men who served with their sons: Of the Ko′hath·ites, He′man the singer, son of Joel son of Samuel 34 son of El·ka′nah son of Je·ro′ham son of E′li·el son of To′ah 35 son of Zuph son of El·ka′nah son of Ma′hath son of A·ma′sai 36 son of El·ka′nah son of Joel son of Az·a·ri′ah son of Zeph·a·ni′ah 37 son of Ta′hath son of As′sir son of E·bi′a·saph son of Kor′ah 38 son of Iz′har son of Ko′hath son of Le′vi son of Israel.

39 His brother A′saph stood at his right hand; A′saph was son of Ber·e·chi′ah son of Shim′e·a 40 son of Mi′cha·el son of Ba·a·se′iah son of Mal·chi′jah 41 son of Eth′ni son of Ze′rah son of A·dai′ah 42 son of E′than son of Zim′mah son of Shim′e·i 43 son of Ja′hath son of Ger′shom son of Le′vi.

44 The descendants of Me·rar′i their brothers were at the left hand; there was E′than son of Kish′i son of Ab′di son of Mal′luch 45 son of Hash·a·bi′ah son of Am·a·zi′ah son of Hil·ki′ah 46 son of Am′zi son of Ba′ni son of She′mer 47 son of Mah′li son of Mu′shi son of Me·rar′i son of Le′vi.

48 Their brothers the Levites were appointed[*] for all the service of the tabernacle, the house of the true God. 49 Aaron and his sons made the sacrifices smoke on the altar of burnt offering and on the altar of incense, performing the duties connected with the most holy things, to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of the true God had commanded. 50 These were the descendants of Aaron: El·e·a′zar his son, Phin′e·has his son, Ab·i·shu′a his son, 51 Buk′ki his son, Uz′zi his son, Zer·a·hi′ah his son, 52 Me·ra′ioth his son, Am·a·ri′ah his son, A·hi′tub his son, 53 Za′dok his son, and A·him′a·az his son.

54 These were their settlements by their encampments[*] in their territory: for the descendants of Aaron belonging to the family of the Ko′hath·ites, as the first lot fell to them, 55 they gave them Heb′ron in the land of Judah, with its surrounding pastures. 56 But the field of the city and its settlements they gave to Ca′leb the son of Je·phun′neh. 57 And to the descendants of Aaron they gave the cities[*] of refuge, Heb′ron, also Lib′nah with its pastures, Jat′tir, Esh·te·mo′a with its pastures, 58 Hi′len with its pastures, De′bir with its pastures, 59 A′shan with its pastures, and Beth-she′mesh with its pastures; 60 and from the tribe of Benjamin, Ge′ba with its pastures, Al′e·meth with its pastures, and An′a·thoth with its pastures. All their cities for their families were 13 cities.

61 To the rest of the Ko′hath·ites, there were allotted[*] ten cities, from the family of the tribe, from the half tribe, the half of Ma·nas′seh.

62 To the Ger′shom·ites by their families they assigned 13 cities from the tribe of Is′sa·char, the tribe of Ash′er, the tribe of Naph′ta·li, and the tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Ba′shan.

63 To the Me·rar′ites by their families they assigned by lot 12 cities from the tribe of Reu′ben, the tribe of Gad, and the tribe of Zeb′u·lun.

64 Thus the Israelites gave the Levites these cities with their pastures. 65 Furthermore, they assigned by lot these cities from the tribe of Judah, the tribe of Sim′e·on, and the tribe of Benjamin, which are mentioned by their names.

66 Some of the Ko′hath·ite families had cities from the tribe of E′phra·im as their territory. 67 They gave them the cities[*] of refuge, She′chem with its pastures in the mountainous region of E′phra·im, Ge′zer with its pastures, 68 Jok′me·am with its pastures, Beth-ho′ron with its pastures, 69 Ai′ja·lon with its pastures, and Gath-rim′mon with its pastures; 70 and from half of the tribe of Ma·nas′seh, A′ner with its pastures and Bil′e·am with its pastures, to the rest of the families of the Ko′hath·ites.

71 To the Ger′shom·ites they assigned from the family of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, Go′lan in Ba′shan with its pastures and Ash′ta·roth with its pastures; 72 and from the tribe of Is′sa·char, Ke′desh with its pastures, Dab′e·rath with its pastures, 73 Ra′moth with its pastures, and A′nem with its pastures; 74 and from the tribe of Ash′er, Ma′shal with its pastures, Ab′don with its pastures, 75 Hu′kok with its pastures, and Re′hob with its pastures; 76 and from the tribe of Naph′ta·li, Ke′desh in Gal′i·lee with its pastures, Ham′mon with its pastures, and Kir·i·a·tha′im with its pastures.

77 To the rest of the Me·rar′ites they assigned from the tribe of Zeb′u·lun, Rim′mo·no with its pastures, Ta′bor with its pastures; 78 and in the region of the Jordan at Jer′i·cho, to the east of the Jordan, from the tribe of Reu′ben, they were given Be′zer in the wilderness with its pastures, Ja′haz with its pastures, 79 Ked′e·moth with its pastures, and Meph′a·ath with its pastures; 80 and from the tribe of Gad, Ra′moth in Gil′e·ad with its pastures, Ma·ha·na′im with its pastures, 81 Hesh′bon with its pastures, and Ja′zer with its pastures.

^ 1 Chron. 6:3 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:16 Also called Gershon in vs. 1.

^ 1 Chron. 6:22 Or “descendants.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:29 Or “descendants.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:48 Lit., “were the ones given.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:54 Or “walled camps.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:57 Or possibly, “city,” in agreement with Jos 21:13.

^ 1 Chron. 6:61 Or “given by lot.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:67 Or possibly, “city,” in agreement with Jos 21:21.

1 Chronicles  7 : 1 - 40

7 Now the sons of Is′sa·char were To′la, Pu′ah, Ja′shub, and Shim′ron—four. 2 And the sons of To′la were Uz′zi, Re·pha′iah, Je′ri·el, Jah′mai, Ib′sam, and She·mu′el, the heads of their paternal houses. Descended from To′la were mighty warriors, whose number in the days of David was 22,600. 3 And the descendants[*] of Uz′zi were Iz·ra·hi′ah and the sons of Iz·ra·hi′ah: Mi′cha·el, O·ba·di′ah, Joel, and Is·shi′ah—all five of them were chiefs.[*] 4 And with them by their descendants, according to their paternal houses, there were 36,000 soldiers in their army available for war, for they had many wives and sons. 5 And their brothers of all the families of Is′sa·char were mighty warriors, 87,000 as listed in the genealogical enrollment.

6 The sons of Benjamin were Be′la, Be′cher, and Je·di′a·el—three. 7 And the sons of Be′la were Ez′bon, Uz′zi, Uz′zi·el, Jer′i·moth, and I′ri—five—heads of their paternal houses, mighty warriors, and 22,034 were in their genealogical enrollment. 8 And the sons of Be′cher were Ze·mi′rah, Jo′ash, E·li·e′zer, Eli·o·e′nai, Om′ri, Jer′e·moth, A·bi′jah, An′a·thoth, and Al′e·meth—all of these were the sons of Be′cher. 9 Their genealogical enrollment by their descendants as respects the heads of their paternal houses was 20,200 mighty warriors. 10 And the sons of Je·di′a·el were Bil′han and the sons of Bil′han: Je′ush, Benjamin, E′hud, Che·na′a·nah, Ze′than, Tar′shish, and A·hish′a·har. 11 All of these were the sons of Je·di′a·el, according to the heads of their forefathers, 17,200 mighty warriors ready to go out to the army for war.

12 The Shup′pim and the Hup′pim were the sons of Ir; the Hu′shim were the sons of A′her.

13 The sons of Naph′ta·li were Jah′zi·el, Gu′ni, Je′zer, and Shal′lum—descendants[*] of Bil′hah.

14 The sons of Ma·nas′seh: As′ri·el, whom his Syrian concubine bore. (She bore Ma′chir the father of Gil′e·ad. 15 Ma′chir took a wife for Hup′pim and for Shup′pim, and the name of his sister was Ma′a·cah.) The name of the second was Ze·lo′phe·had, but Ze·lo′phe·had had daughters. 16 Ma′a·cah, Ma′chir’s wife, bore a son and named him Pe′resh; and the name of his brother was She′resh; and his sons were U′lam and Re′kem. 17 And the son[*] of U′lam was Be′dan. These were the sons of Gil′e·ad son of Ma′chir son of Ma·nas′seh. 18 And his sister was Ham·mo′le·cheth. She gave birth to Ish′hod, Abi-e′zer, and Mah′lah. 19 And the sons of She·mi′da were A·hi′an, She′chem, Lik′hi, and A·ni′am.

20 The sons of E′phra·im were Shu′the·lah, Be′red his son, Ta′hath his son, E·le·a′dah his son, Ta′hath his son, 21 Za′bad his son, Shu′the·lah his son, E′zer, and E′le·ad. The men of Gath who were born in the land killed them because they went down to take their livestock. 22 E′phra·im their father carried on mourning for many days, and his brothers kept coming in to comfort him. 23 Afterward he had relations with his wife, and she became pregnant and gave birth to a son. But he named him Be·ri′ah[*] because it was with calamity that she was in his house. 24 And his daughter was She′e·rah, who built Lower and Upper Beth-ho′ron and Uz′zen-she′e·rah. 25 And there was Re′phah his son, Re′sheph, Te′lah his son, Ta′han his son, 26 La′dan his son, Am·mi′hud his son, E·lish′a·ma his son, 27 Nun his son, and Joshua[*] his son.

28 Their possession and their settlements were Beth′el and its dependent[*] towns, and to the east Na′a·ran, and to the west Ge′zer and its dependent towns, and She′chem and its dependent towns, as far as Ay′yah[*] and its dependent towns; 29 and next to the descendants of Ma·nas′seh, Beth-she′an and its dependent towns, Ta′a·nach and its dependent towns, Me·gid′do and its dependent towns, and Dor and its dependent towns. In these the descendants of Joseph the son of Israel lived.

30 The sons of Ash′er were Im′nah, Ish′vah, Ish′vi, and Be·ri′ah, and their sister was Se′rah. 31 The sons of Be·ri′ah were He′ber and Mal′chi·el, who was the father of Bir′za·ith. 32 He′ber became father to Japh′let, Sho′mer, and Ho′tham, and to Shu′a their sister. 33 The sons of Japh′let were Pa′sach, Bim′hal, and Ash′vath. These were the sons of Japh′let. 34 The sons of She′mer[*] were A′hi, Roh′gah, Je·hub′bah, and A′ram. 35 The sons of He′lem[*] his brother were Zo′phah, Im′na, She′lesh, and A′mal. 36 The sons of Zo′phah were Su′ah, Har′ne·pher, Shu′al, Be′ri, Im′rah, 37 Be′zer, Hod, Sham′ma, Shil′shah, Ith′ran, and Be·e′ra. 38 The sons of Je′ther were Je·phun′neh, Pis′pah, and A′ra. 39 The sons of Ul′la were A′rah, Han′ni·el, and Ri·zi′a. 40 All of these were the sons of Ash′er, heads of their paternal houses, select, mighty warriors, heads of the chieftains; and their number listed in the genealogical enrollment was 26,000 men in the army available for war.

^ 1 Chron. 7:3 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:3 Lit., “heads.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:13 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:17 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:23 Meaning “With Calamity.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:27 Or “Jehoshua,” meaning “Jehovah Is Salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:28 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:28 Or possibly, “Gaza,” though not the Gaza in Philistia.

^ 1 Chron. 7:34 Also called Shomer in vs. 32.

^ 1 Chron. 7:35 Likely the same as “Hotham” in vs. 32.

1 Chronicles  9 : 1 - 44

9 All the Israelites were enrolled genealogically, and they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel. And Judah was taken into exile to Babylon for their unfaithfulness. 2 The first inhabitants to return to their possession in their cities were some Israelites, the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants.[*] 3 And some of the descendants of Judah, of Benjamin, of E′phra·im, and of Ma·nas′seh settled in Jerusalem: 4 U′thai son of Am·mi′hud son of Om′ri son of Im′ri son of Ba′ni, of the descendants of Pe′rez son of Judah. 5 And of the Shi′lo·nites, A·sai′ah the firstborn and his sons. 6 And of the sons of Ze′rah, Je·u′el and 690 of their brothers.

7 And of the descendants of Benjamin, Sal′lu son of Me·shul′lam son of Hod·a·vi′ah son of Has·se·nu′ah, 8 Ib·ne′iah son of Je·ro′ham, E′lah son of Uz′zi son of Mich′ri, and Me·shul′lam son of Sheph·a·ti′ah son of Reu′el son of Ib·ni′jah. 9 And their brothers by line of descent were 956. All these men were heads of their paternal houses.[*]

10 And of the priests, there were Je·da′iah, Je·hoi′a·rib, Ja′chin, 11 Az·a·ri′ah son of Hil·ki′ah son of Me·shul′lam son of Za′dok son of Me·ra′ioth son of A·hi′tub, a leader of the house[*] of the true God, 12 A·dai′ah son of Je·ro′ham son of Pash′hur son of Mal·chi′jah, Ma′a·sai son of Ad′i·el son of Jah′ze·rah son of Me·shul′lam son of Me·shil′le·mith son of Im′mer, 13 and their brothers, heads of the paternal houses, 1,760 mighty, capable men available for the service of the house of the true God.

14 And of the Levites, there were She·mai′ah son of Has′shub son of Az·ri′kam son of Hash·a·bi′ah from the descendants of Me·rar′i; 15 and Bak·bak′kar, He′resh, Ga′lal, Mat·ta·ni′ah son of Mi′ca son of Zich′ri son of A′saph, 16 O·ba·di′ah son of She·mai′ah son of Ga′lal son of Je·du′thun, and Ber·e·chi′ah son of A′sa son of El·ka′nah, who was dwelling in the settlements of the Ne·toph′a·thites.

17 The gatekeepers were Shal′lum, Ak′kub, Tal′mon, A·hi′man, and their brother Shal′lum the head, 18 and until then he was at the king’s gate to the east. These were the gatekeepers of the camps of the Levites. 19 And Shal′lum son of Ko′re son of E·bi′a·saph son of Kor′ah, and his brothers of his paternal house, the Kor′ah·ites, were over the duties of the service, the doorkeepers of the tent, and their fathers had been over the camp of Jehovah as the keepers of the entryway. 20 It was Phin′e·has the son of El·e·a′zar who had been their leader in the past; Jehovah was with him. 21 Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Me·shel·e·mi′ah was the gatekeeper of the entrance of the tent of meeting.

22 All those selected as gatekeepers at the thresholds numbered 212. They were in their settlements by their genealogical enrollment. David and Samuel the seer appointed these to their office of trust. 23 They and their sons were over the guard service for the gates of the house of Jehovah, the house of the tent. 24 The gatekeepers were on the four sides—east, west, north, and south. 25 From time to time, their brothers were to come in from their settlements for seven days to serve along with them. 26 There were four chief[*] gatekeepers in the office of trust. They were Levites, and they were in charge of the chambers[*] and of the treasuries of the house of the true God. 27 They would spend the night in their stations all around the house of the true God, for they cared for the guard service and were in charge of the key and would open up the house from morning to morning.

28 Some of them were in charge of the utensils of the service; they would count them when they brought them in and count them when they took them out. 29 Some of them were appointed over the utensils, over all the holy utensils, and over the fine flour, the wine, the oil, the frankincense, and the balsam oil. 30 Some of the sons of the priests mixed the ointment of balsam oil. 31 And Mat·ti·thi′ah of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shal′lum the Kor′ah·ite, was in the office of trust over the things baked in pans. 32 Some of their brothers of the Ko′hath·ites were in charge of the layer bread,[*] to prepare it every sabbath.

33 These were the singers, the heads of the paternal houses of the Levites in the chambers,[*] those set free from other duties; for by day and by night it was their responsibility to be on duty. 34 These were the heads of the paternal houses of the Levites by their line of descent, headmen. These lived in Jerusalem.

35 The father of Gib′e·on, Je·i′el, lived in Gib′e·on. His wife’s name was Ma′a·cah. 36 And his firstborn son was Ab′don, followed by Zur, Kish, Ba′al, Ner, Na′dab, 37 Ge′dor, A·hi′o, Zech·a·ri′ah, and Mik′loth. 38 Mik′loth became father to Shim′e·am. And they all lived near their brothers in Jerusalem, along with their other brothers. 39 Ner became father to Kish; Kish became father to Saul; Saul became father to Jon′a·than, Mal′chi-shu′a, A·bin′a·dab, and Esh·ba′al. 40 And Jon′a·than’s son was Mer′ib-ba′al. Mer′ib-ba′al became father to Mi′cah. 41 And the sons of Mi′cah were Pi′thon, Mel′ech, Tahr′e·a, and A′haz. 42 A′haz became father to Ja′rah; Ja′rah became father to Al′e·meth, Az′ma·veth, and Zim′ri. Zim′ri became father to Mo′za. 43 Mo′za became father to Bin′e·a and Re·pha′iah his son, El·e·a′sah his son, A′zel his son. 44 A′zel had six sons, and their names were Az·ri′kam, Bo′che·ru, Ish′ma·el, She·a·ri′ah, O·ba·di′ah, and Ha′nan. These were the sons of A′zel.

^ 1 Chron. 9:2 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:9 Lit., “heads of fathers for the house of their fathers.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:11 Or “temple.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:26 Lit., “mighty.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:26 Or “dining rooms.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:32 That is, the showbread.

^ 1 Chron. 9:33 Or “dining rooms.”

1 Chronicles  11 : 1 - 47

11 In time all the Israelites gathered to David at Heb′ron and said: “Look! We are your own bone and flesh.[*] 2 In times past while Saul was king, you were the one who was leading Israel on its campaigns.[*] And Jehovah your God said to you: ‘You will shepherd my people Israel, and you will become leader over my people Israel.’” 3 So all the elders of Israel came to the king at Heb′ron, and David made a covenant with them in Heb′ron before Jehovah. Then they anointed David as king over Israel, according to Jehovah’s word through Samuel.

4 Later David and all Israel set out for Jerusalem, that is, Je′bus, where the Jeb′u·sites were inhabiting the land. 5 The inhabitants of Je′bus taunted David: “You will never come in here!” However, David captured the stronghold of Zion, which is now the City of David. 6 So David said: “Whoever is the first to strike the Jeb′u·sites will become chief[*] and prince.” And Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah went up first, and he became the chief. 7 Then David took up residence in the stronghold. That is why they called it the City of David. 8 He began to build up the city all around, from the Mound[*] to the areas around it, and Jo′ab restored the rest of the city. 9 Thus David became greater and greater, and Jehovah of armies was with him.

10 Now these are the heads of David’s mighty warriors, who gave him strong support in his kingship, together with all Israel, to make him king according to Jehovah’s word concerning Israel. 11 This is the list of David’s mighty warriors: Ja·sho′be·am the son of a Hach′mon·ite, the head of the three. He brandished his spear over 300 slain at one time. 12 Next to him was El·e·a′zar the son of Do′do the A·ho′hite. He was among the three mighty warriors. 13 He was with David at Pas-dam′mim, where the Phi·lis′tines had gathered together for war. Now there was a plot of land full of barley, and the people had fled because of the Phi·lis′tines. 14 But he took his stand in the middle of the field and defended it and kept striking down the Phi·lis′tines, so that Jehovah brought about a great victory.[*]

15 Three of the 30 headmen went down to the rock, to David at the cave of A·dul′lam, while a Phi·lis′tine army was camped in the Valley[*] of Reph′a·im. 16 David was then in the stronghold, and a garrison of the Phi·lis′tines was in Beth′le·hem. 17 Then David expressed his longing: “If only I could have a drink of the water from the cistern by the gate of Beth′le·hem!” 18 At that the three forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lis′tines and drew water from the cistern by the gate of Beth′le·hem and brought it to David; but David refused to drink it and poured it out to Jehovah. 19 He said: “It is unthinkable on my part from the standpoint of my God to do this! Should I drink the blood of these men who risked their lives?[*] For it was at the risk of their lives[*] that they brought it.” So he refused to drink it. These are the things that his three mighty warriors did.

20 A·bish′ai the brother of Jo′ab became head of another three; he brandished his spear over 300 slain, and he had a reputation like the three. 21 Of the other three, he was more distinguished than two of them, and he was their chief; yet he did not attain to the rank of the first three.

22 Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was a courageous man[*] who performed many exploits in Kab′ze·el. He struck down the two sons of Ar′i·el of Mo′ab, and he descended into a waterpit on a snowy day and killed a lion. 23 He also struck down an Egyptian man of extraordinary size—five cubits[*] tall. Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand like the beam of loom workers, he went against him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. 24 These things Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da did, and he had a reputation like that of the three mighty warriors. 25 Although he was distinguished even more than the thirty, he did not attain to the rank of the three. However, David appointed him over his own bodyguard.

26 The mighty warriors of the military forces were As′a·hel the brother of Jo′ab, El·ha′nan the son of Do′do of Beth′le·hem, 27 Sham′moth the Ha′ro·rite, He′lez the Pel′o·nite, 28 I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite, 29 Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite, I′lai the A·ho′hite, 30 Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite, He′led the son of Ba′a·nah the Ne·toph′a·thite, 31 I′thai the son of Ri′bai of Gib′e·ah of the Ben′ja·min·ites, Be·nai′ah the Pir′a·thon·ite, 32 Hu′rai of the wadis[*] of Ga′ash, A·bi′el the Ar′bath·ite, 33 Az′ma·veth the Ba·ha′rum·ite, E·li′ah·ba the Sha·al′bo·nite, 34 the sons of Ha′shem the Gi′zo·nite, Jon′a·than the son of Sha′gee the Har′a·rite, 35 A·hi′am the son of Sa′car the Har′a·rite, E·li′phal the son of Ur, 36 He′pher the Me·che′rath·ite, A·hi′jah the Pel′o·nite, 37 Hez′ro the Car′mel·ite, Na′a·rai the son of Ez′bai, 38 Joel the brother of Nathan, Mib′har the son of Hag′ri, 39 Ze′lek the Am′mon·ite, Na′ha·rai the Be·roth′ite, the armor-bearer of Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah; 40 I′ra the Ith′rite, Ga′reb the Ith′rite, 41 U·ri′ah the Hit′tite, Za′bad the son of Ah′lai, 42 Ad′i·na the son of Shi′za the Reu′ben·ite, a head of the Reu′ben·ites, and 30 with him; 43 Ha′nan the son of Ma′a·cah, Josh′a·phat the Mith′nite, 44 Uz·zi′a the Ash′te·rath·ite, Sha′ma and Je·i′el, the sons of Ho′tham the A·ro′er·ite; 45 Je·di′a·el the son of Shim′ri, and Jo′ha his brother the Ti′zite; 46 E′li·el the Ma′ha·vite, Jer′i·bai and Josh·a·vi′ah the sons of El′na·am, and Ith′mah the Mo′ab·ite; 47 E′li·el, O′bed, and Ja·a·si′el the Me·zo′ba·ite.

^ 1 Chron. 11:1 Or “your blood relatives.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:2 Lit., “the one bringing out and the one bringing in Israel.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:6 Lit., “head.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:8 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:14 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:15 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:19 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:19 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:22 Lit., “the son of a man of valor.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:23 His height was about 2.23 m (7.3 ft). See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 11:32 See Glossary.

1 Chronicles  12 : 1 - 40

12 These were the men who came to David at Zik′lag while he was unable to move about freely because of Saul the son of Kish, and they were among the mighty warriors who supported him in battle. 2 They were armed with the bow, and they could use both the right hand and the left hand to sling stones or to shoot arrows with the bow. They were of the brothers of Saul, from Benjamin. 3 The head was A·hi·e′zer, along with Jo′ash, both sons of She·ma′ah the Gib′e·ath·ite; Je′zi·el and Pel′et the sons of Az′ma·veth, Ber′a·cah, Je′hu the An′a·thoth·ite, 4 Ish·ma′iah the Gib′e·on·ite, a mighty warrior among the thirty and over the thirty; also Jeremiah, Ja·ha·zi′el, Jo·ha′nan, Jo′za·bad the Ge·de′rath·ite, 5 E·lu′zai, Jer′i·moth, Be·a·li′ah, Shem·a·ri′ah, Sheph·a·ti′ah the Har′i·phite, 6 El·ka′nah, Is·shi′ah, Az′ar·el, Jo·e′zer, and Ja·sho′be·am, the Kor′ah·ites; 7 and Jo·e′lah and Zeb·a·di′ah the sons of Je·ro′ham of Ge′dor.

8 Some of the Gad′ites went over to David’s side at the stronghold in the wilderness; they were mighty warriors, soldiers trained for war, standing ready with the large shield and the lance, whose faces were like those of lions and who were as swift as the gazelles on the mountains. 9 E′zer was the head, O·ba·di′ah the second, E·li′ab the third, 10 Mish·man′nah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, 11 At′tai the sixth, E′li·el the seventh, 12 Jo·ha′nan the eighth, El·za′bad the ninth, 13 Jeremiah the tenth, Mach′ban·nai the eleventh. 14 These were of the Gad′ites, heads of the army. The least one was equal to 100, and the greatest to 1,000. 15 These are the men who crossed the Jordan in the first month when it was overflowing its banks, and they chased away all those living in the lowlands, to the east and to the west.

16 Some of the men of Benjamin and Judah also came to David at his stronghold. 17 Then David went out before them and said to them: “If you have come to me in peace to help me, my heart will be united with you. But if it is to betray me to my adversaries when my hands have done no wrong, let the God of our forefathers see it and judge.” 18 Then the spirit came upon[*] A·ma′sai, the head of the thirty:

“We are yours, O David, and we are with you, O son of Jes′se.

Peace, peace be yours, and peace to the one helping you,

For your God is helping you.”

So David received them and appointed them among the heads of the troops.

19 Some from Ma·nas′seh also deserted to David when he came with the Phi·lis′tines to battle against Saul; but he did not help the Phi·lis′tines, for after consultation, the lords of the Phi·lis′tines sent him away, saying: “He will desert to his lord Saul, and it will cost us our heads.” 20 When he went to Zik′lag, these deserted to him from Ma·nas′seh: Ad′nah, Jo′za·bad, Je·di′a·el, Mi′cha·el, Jo′za·bad, E·li′hu, and Zil′le·thai, heads of the thousands of Ma·nas′seh. 21 They helped David against the marauder band, because all of them were mighty, courageous men, and they became chiefs in the army. 22 Day after day people kept coming to David to help him until it was a camp as great as the camp of God.

23 This is the number of the heads of those armed for battle who came to David at Heb′ron to turn the kingship of Saul over to him according to Jehovah’s order. 24 The men of Judah carrying the large shield and the lance were 6,800, armed for battle. 25 Of the Sim′e·on·ites, the mighty, courageous men of the army were 7,100.

26 Of the Levites, 4,600. 27 Je·hoi′a·da was the leader of the sons of Aaron, and with him were 3,700, 28 as well as Za′dok, a mighty and courageous young man, along with 22 chiefs from his paternal house.

29 Of the Ben′ja·min·ites, the brothers of Saul, there were 3,000, of whom the greater number had previously been guarding the interests of the house of Saul. 30 Of the E′phra·im·ites, there were 20,800 mighty, courageous men of fame among their paternal houses.

31 Of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, there were 18,000 who had been designated by name to come to make David king. 32 Of the tribe of Is′sa·char, who understood the times and knew what Israel should do, there were 200 of their headmen, and all their brothers were under their command. 33 Of Zeb′u·lun, there were 50,000 who could serve in the army, drawing up in battle formation with all the weapons of war, all joining David with undivided loyalty.[*] 34 Of Naph′ta·li, there were 1,000 chiefs, and with them were 37,000 with the large shield and the spear. 35 Of the Dan′ites, those drawing up in battle formation were 28,600. 36 And of Ash′er, those who could serve in the army for drawing up in battle formation were 40,000.

37 From across the Jordan, of the Reu′ben·ites, the Gad′ites, and the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, there were 120,000 soldiers with all kinds of weapons of war. 38 All of these were men of war, joining together in battle line; they came with a complete heart to Heb′ron to make David king over all Israel, and also all the rest of Israel were united in wanting[*] to make David king. 39 And they remained there with David for three days, eating and drinking, for their brothers had made preparation for them. 40 Also those near them, and even those as far as Is′sa·char, Zeb′u·lun, and Naph′ta·li, were bringing food on donkeys, camels, mules, and cattle—provisions of flour, cakes of pressed figs and raisins, wine, oil, and cattle and sheep in great quantity, for there was rejoicing in Israel.

^ 1 Chron. 12:18 Lit., “clothed.”

^ 1 Chron. 12:33 Or “all those joining David were not doublehearted.”

^ 1 Chron. 12:38 Lit., “were of one heart.”

1 Chronicles  14 : 1 - 17

14 King Hi′ram of Tyre sent messengers to David, along with cedar timbers, stonemasons,[*] and woodworkers to build a house[*] for him. 2 And David knew that Jehovah had firmly established him as king over Israel, for his kingship was highly exalted for the sake of His people Israel.

3 David took more wives in Jerusalem, and David became father to more sons and daughters. 4 These are the names of the children born to him in Jerusalem: Sham·mu′a, Sho′bab, Nathan, Sol′o·mon, 5 Ib′har, E·li′shu·a, El′pe·let, 6 No′gah, Ne′pheg, Ja·phi′a, 7 E·lish′a·ma, Be·e·li′a·da, and E·liph′e·let.

8 When the Phi·lis′tines heard that David had been anointed as king over all Israel, all the Phi·lis′tines came up to search for David. When David heard about it, he went out against them. 9 Then the Phi·lis′tines came in and kept making raids in the Valley[*] of Reph′a·im. 10 David inquired of God, saying: “Should I go up against the Phi·lis′tines? Will you give them into my hand?” At this Jehovah said to him: “Go up, and I will surely give them into your hand.” 11 So David went up to Ba′al-pe·ra′zim, and he struck them down there. At that David said: “The true God has broken through my enemies by my hand, like a breach made by waters.” That is why they named that place Ba′al-pe·ra′zim.[*] 12 The Phi·lis′tines abandoned their gods there, and when David gave the order, these were burned in the fire.

13 Later the Phi·lis′tines once again made a raid in the valley.[*] 14 David again inquired of God, but the true God said to him: “Do not go directly up after them. Instead, go around behind them, and come against them in front of the ba′ca bushes. 15 And when you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the ba′ca bushes, launch your attack, for the true God will have gone out before you to strike down the army of the Phi·lis′tines.” 16 So David did just as the true God commanded him, and they struck down the Phi·lis′tine army from Gib′e·on to Ge′zer. 17 And David’s fame spread into all the lands, and Jehovah put the dread of him upon all the nations.

^ 1 Chron. 14:1 Or “builders of walls.”

^ 1 Chron. 14:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Chron. 14:9 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Chron. 14:11 Meaning “Master of Breakings Through.”

^ 1 Chron. 14:13 Or “low plain.”

1 Chronicles  18 : 1 - 17

18 Some time later, David defeated the Phi·lis′tines and subdued them and took Gath and its dependent[*] towns out of the hands of the Phi·lis′tines. 2 Then he defeated Mo′ab, and the Mo′ab·ites became David’s servants and brought tribute.

3 David defeated King Had·ad·e′zer of Zo′bah near Ha′math as he was on his way to establish his authority at the Eu·phra′tes River. 4 David captured 1,000 chariots, 7,000 horsemen, and 20,000 foot soldiers from him. Then David hamstrung all but 100 of the chariot horses. 5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help King Had·ad·e′zer of Zo′bah, David struck down 22,000 of the Syrians. 6 David then established garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians became David’s servants and brought tribute. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. 7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold from the servants of Had·ad·e′zer and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 From Tib′hath and Cun, cities of Had·ad·e′zer, David took a great quantity of copper. With it Sol′o·mon made the copper Sea, the pillars, and the copper utensils.

9 When King To′u of Ha′math heard that David had defeated the entire army of King Had·ad·e′zer of Zo′bah, 10 he immediately sent his son Ha·do′ram to King David to ask about his welfare and to congratulate him because he had fought and defeated Had·ad·e′zer (for Had·ad·e′zer had often fought against To′u), and he brought all sorts of articles of gold, silver, and copper. 11 King David sanctified these to Jehovah, along with the silver and the gold that he had carried off from all the nations: from E′dom and Mo′ab, from the Am′mon·ites, the Phi·lis′tines, and the A·mal′ek·ites.

12 A·bish′ai the son of Ze·ru′iah struck down 18,000 E′dom·ites in the Valley of Salt. 13 He established garrisons in E′dom, and all the E′dom·ites became David’s servants. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. 14 David kept reigning over all Israel, and he was administering justice and righteousness for all his people. 15 Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah was over the army, Je·hosh′a·phat the son of A·hi′lud was recorder, 16 Za′dok the son of A·hi′tub and A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar were priests, and Shav′sha was secretary. 17 Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da was over the Cher′e·thites and the Pel′e·thites. And David’s sons were first in position next to the king.

^ 1 Chron. 18:1 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 18:6 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 18:13 Or “salvation.”

1 Chronicles  24 : 1 - 31

24 Now the divisions of the descendants of Aaron were these: The sons of Aaron were Na′dab, A·bi′hu, El·e·a′zar, and Ith′a·mar. 2 However, Na′dab and A·bi′hu died before their father, and they did not have any sons; but El·e·a′zar and Ith′a·mar continued to serve as priests. 3 David, along with Za′dok from the sons of El·e·a′zar and A·him′e·lech from the sons of Ith′a·mar, made divisions of them for the office of their service. 4 Since the sons of El·e·a′zar had more headmen than the sons of Ith′a·mar had, they divided them accordingly: The sons of El·e·a′zar had 16 as heads of their paternal houses, and the sons of Ith′a·mar had 8 as heads of their paternal houses.

5 Further, they divided them by lots, the one group along with the other, for there were chiefs of the holy place and chiefs of the true God from both the sons of El·e·a′zar and the sons of Ith′a·mar. 6 Then She·mai′ah the son of Ne·than′el the secretary of the Levites recorded their names before the king, the princes, Za′dok the priest, A·him′e·lech the son of A·bi′a·thar, and the heads of the paternal houses of the priests and of the Levites, one paternal house being selected for El·e·a′zar and one being selected for Ith′a·mar.

7 The first lot came out to Je·hoi′a·rib; the second to Je·da′iah, 8 the third to Ha′rim, the fourth to Se·o′rim, 9 the fifth to Mal·chi′jah, the sixth to Mij′a·min, 10 the seventh to Hak′koz, the eighth to A·bi′jah, 11 the ninth to Jesh′u·a, the tenth to Shec·a·ni′ah, 12 the 11th to E·li′a·shib, the 12th to Ja′kim, 13 the 13th to Hup′pah, the 14th to Je·sheb′e·ab, 14 the 15th to Bil′gah, the 16th to Im′mer, 15 the 17th to He′zir, the 18th to Hap′piz·zez, 16 the 19th to Peth·a·hi′ah, the 20th to Je·hez′kel, 17 the 21st to Ja′chin, the 22nd to Ga′mul, 18 the 23rd to De·la′iah, the 24th to Ma·a·zi′ah.

19 These were their offices for their service when they would come into the house of Jehovah according to the procedure set by their forefather Aaron, just as Jehovah the God of Israel had commanded him.

20 And of the rest of the Levites: of the sons of Am′ram, there was Shu′ba·el; of the sons of Shu′ba·el, Jeh·de′iah; 21 of Re·ha·bi′ah: of the sons of Re·ha·bi′ah, Is·shi′ah the head; 22 of the Iz′har·ites, She·lo′moth; of the sons of She·lo′moth, Ja′hath; 23 and of the sons of Heb′ron, Je·ri′ah the head, Am·a·ri′ah the second, Ja·ha·zi′el the third, Jek·a·me′am the fourth; 24 of the sons of Uz′zi·el, Mi′cah; of the sons of Mi′cah, Sha′mir. 25 The brother of Mi′cah was Is·shi′ah; of the sons of Is·shi′ah, Zech·a·ri′ah.

26 The sons of Me·rar′i were Mah′li and Mu′shi; of the sons of Ja·a·zi′ah, Be′no. 27 The sons of Me·rar′i: of Ja·a·zi′ah, Be′no, Sho′ham, Zac′cur, and Ib′ri; 28 of Mah′li, El·e·a′zar, who did not have any sons; 29 of Kish: the sons of Kish, Je·rah′me·el; 30 and the sons of Mu′shi were Mah′li, E′der, and Jer′i·moth.

These were the sons of Le′vi by their paternal houses. 31 And they also cast lots just as their brothers the sons of Aaron did in the presence of King David, Za′dok, A·him′e·lech, and the heads of the paternal houses of the priests and of the Levites. Regarding the paternal houses, the head one was just as his younger brother.

1 Chronicles  26 : 1 - 32

26 The divisions of gatekeepers were as follows: of the Kor′ah·ites, Me·shel·e·mi′ah the son of Ko′re of the sons of A′saph. 2 And Me·shel·e·mi′ah had sons: Zech·a·ri′ah the firstborn, Je·di′a·el the second, Zeb·a·di′ah the third, Jath′ni·el the fourth, 3 E′lam the fifth, Je·ho·ha′nan the sixth, El′ie·ho-e′nai the seventh. 4 And O′bed-e′dom had sons: She·mai′ah the firstborn, Je·hoz′a·bad the second, Jo′ah the third, Sa′car the fourth, Ne·than′el the fifth, 5 Am′mi·el the sixth, Is′sa·char the seventh, and Pe·ul′le·thai the eighth; for God had blessed him.

6 And to his son She·mai′ah, there were sons born who were rulers of their paternal house, for they were mighty, capable men. 7 The sons of She·mai′ah: Oth′ni, Reph′a·el, O′bed, and El·za′bad; and his brothers E·li′hu and Sem·a·chi′ah were also capable men. 8 All of these were of the sons of O′bed-e′dom; they and their sons and their brothers were capable men and qualified for the service, 62 belonging to O′bed-e′dom. 9 And Me·shel·e·mi′ah had sons and brothers, 18 capable men. 10 And Ho′sah of the sons of Me·rar′i had sons. Shim′ri was the head, for although he was not the firstborn, his father appointed him as head, 11 Hil·ki′ah the second, Teb·a·li′ah the third, Zech·a·ri′ah the fourth. All the sons and brothers of Ho′sah were 13.

12 Of these divisions of the gatekeepers, the headmen had duties just as their brothers did, to minister at the house of Jehovah. 13 So they cast lots, the small and the great alike by their paternal houses, for the different gates. 14 Then the lot to the east fell to Shel·e·mi′ah. For Zech·a·ri′ah his son, a discreet adviser, they cast the lots, and his lot came out to the north. 15 O′bed-e′dom had his to the south, and his sons were assigned the storehouses. 16 Shup′pim and Ho′sah had theirs to the west, near the Shal′lech·eth Gate by the highway that goes up, guard group corresponding to guard group; 17 there were six Levites to the east; to the north, four each day and to the south, four each day; and for the storehouses, two by two; 18 for the portico to the west, there were four at the highway and two at the portico. 19 These were the divisions of the gatekeepers from the sons of the Kor′ah·ites and of the Me·rar′ites.

20 As regards the Levites, A·hi′jah was in charge of the treasuries of the house of the true God and the treasuries of the things made holy.[*] 21 The sons of La′dan: the sons of the Ger′shon·ite belonging to La′dan, the heads of the paternal houses belonging to La′dan the Ger′shon·ite, Je·hi′e·li 22 and the sons of Je·hi′e·li, Ze′tham and his brother Joel. They were in charge of the treasuries of the house of Jehovah. 23 From the Am′ram·ites, the Iz′har·ites, the Heb′ron·ites, and the Uz·zi′el·ites, 24 Sheb′u·el son of Ger′shom son of Moses was a leader in charge of the storehouses. 25 As regards his brothers, of E·li·e′zer, there was Re·ha·bi′ah his son, Je·sha′iah his son, Jo′ram his son, Zich′ri his son, and She·lo′moth his son. 26 This She·lo′moth and his brothers were in charge of all the treasuries of the things made holy, which King David, the heads of the paternal houses, the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, and the chiefs of the army had made holy. 27 From the wars and from the spoil, they had made things holy to maintain the house of Jehovah; 28 also, all that Samuel the seer, Saul the son of Kish, Ab′ner the son of Ner, and Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah had made holy. Whatever anyone made holy was put in the care of She·lo′mith and his brothers.

29 Of the Iz′har·ites, Chen·a·ni′ah and his sons were assigned outside administrative duties as officers and as judges over Israel.

30 Of the Heb′ron·ites, Hash·a·bi′ah and his brothers, 1,700 capable men, were over the administration of Israel in the region west of the Jordan for all the work of Jehovah and for the king’s service. 31 Of the Heb′ron·ites, Je·ri′jah was the head of the Heb′ron·ites by line of descent of their paternal house. In the 40th year of David’s kingship, they were sought out, and mighty, capable men were found among them in Ja′zer in Gil′e·ad. 32 And his brothers numbered 2,700 capable men, heads of the paternal houses. So King David assigned them over the Reu′ben·ites, the Gad′ites, and the half tribe of the Ma·nas′sites, for every matter of the true God and matter of the king.

^ 1 Chron. 26:20 Or “the things dedicated.”

1 Chronicles  27 : 1 - 34

27 This is the number of Israelites, the heads of the paternal houses, the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, and their officers who ministered to the king in every matter of the divisions that would come in and go out month by month during all the months of the year; there were 24,000 in each division.

2 Over the first division of the first month was Ja·sho′be·am the son of Zab′di·el, and 24,000 were in his division. 3 Of the sons of Pe′rez, he was the head of all the chiefs of the groups assigned to serve during the first month. 4 Over the division of the second month was Do′dai the A·ho′hite with his division, and Mik′loth was the leader, and 24,000 were in his division. 5 The chief of the third group assigned to serve during the third month was Be·nai′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·da the chief priest, and 24,000 were in his division. 6 This Be·nai′ah was a mighty warrior of the thirty and in charge of the thirty, and over his division was his son Am·miz′a·bad. 7 The fourth for the fourth month was As′a·hel, Jo′ab’s brother, and his son Zeb·a·di′ah after him, and 24,000 were in his division. 8 The fifth chief for the fifth month was Sham′huth the Iz′rah·ite, and 24,000 were in his division. 9 The sixth for the sixth month was I′ra the son of Ik′kesh the Te·ko′ite, and 24,000 were in his division. 10 The seventh for the seventh month was He′lez the Pel′o·nite of the E′phra·im·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. 11 The eighth for the eighth month was Sib′be·cai the Hu′shath·ite of the Ze′rah·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. 12 The ninth for the ninth month was Abi-e′zer the An′a·thoth·ite of the Ben′ja·min·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. 13 The tenth for the tenth month was Ma′ha·rai the Ne·toph′a·thite of the Ze′rah·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. 14 The 11th for the 11th month was Be·nai′ah the Pir′a·thon·ite of the sons of E′phra·im, and 24,000 were in his division. 15 The 12th for the 12th month was Hel′dai the Ne·toph′a·thite, of Oth′ni·el, and 24,000 were in his division.

16 These were the leaders of the tribes of Israel: Of the Reu′ben·ites, E·li·e′zer the son of Zich′ri was leader; of the Sim′e·on·ites, Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of Ma′a·cah; 17 of Le′vi, Hash·a·bi′ah the son of Kem·u′el; of Aaron, Za′dok; 18 of Judah, E·li′hu, one of David’s brothers; of Is′sa·char, Om′ri the son of Mi′cha·el; 19 of Zeb′u·lun, Ish·ma′iah the son of O·ba·di′ah; of Naph′ta·li, Jer′i·moth the son of Az′ri·el; 20 of the E′phra·im·ites, Ho·she′a the son of Az·a·zi′ah; of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh, Joel the son of Pe·dai′ah; 21 of the half tribe of Ma·nas′seh in Gil′e·ad, Id′do the son of Zech·a·ri′ah; of Benjamin, Ja·a·si′el the son of Ab′ner; 22 of Dan, Az′ar·el the son of Je·ro′ham. These were the princes of the tribes of Israel.

23 David did not count those 20 years of age and under, because Jehovah had promised to make Israel as many as the stars of the heavens. 24 Jo′ab the son of Ze·ru′iah had started to take the count, but he did not finish; and God’s anger came against Israel[*] because of this, and the number was not entered into the account of the history of the times of King David.

25 Over the treasuries of the king was Az′ma·veth the son of Ad′i·el. Jon′a·than the son of Uz·zi′ah was over the storehouses[*] in the fields, in the cities, in the villages, and in the towers. 26 Over the field workers who cultivated the soil was Ez′ri the son of Che′lub. 27 Shim′e·i the Ra′math·ite was over the vineyards; over the produce of the vineyards for the wine supplies was Zab′di the Shiph′mite. 28 Over the olive groves and the sycamore trees in the She·phe′lah was Ba′al-ha′nan the Ge·de′rite; over the oil supplies was Jo′ash. 29 Over the herds that grazed in Shar′on was Shit′rai the Shar′on·ite, and Sha′phat the son of Ad′lai was over the herds in the valley plains.[*] 30 Over the camels was O′bil the Ish′ma·el·ite; over the donkeys[*] was Jeh·de′iah the Me·ron′o·thite. 31 Over the flocks was Ja′ziz the Hag′rite. All of these were the chiefs of King David’s property.

32 Jon′a·than, David’s nephew, was an adviser, a man of understanding and a secretary, and Je·hi′el the son of Hach′mo·ni looked after the king’s sons. 33 A·hith′o·phel was an adviser to the king, and Hu′shai the Ar′chite was the king’s friend.[*] 34 After A·hith′o·phel there were Je·hoi′a·da the son of Be·nai′ah and A·bi′a·thar; and Jo′ab was chief of the king’s army.

^ 1 Chron. 27:24 Lit., “and anger was on Israel.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:25 Or “treasuries.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:29 Or “low plains.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:30 Lit., “female donkeys.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:33 Or “confidant.”

2 Chronicles  9 : 1 - 31

9 Now the queen of She′ba heard the report about Sol′o·mon, so she came to Jerusalem to test Sol′o·mon with perplexing questions.[*] She was accompanied by a very impressive entourage,[*] with camels carrying balsam oil and great quantities of gold and precious stones. She went in to Sol′o·mon and spoke to him about everything that was close to her heart. 2 Sol′o·mon then answered all her questions. There was nothing too difficult for[*] Sol′o·mon to explain to her.

3 When the queen of She′ba had seen Sol′o·mon’s wisdom, the house that he built, 4 the food of his table, the seating of his servants, the table service of his waiters and their attire, his cupbearers and their attire, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, she was left completely breathless.[*] 5 So she said to the king: “The report that I heard in my own land about your achievements[*] and about your wisdom was true. 6 But I did not put faith in the reports until I had come and had seen it with my own eyes. And look! I had not been told the half of your great wisdom. You have far surpassed the report that I heard. 7 Happy are your men, and happy are your servants who stand before you constantly, listening to your wisdom! 8 May Jehovah your God be praised, who has taken pleasure in you by putting you on his throne as king for Jehovah your God. Because your God loves Israel, in order to make it continue forever, he appointed you over it as king to administer justice and righteousness.”

9 Then she gave the king 120 talents[*] of gold and a great quantity of balsam oil and precious stones. Never again was such balsam oil brought in as what the queen of She′ba gave to King Sol′o·mon.

10 Moreover, the servants of Hi′ram and the servants of Sol′o·mon who brought gold from O′phir also brought algum timbers and precious stones. 11 The king made from the algum timbers stairs for the house of Jehovah and for the king’s house,[*] as well as harps and stringed instruments for the singers. Nothing like them had ever been seen before in the land of Judah.

12 King Sol′o·mon also gave the queen of She′ba whatever she desired and asked for, more than[*] what she had brought to the king. Then she left and returned to her own land, together with her servants.

13 And the weight of the gold that came to Sol′o·mon in one year amounted to 666 talents of gold, 14 besides that brought in by the merchants and the traders and all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land who were bringing gold and silver in to Sol′o·mon.

15 King Sol′o·mon made 200 large shields of alloyed gold (600 shekels[*] of alloyed gold went on each shield) 16 and 300 bucklers[*] of alloyed gold (three mi′nas[*] of gold went on each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non.

17 The king also made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with pure gold. 18 There were six steps to the throne, and there was a gold footstool attached to the throne, and there were armrests on both sides of the seat, and two lions were standing beside the armrests. 19 And there were 12 lions standing on the six steps, one at each end of the six steps. No other kingdom had made anything like it. 20 All the drinking vessels of King Sol′o·mon were of gold, and all the utensils of the House of the Forest of Leb′a·non were of pure gold. There was nothing made of silver, for silver was considered as nothing in the days of Sol′o·mon. 21 For the king’s ships would go to Tar′shish with the servants of Hi′ram. Once every three years, the ships of Tar′shish would come loaded with gold and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.

22 So King Sol′o·mon was greater than all the other kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. 23 And the kings of all the earth sought an audience with[*] Sol′o·mon to hear his wisdom that the true God had put in his heart. 24 They would each bring a gift—articles of silver, articles of gold, garments, armor, balsam oil, horses, and mules—and this continued year after year. 25 And Sol′o·mon had 4,000 stalls for his horses and chariots and 12,000 horses,[*] and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem. 26 And he ruled over all the kings from the River[*] to the land of the Phi·lis′tines and to the boundary of Egypt. 27 The king made the silver in Jerusalem as plentiful as the stones, and cedarwood as plentiful as the sycamore trees in the She·phe′lah. 28 And they would bring horses to Sol′o·mon from Egypt and from all the other lands.

29 As for the rest of the history of Sol′o·mon, from beginning to end, is it not written among the words of Nathan the prophet, in the prophecy of A·hi′jah the Shi′lo·nite, and in the record of visions of Id′do the visionary concerning Jer·o·bo′am the son of Ne′bat? 30 Sol′o·mon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel for 40 years. 31 Then Sol′o·mon was laid to rest with his forefathers. So they buried him in the City of David his father; and his son Re·ho·bo′am became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 9:1 Or “with riddles.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:1 Or “train.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:2 Lit., “nothing hidden from.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:4 Lit., “there was no more spirit in her.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:5 Or “words.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:9 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:11 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:12 Or possibly, “in addition to gifts corresponding to the value of.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:15 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:16 A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ 2 Chron. 9:16 A mina in the Hebrew Scriptures equaled 570 g (18.35 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:23 Lit., “sought the face of.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:25 Or “horsemen.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:26 That is, the Euphrates.

2 Chronicles  17 : 1 - 19

17 And his son Je·hosh′a·phat became king in his place, and he strengthened his position over Israel. 2 He stationed military forces in all the fortified cities of Judah and put garrisons in the land of Judah and in the cities of E′phra·im that A′sa his father had captured. 3 Jehovah continued with Je·hosh′a·phat because he walked in the former ways of his forefather David and did not search for the Ba′als. 4 For he searched for the God of his father and followed[*] his commandment and not the practices of Israel. 5 Jehovah kept the kingdom firmly established in his hand; and all Judah continued to give gifts to Je·hosh′a·phat, and he had riches and glory in abundance. 6 His heart became bold in the ways of Jehovah, and he even removed the high places and the sacred poles[*] from Judah.

7 In the third year of his reign he sent for his princes, Ben-ha′il, O·ba·di′ah, Zech·a·ri′ah, Ne·than′el, and Mi·cai′ah, to teach in the cities of Judah. 8 There were Levites with them: She·mai′ah, Neth·a·ni′ah, Zeb·a·di′ah, As′a·hel, She·mir′a·moth, Je·hon′a·than, Ad·o·ni′jah, To·bi′jah, and Tob-ad·o·ni′jah, and along with them E·lish′a·ma and Je·ho′ram the priests. 9 They began teaching in Judah, taking with them the book of Jehovah’s Law, and they went around through all the cities of Judah teaching among the people.

10 And the dread of Jehovah came upon all the kingdoms of the lands surrounding Judah, and they did not fight against Je·hosh′a·phat. 11 And the Phi·lis′tines brought to Je·hosh′a·phat gifts and money as tribute. The Arabs brought him 7,700 rams and 7,700 male goats from their flocks.

12 Je·hosh′a·phat grew greater and greater, and he continued building fortified places and storage cities in Judah. 13 He carried out extensive projects in the cities of Judah, and he had soldiers, mighty warriors, in Jerusalem. 14 These were grouped by their paternal houses: of Judah the chiefs of thousands, Ad′nah the chief, and with him were 300,000 mighty warriors. 15 And under his command was Je·ho·ha′nan the chief, and with him were 280,000. 16 And also under his command was Am·a·si′ah the son of Zich′ri, who volunteered for Jehovah’s service, and with him were 200,000 mighty warriors. 17 And out of Benjamin was E·li′a·da, a mighty warrior, and with him were 200,000 men equipped with the bow and shield. 18 And under his command was Je·hoz′a·bad, and with him were 180,000 men equipped for the army. 19 These were ministering to the king in addition to those whom the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.

^ 2 Chron. 17:4 Lit., “walked in.”

^ 2 Chron. 17:6 See Glossary.

2 Chronicles  22 : 1 - 12

22 Then the inhabitants of Jerusalem made his youngest son A·ha·zi′ah king in his place, for the marauder band that came with the Arabs to the camp had killed all the older ones. So A·ha·zi′ah the son of Je·ho′ram began to reign as king of Judah. 2 A·ha·zi′ah was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ath·a·li′ah the granddaughter[*] of Om′ri.

3 He too walked in the ways of the house of A′hab, for his mother became his adviser in acting wickedly. 4 And he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of A′hab, for they became his advisers after the death of his father, to his destruction. 5 He followed their advice and went with Je·ho′ram the son of King A′hab of Israel to wage war against King Haz′a·el of Syria at Ra′moth-gil′e·ad, where the archers wounded Je·ho′ram. 6 He returned to Jez′re·el to recover from the wounds that they had inflicted on him at Ra′mah when he fought against King Haz′a·el of Syria.

A·ha·zi′ah[*] the son of Je·ho′ram the king of Judah went down to Jez′re·el to see Je·ho′ram the son of A′hab, because he had been wounded.[*] 7 But God brought about the downfall of A·ha·zi′ah by his coming to Je·ho′ram; and when he came, he went out with Je·ho′ram to meet Je′hu the grandson[*] of Nim′shi, whom Jehovah had anointed to do away with[*] the house of A′hab. 8 When Je′hu began to execute judgment on the house of A′hab, he found the princes of Judah and the sons of A·ha·zi′ah’s brothers, ministers of A·ha·zi′ah, and he killed them. 9 Then he looked for A·ha·zi′ah; they captured him where he was hiding in Sa·mar′i·a, and they brought him to Je′hu. Then they put him to death and buried him, for they said: “He is the grandson of Je·hosh′a·phat, who searched for Jehovah with all his heart.” There was no one of the house of A·ha·zi′ah who had the power to rule the kingdom.

10 When Ath·a·li′ah, A·ha·zi′ah’s mother, saw that her son had died, she rose up and destroyed the entire royal line[*] of the house of Judah. 11 However, Je·ho·shab′e·ath the daughter of the king took Je·ho′ash the son of A·ha·zi′ah and stole him away from among the sons of the king who were to be put to death, and she put him and his nurse in an inner bedroom. Je·ho·shab′e·ath the daughter of King Je·ho′ram (she was the wife of Je·hoi′a·da the priest and a sister of A·ha·zi′ah) managed to keep him concealed from Ath·a·li′ah, so that she did not put him to death. 12 He remained with them for six years, hidden at the house of the true God, while Ath·a·li′ah was ruling over the land.

^ 2 Chron. 22:2 Lit., “daughter.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:6 In some Hebrew manuscripts, “Azariah.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:6 Or “he was sick.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:7 Lit., “son.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:7 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:10 Lit., “all seed of the kingdom.”

2 Chronicles  34 : 1 - 33

34 Jo·si′ah was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned for 31 years in Jerusalem. 2 He did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes and walked in the ways of David his forefather, and he did not deviate to the right or to the left.

3 In the 8th year of his reign, while he was still a boy, he started to search for the God of David his forefather; and in the 12th year, he started to cleanse Judah and Jerusalem of the high places and the sacred poles,[*] the graven images, and the metal statues.[*] 4 Further, they tore down the altars of the Ba′als in his presence, and he cut down the incense stands that were up above them. He also broke into pieces the sacred poles,[*] the graven images, and the metal statues[*] and reduced them to powder and sprinkled it over the graves of those who used to sacrifice to them. 5 And he burned the bones of priests on their altars. Thus he cleansed Judah and Jerusalem.

6 And in the cities of Ma·nas′seh, E′phra·im, Sim′e·on, and clear to Naph′ta·li, in their surrounding ruins, 7 he tore down the altars and he crushed the sacred poles[*] and the graven images, reducing them to powder; and he cut down all the incense stands in all the land of Israel, after which he returned to Jerusalem.

8 In the 18th year of his reign, when he had cleansed the land and the temple,[*] he sent Sha′phan the son of Az·a·li′ah, Ma·a·sei′ah the chief of the city, and Jo′ah the son of Jo′a·haz the recorder to repair the house of Jehovah his God. 9 They came to Hil·ki′ah the high priest and gave him the money that had been brought to the house of God, which the Levites serving as doorkeepers had collected from Ma·nas′seh, E′phra·im, and all the rest of Israel, as well as from Judah, Benjamin, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 10 Then they gave it to those who were appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah. In turn the workers in the house of Jehovah used it to mend and repair the house. 11 They gave it to the craftsmen and the builders to buy hewn stones and timbers for braces and to build with beams the houses that the kings of Judah had allowed to fall into ruin.

12 And the men did the work faithfully. Over them were appointed the Levites Ja′hath and O·ba·di′ah of the Me·rar′ites, and Zech·a·ri′ah and Me·shul′lam of the Ko′hath·ites, to serve as overseers. And the Levites, all of whom were skilled musicians, 13 were in charge of the common laborers[*] and were overseers of all those who were doing the work in every kind of service; and some of the Levites were secretaries, officers, and gatekeepers.

14 While they were taking out the money that had been brought to the house of Jehovah, Hil·ki′ah the priest found the book of Jehovah’s Law given through[*] Moses. 15 So Hil·ki′ah said to Sha′phan the secretary: “I have found the book of the Law in the house of Jehovah.” With that Hil·ki′ah gave the book to Sha′phan. 16 Then Sha′phan brought the book to the king and told him: “Your servants are doing everything that was assigned to them. 17 They have poured out the money that was found in the house of Jehovah, and they have handed it over to the appointed men and to those doing the work.” 18 Sha′phan the secretary also told the king: “There is a book that Hil·ki′ah the priest has given me.” Then Sha′phan began to read from it before the king.

19 As soon as the king heard the words of the Law, he ripped his garments apart. 20 Then the king gave this order to Hil·ki′ah, A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan, Ab′don the son of Mi′cah, Sha′phan the secretary, and A·sai′ah the king’s servant: 21 “Go, inquire of Jehovah in my behalf and in behalf of those who remain in Israel and in Judah concerning the words of the book that has been found; for Jehovah’s rage that will be poured out against us is great because our forefathers did not carry out the word of Jehovah by observing all that is written in this book.”

22 So Hil·ki′ah, along with those sent by the king, went to Hul′dah the prophetess. She was the wife of Shal′lum son of Tik′vah son of Har′has, the caretaker of the wardrobe, and she was dwelling in the Second Quarter of Jerusalem; and they spoke to her there. 23 She said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Tell the man who sent you to me: 24 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘I will bring calamity on this place and its inhabitants, all the curses that are written in the book that they read before the king of Judah. 25 Because they have abandoned me and are making sacrifices smoke to other gods in order to offend me with all the works of their hands, my rage will pour out on this place and it will not be extinguished.’” 26 But to the king of Judah who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, this is what you should say to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Regarding the words that you have heard, 27 because your heart was responsive[*] and you humbled yourself before God on hearing his words concerning this place and its inhabitants and you humbled yourself before me and ripped your garments apart and wept before me, I also have heard you, declares Jehovah. 28 That is why I will gather you to your ancestors,[*] and you will be laid in your grave in peace, and your eyes will not see all the calamity that I will bring on this place and its inhabitants.’”’”

Then they brought the reply to the king. 29 So the king sent word and summoned all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. 30 After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, the Levites—all the people, the great as well as the small. He read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant that had been found in the house of Jehovah. 31 The king stood in his place and made a covenant[*] before Jehovah that he would follow Jehovah and keep his commandments, his reminders, and his regulations with all his heart and with all his soul[*] by carrying out the words of the covenant that were written in this book. 32 Furthermore, he had all those who were in Jerusalem and Benjamin to agree to it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem acted according to the covenant of God, the God of their forefathers. 33 Jo·si′ah then removed all the detestable things[*] out of all the lands that belonged to the Israelites, and he made everyone in Israel serve Jehovah their God. Throughout his lifetime[*] they did not deviate from following Jehovah the God of their forefathers.

^ 2 Chron. 34:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:3 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:4 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:4 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:8 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:13 Or “the burden bearers.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:14 Lit., “by the hand of.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:27 Lit., “soft.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:28 This is a poetic expression for death.

^ 2 Chron. 34:31 Or “renewed the covenant.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:31 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:33 Or “idols.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:33 Lit., “All his days.”

Ezra  8 : 1 - 36

8 Now these were the heads of their paternal houses and the genealogical enrollment of those who went up with me out of Babylon during the reign of King Ar·ta·xerx′es: 2 of the sons of Phin′e·has, Ger′shom; of the sons of Ith′a·mar, Daniel; of the sons of David, Hat′tush; 3 of the sons of Shec·a·ni′ah, of the sons of Pa′rosh, Zech·a·ri′ah, and with him there was an enrollment of 150 males; 4 of the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, El′ie·ho-e′nai the son of Zer·a·hi′ah, and with him 200 males; 5 of the sons of Zat′tu, Shec·a·ni′ah the son of Ja·ha·zi′el, and with him 300 males; 6 of the sons of A′din, E′bed the son of Jon′a·than, and with him 50 males; 7 of the sons of E′lam, Je·sha′iah the son of Ath·a·li′ah, and with him 70 males; 8 of the sons of Sheph·a·ti′ah, Zeb·a·di′ah the son of Mi′cha·el, and with him 80 males; 9 of the sons of Jo′ab, O·ba·di′ah the son of Je·hi′el, and with him 218 males; 10 of the sons of Ba′ni, She·lo′mith the son of Jo·si·phi′ah, and with him 160 males; 11 of the sons of Be′bai, Zech·a·ri′ah the son of Be′bai, and with him 28 males; 12 of the sons of Az′gad, Jo·ha′nan the son of Hak′ka·tan, and with him 110 males; 13 of the sons of Ad·o·ni′kam, those who were the last, and these were their names: E·liph′e·let, Je·i′el, and She·mai′ah, and with them 60 males; 14 and of the sons of Big′vai, U′thai and Zab′bud, and with them 70 males.

15 I assembled them at the river that comes to A·ha′va, and we camped there for three days. But when I examined the people and the priests, I did not find any of the Levites there. 16 So I sent for E·li·e′zer, Ar′i·el, She·mai′ah, El·na′than, Ja′rib, El·na′than, Nathan, Zech·a·ri′ah, and Me·shul′lam, who were leading men, and for Joi′a·rib and El·na′than, who were instructors. 17 Then I gave them a command concerning Id′do the leader in the place called Ca·si·phi′a. I told them to tell Id′do and his brothers, the temple servants[*] who were in Ca·si·phi′a, to bring to us ministers for the house of our God. 18 Since the good hand of our God was upon us, they brought a discreet man from the sons of Mah′li the grandson of Le′vi the son of Israel, namely, She·re·bi′ah, and his sons and his brothers, 18 men; 19 and Hash·a·bi′ah, and with him Je·sha′iah from the Me·rar′ites, his brothers and their sons, 20 men. 20 And there were 220 of the temple servants,[*] whom David and the princes gave to the service of the Levites, all of whom had been designated by name.

21 Then I proclaimed a fast there at the river A·ha′va, to humble ourselves before our God, to seek guidance from him for our journey, for us and for our children and for all our goods. 22 I was ashamed to ask the king for soldiers and horsemen to protect us against the enemies along the way, because we had said to the king: “The good hand of our God is over all those seeking him, but his strength and his anger are against all those abandoning him.” 23 So we fasted and made request of our God concerning this, and he listened to our entreaty.

24 I now set apart 12 of the chiefs of the priests, namely, She·re·bi′ah and Hash·a·bi′ah, along with ten of their brothers. 25 Then I weighed out to them the silver and the gold and the utensils, the contribution that the king and his advisers and his princes and all the Israelites who were present there had made to the house of our God. 26 Thus I weighed out into their hand 650 talents[*] of silver, 100 silver utensils worth 2 talents, 100 talents of gold, 27 20 small gold bowls worth 1,000 darics,[*] and 2 utensils of fine copper, gleaming red, as desirable as gold.

28 Then I said to them: “You are holy to Jehovah, and the utensils are holy, and the silver and the gold are a voluntary offering to Jehovah the God of your forefathers. 29 Guard them carefully until you weigh them out before the chiefs of the priests and the Levites and the princes of the paternal houses of Israel in Jerusalem, in the chambers[*] of the house of Jehovah.” 30 And the priests and the Levites took the silver and the gold and the utensils that had been weighed out to them, in order to bring them to Jerusalem to the house of our God.

31 Finally we pulled away from the river A·ha′va on the 12th day of the first month to go to Jerusalem, and the hand of our God was over us, and he rescued us from the hand of the enemy and from ambush along the way. 32 So we came to Jerusalem and stayed there for three days. 33 And on the fourth day, we weighed out the silver and the gold and the utensils in the house of our God and handed them over to Mer′e·moth son of U·ri′jah the priest, and with him was El·e·a′zar son of Phin′e·has, and with them were the Levites Jo′za·bad son of Jesh′u·a and No·a·di′ah son of Bin′nu·i. 34 Everything was numbered and weighed, and all the weight was recorded. 35 Those coming out of the captivity, the former exiles, presented burnt sacrifices to the God of Israel, 12 bulls for all Israel, 96 rams, 77 male lambs, and 12 male goats as a sin offering; all of this was a burnt offering to Jehovah.

36 Then we gave the decrees of the king to the satraps[*] of the king and the governors of the region Beyond the River,[*] and they supported the people and the house of the true God.

^ Ezra 8:17 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Ezra 8:20 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Ezra 8:26 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Ezra 8:27 A daric was a Persian gold coin. See App. B14.

^ Ezra 8:29 Or “dining halls.”

^ Ezra 8:36 Title meaning “protectors of the realm,” here applied to governors of provinces in the Persian Empire.

^ Ezra 8:36 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

Ezra  10 : 1 - 44

10 While Ez′ra was praying and making confession, weeping and lying prostrate before the house of the true God, a large crowd of men, women, and children of Israel gathered around him, for the people were weeping profusely. 2 Then Shec·a·ni′ah the son of Je·hi′el of the sons of E′lam said to Ez′ra: “We have acted unfaithfully against our God by marrying[*] foreign women from the peoples of the land. Despite this, there is still hope for Israel. 3 Now let us make a covenant with our God to send away all the wives and those born from them, in harmony with the direction of Jehovah and of those who have reverence for[*] the commandment of our God. Let us act according to the Law. 4 Get up, for this matter is your responsibility, and we are with you. Be strong and take action.”

5 At that Ez′ra rose and had the chiefs of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel take an oath to do what had been said. So they took an oath. 6 Ez′ra now got up from before the house of the true God and went to the chamber[*] of Je·ho·ha′nan the son of E·li′a·shib. Although he went there, he ate no food and drank no water, for he was in mourning because of the unfaithfulness of the exiled people.

7 Then they made a proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem that all the former exiles gather together at Jerusalem; 8 and according to the decision of the princes and the elders, anyone who did not come within three days’ time would have all his goods confiscated,[*] and he would be banished from the congregation of the exiled people. 9 So all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered together at Jerusalem within three days, that is, in the ninth month, on the 20th day of the month. All the people were sitting in a courtyard of the house of the true God, shivering because of the matter at hand and because of the heavy rain.

10 Then Ez′ra the priest rose and said to them: “You have acted unfaithfully by marrying foreign women, and so you have added to the guilt of Israel. 11 Now make confession to Jehovah the God of your forefathers and do his will. Separate yourselves from the peoples of the land and from these foreign wives.” 12 To this the whole congregation answered with a loud voice: “It is our duty to do exactly as you say. 13 However, there are many people, and it is the rainy season. It is not possible to stand outside, and the matter will not take just one or two days, for we have rebelled extensively in this matter. 14 So, please, let our princes represent the entire congregation; and let all those in our cities who have married foreign women come at an appointed time, along with the elders and judges of each city, until we turn back the burning anger of our God from us concerning this matter.”

15 However, Jon′a·than the son of As′a·hel and Jah·zei′ah the son of Tik′vah objected to this, and the Levites Me·shul′lam and Shab′be·thai supported them. 16 But the former exiles did what was agreed on; and Ez′ra the priest and the family heads of their paternal houses, all designated by name, convened separately on the first day of the tenth month to look into the matter; 17 and by the first day of the first month they finished dealing with all the men who had married foreign women. 18 And it was discovered that some of the sons of the priests had married foreign women: of the sons of Jesh′u·a the son of Je·hoz′a·dak and his brothers, Ma·a·sei′ah, E·li·e′zer, Ja′rib, and Ged·a·li′ah. 19 But they promised[*] to send their wives away, and since they were guilty, they would offer a ram of the flock for their guilt.

20 Of the sons of Im′mer, there were Ha·na′ni and Zeb·a·di′ah; 21 and of the sons of Ha′rim, Ma·a·sei′ah, E·li′jah, She·mai′ah, Je·hi′el, and Uz·zi′ah; 22 and of the sons of Pash′hur, Eli·o·e′nai, Ma·a·sei′ah, Ish′ma·el, Ne·than′el, Jo′za·bad and El·e·a′sah. 23 And of the Levites, there were Jo′za·bad, Shim′e·i, Ke·lai′ah (that is, Ke·li′ta), Peth·a·hi′ah, Judah, and E·li·e′zer; 24 and of the singers, E·li′a·shib; and of the gatekeepers, Shal′lum, Te′lem, and U′ri.

25 And of Israel, of the sons of Pa′rosh, there were Ra·mi′ah, Iz·zi′ah, Mal·chi′jah, Mij′a·min, El·e·a′zar, Mal·chi′jah, and Be·nai′ah; 26 and of the sons of E′lam, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Zech·a·ri′ah, Je·hi′el, Ab′di, Jer′e·moth, and E·li′jah; 27 and of the sons of Zat′tu, Eli·o·e′nai, E·li′a·shib, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Jer′e·moth, Za′bad, and A·zi′za; 28 and of the sons of Be′bai, Je·ho·ha′nan, Han·a·ni′ah, Zab′bai, and Ath′lai; 29 and of the sons of Ba′ni, Me·shul′lam, Mal′luch, A·dai′ah, Ja′shub, She′al, and Jer′e·moth; 30 and of the sons of Pa′hath-mo′ab, Ad′na, Che′lal, Be·nai′ah, Ma·a·sei′ah, Mat·ta·ni′ah, Bez′al·el, Bin′nu·i, and Ma·nas′seh; 31 and of the sons of Ha′rim, E·li·e′zer, Is·shi′jah, Mal·chi′jah, She·mai′ah, Shim′e·on, 32 Benjamin, Mal′luch, and Shem·a·ri′ah; 33 of the sons of Ha′shum, Mat·te′nai, Mat′tat·tah, Za′bad, E·liph′e·let, Jer′e·mai, Ma·nas′seh, and Shim′e·i; 34 of the sons of Ba′ni, Ma·a·da′i, Am′ram, U′el, 35 Be·nai′ah, Be·dei′ah, Chel′u·hi, 36 Va·ni′ah, Mer′e·moth, E·li′a·shib, 37 Mat·ta·ni′ah, Mat·te′nai, and Ja′a·su; 38 and of the sons of Bin′nu·i, Shim′e·i, 39 Shel·e·mi′ah, Nathan, A·dai′ah, 40 Mach·nad′e·bai, Sha′shai, Sha′rai, 41 Az′ar·el, Shel·e·mi′ah, Shem·a·ri′ah, 42 Shal′lum, Am·a·ri′ah, and Joseph; 43 and of the sons of Ne′bo, Je·i′el, Mat·ti·thi′ah, Za′bad, Ze·bi′na, Jad′dai, Joel, and Be·nai′ah. 44 All of these had taken foreign wives, and they sent their wives away, along with their sons.

^ Ezra 10:2 Or “by taking into our houses.”

^ Ezra 10:3 Lit., “who tremble at.”

^ Ezra 10:6 Or “dining hall.”

^ Ezra 10:8 Or “put under ban.”

^ Ezra 10:19 Lit., “they gave their hands.”

Nehemiah  10 : 1 - 39

10 Those who attested it by putting their seal to it were:

Ne·he·mi′ah the governor,[*] the son of Hac·a·li′ah,

And Zed·e·ki′ah, 2 Se·rai′ah, Az·a·ri′ah, Jeremiah, 3 Pash′hur, Am·a·ri′ah, Mal·chi′jah, 4 Hat′tush, Sheb·a·ni′ah, Mal′luch, 5 Ha′rim, Mer′e·moth, O·ba·di′ah, 6 Daniel, Gin′ne·thon, Bar′uch, 7 Me·shul′lam, A·bi′jah, Mij′a·min, 8 Ma·a·zi′ah, Bil′gai, and She·mai′ah; these are the priests.

9 Also the Levites: Jesh′u·a the son of Az·a·ni′ah, Bin′nu·i of the sons of Hen′a·dad, Kad′mi·el, 10 and their brothers Sheb·a·ni′ah, Ho·di′ah, Ke·li′ta, Pe·la′iah, Ha′nan, 11 Mi′ca, Re′hob, Hash·a·bi′ah, 12 Zac′cur, She·re·bi′ah, Sheb·a·ni′ah, 13 Ho·di′ah, Ba′ni, and Be·ni′nu.

14 The heads of the people: Pa′rosh, Pa′hath-mo′ab, E′lam, Zat′tu, Ba′ni, 15 Bun′ni, Az′gad, Be′bai, 16 Ad·o·ni′jah, Big′vai, A′din, 17 A′ter, Hez·e·ki′ah, Az′zur, 18 Ho·di′ah, Ha′shum, Be′zai, 19 Ha′riph, An′a·thoth, Ne′bai, 20 Mag′pi·ash, Me·shul′lam, He′zir, 21 Me·shez′a·bel, Za′dok, Jad′du·a, 22 Pel·a·ti′ah, Ha′nan, A·nai′ah, 23 Ho·she′a, Han·a·ni′ah, Has′shub, 24 Hal·lo′hesh, Pil′ha, Sho′bek, 25 Re′hum, Ha·shab′nah, Ma·a·sei′ah, 26 A·hi′jah, Ha′nan, A′nan, 27 Mal′luch, Ha′rim, and Ba′a·nah.

28 The rest of the people—the priests, the Levites, the gatekeepers, the singers, the temple servants,[*] and everyone who separated himself from the peoples of the lands to follow the Law of the true God, along with their wives, their sons, and their daughters, all those with knowledge and understanding[*]— 29 joined their brothers, their prominent men, and bound themselves with a curse and an oath, to walk in the Law of the true God, which had been given through Moses the servant of the true God, and to observe carefully all the commandments of Jehovah our Lord, his judgments, and his regulations. 30 We will not give our daughters to the peoples of the land, and we will not take their daughters for our sons.

31 If the peoples of the land bring in their wares and every kind of grain to sell on the Sabbath day, we will not buy anything from them on the Sabbath or on a holy day. We will also forgo the produce of the seventh year and every outstanding debt.

32 Also, we imposed the obligation on ourselves for each of us to give a third of a shekel[*] yearly for the service of the house[*] of our God, 33 for the layer bread,[*] the regular grain offering, the regular burnt offering of the Sabbaths and the new moons, and for the appointed feasts, for the holy things, for the sin offerings to make atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God.

34 Also, we cast lots concerning the supply of the wood that the priests, the Levites, and the people should bring to the house of our God by our paternal houses, at the appointed times, year by year, to burn on the altar of Jehovah our God, according to what is written in the Law. 35 We will also bring the first ripe fruits of our land and the first ripe fruits of every sort of fruit tree, year by year, to the house of Jehovah, 36 as well as the firstborn of our sons and of our livestock—according to what is written in the Law—and the firstborn of our herds and of our flocks. We will bring them to the house of our God, to the priests who minister at the house of our God. 37 Also, the firstfruits of our coarse meal, our contributions, the fruitage of every sort of tree, new wine, and oil, we should bring to the priests to the storerooms[*] of the house of our God, along with the tenth[*] from our land to the Levites, for the Levites are the ones who collect the tenths in all our agricultural cities.

38 And the priest, the son of Aaron, must be with the Levites when the Levites collect the tenth; and the Levites should offer up a tenth of the tenth to the house of our God, to the rooms[*] of the storehouse. 39 For it is to the storerooms[*] that the Israelites and the sons of the Levites should bring the contribution of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, and that is where the utensils of the sanctuary are, as well as the priests who minister, the gatekeepers, and the singers. We will not neglect the house of our God.

^ Neh. 10:1 Or “the Tirshatha,” a Persian title for a governor of a province.

^ Neh. 10:28 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Neh. 10:28 Or possibly, “all those old enough to understand.”

^ Neh. 10:32 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Neh. 10:32 Or “temple.”

^ Neh. 10:33 That is, the showbread.

^ Neh. 10:37 Or “dining halls.”

^ Neh. 10:37 Or “tithes.”

^ Neh. 10:38 Or “dining halls.”

^ Neh. 10:39 Or “dining halls.”

Nehemiah  12 : 1 - 47

12 These were the priests and the Levites who went up with Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el, and Jesh′u·a: Se·rai′ah, Jeremiah, Ez′ra, 2 Am·a·ri′ah, Mal′luch, Hat′tush, 3 Shec·a·ni′ah, Re′hum, Mer′e·moth, 4 Id′do, Gin′ne·thoi, A·bi′jah, 5 Mij′a·min, Ma·a·di′ah, Bil′gah, 6 She·mai′ah, Joi′a·rib, Je·da′iah, 7 Sal′lu, A′mok, Hil·ki′ah, and Je·da′iah. These were the heads of the priests and their brothers in the days of Jesh′u·a.

8 The Levites were Jesh′u·a, Bin′nu·i, Kad′mi·el, She·re·bi′ah, Judah, and Mat·ta·ni′ah, who led the songs of thanksgiving along with his brothers. 9 And Bak·bu·ki′ah and Un′ni their brothers stood opposite them for guard duties.[*] 10 Jesh′u·a became father to Joi′a·kim, and Joi′a·kim became father to E·li′a·shib, and E·li′a·shib to Joi′a·da. 11 And Joi′a·da became father to Jon′a·than, and Jon′a·than became father to Jad′du·a.

12 In the days of Joi′a·kim, these were the priests, the heads of the paternal houses: for Se·rai′ah, Me·rai′ah; for Jeremiah, Han·a·ni′ah; 13 for Ez′ra, Me·shul′lam; for Am·a·ri′ah, Je·ho·ha′nan; 14 for Mal′lu·chi, Jon′a·than; for Sheb·a·ni′ah, Joseph; 15 for Ha′rim, Ad′na; for Me·ra′ioth, Hel′kai; 16 for Id′do, Zech·a·ri′ah; for Gin′ne·thon, Me·shul′lam; 17 for A·bi′jah, Zich′ri; for Mi·ni′a·min, . . .  ;[*] for Mo·a·di′ah, Pil′tai; 18 for Bil′gah, Sham·mu′a; for She·mai′ah, Je·hon′a·than; 19 for Joi′a·rib, Mat·te′nai; for Je·da′iah, Uz′zi; 20 for Sal·la′i, Kal′lai; for A′mok, E′ber; 21 for Hil·ki′ah, Hash·a·bi′ah; for Je·da′iah, Ne·than′el.

22 The heads of the paternal houses of the Levites in the days of E·li′a·shib, Joi′a·da, Jo·ha′nan, and Jad′du·a were recorded, as were the priests, down to the kingship of Da·ri′us the Persian.

23 The Levites who were heads of the paternal houses were recorded in the book of the history of the times, down to the days of Jo·ha′nan the son of E·li′a·shib. 24 The heads of the Levites were Hash·a·bi′ah, She·re·bi′ah, and Jesh′u·a the son of Kad′mi·el, and their brothers stood opposite them to offer praise and give thanks according to the instructions of David the man of the true God, guard group corresponding to guard group. 25 Mat·ta·ni′ah, Bak·bu·ki′ah, O·ba·di′ah, Me·shul′lam, Tal′mon, and Ak′kub were standing guard as gatekeepers, guarding the storerooms by the gates. 26 These served in the days of Joi′a·kim the son of Jesh′u·a the son of Jo′za·dak and in the days of Ne·he·mi′ah the governor and Ez′ra the priest and copyist.[*]

27 At the inauguration of the walls of Jerusalem, they sought the Levites and brought them to Jerusalem from all the places they lived to celebrate the inauguration with rejoicing, with songs of thanksgiving, and with cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps. 28 And the sons of the singers[*] gathered together from the district,[*] from all around Jerusalem, from the settlements of the Ne·toph′a·thites, 29 from Beth-gil′gal, and from the fields of Ge′ba and Az′ma·veth, for the singers had built settlements for themselves all around Jerusalem. 30 And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and they purified the people, the gates, and the wall.

31 Then I brought the princes of Judah up on top of the wall. Further, I appointed two large thanksgiving choirs and processions, and the one walked to the right on the wall toward the Gate of the Ash Heaps. 32 Ho·shai′ah and half of the princes of Judah walked behind them, 33 along with Az·a·ri′ah, Ez′ra, Me·shul′lam, 34 Judah, Benjamin, She·mai′ah, and Jeremiah. 35 With them were some of the sons of the priests with the trumpets: Zech·a·ri′ah son of Jon′a·than son of She·mai′ah son of Mat·ta·ni′ah son of Mi·cai′ah son of Zac′cur son of A′saph, 36 and his brothers She·mai′ah, Az′ar·el, Mil′a·lai, Gil′a·lai, Ma′ai, Ne·than′el, Judah, and Ha·na′ni, with the musical instruments of David the man of the true God; and Ez′ra the copyist[*] went before them. 37 At the Fountain Gate they went straight ahead up the Stairway of the City of David by the ascent of the wall above the House of David and on to the Water Gate to the east.

38 The other thanksgiving choir walked in the opposite direction,[*] and I followed it with half of the people, on the wall up over the Tower of the Ovens and on to the Broad Wall 39 and up over the Gate of E′phra·im and on to the Gate of the Old City and on to the Fish Gate, the Tower of Ha·nan′el, the Tower of Me′ah, and on to the Sheep Gate; and they came to a halt at the Gate of the Guard.

40 At length the two thanksgiving choirs stood before the house of the true God; so did I and half of the deputy rulers with me, 41 and the priests E·li′a·kim, Ma·a·sei′ah, Mi·ni′a·min, Mi·cai′ah, Eli·o·e′nai, Zech·a·ri′ah, and Han·a·ni′ah, with the trumpets, 42 and Ma·a·sei′ah, She·mai′ah, El·e·a′zar, Uz′zi, Je·ho·ha′nan, Mal·chi′jah, E′lam, and E′zer. And the singers sang loudly under the oversight of Iz·ra·hi′ah.

43 On that day they offered great sacrifices and rejoiced, for the true God made them rejoice with great joy. The women and the children also rejoiced, so that the rejoicing of Jerusalem could be heard far away.

44 On that day men were appointed over the storehouses for the contributions, the firstfruits, and the tenths.[*] Into them they were to gather from the fields of the cities the portions required by the Law for the priests and the Levites, for there was rejoicing in Judah because of the priests and the Levites who were ministering. 45 And they began taking care of the duties of their God and the obligation of the purification, as did the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the instructions of David and his son Sol′o·mon. 46 For long ago in the days of David and A′saph, there were directors[*] for the singers and for the songs of praise and thanksgiving to God. 47 And during the days of Ze·rub′ba·bel and during the days of Ne·he·mi′ah, all Israel gave portions to the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the daily need. They also set aside the portion for the Levites, and the Levites set aside the portion for the descendants of Aaron.

^ Neh. 12:9 Or possibly, “during the service.”

^ Neh. 12:17 The Hebrew text evidently omits a name here.

^ Neh. 12:26 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 12:28 Or “And the trained singers.”

^ Neh. 12:28 That is, the district around the Jordan.

^ Neh. 12:36 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 12:38 Or “in front.”

^ Neh. 12:44 Or “tithes.”

^ Neh. 12:46 Lit., “heads.”

Ecclesiastes  4 : 1 - 16

4 Again I turned my attention to all the acts of oppression that go on under the sun. I saw the tears of the oppressed, and there was no one to comfort them. And their oppressors had the power, and there was no one to comfort them. 2 And I congratulated the dead who had already died rather than the living who were still alive. 3 And better off than both of them is the one who has not yet been born, who has not seen the distressing deeds that are done under the sun.

4 And I have seen how much effort[*] and skillful work spring from rivalry between people; this too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

5 The stupid one folds his hands while his flesh wastes away.[*]

6 Better is a handful of rest than two handfuls of hard work and chasing after the wind.

7 I turned my attention to another example of futility under the sun: 8 There is a man who is all alone, without any companion; he has no son or brother, but there is no end to all his hard work. His eyes are never satisfied with riches. But does he ask himself, ‘For whom am I working hard and depriving myself[*] of good things’? This too is futility and a miserable occupation.

9 Two are better than one because they have a good reward[*] for their hard work. 10 For if one of them falls, the other can help his partner up. But what will happen to the one who falls with no one to help him up?

11 Moreover, if two lie down together, they will stay warm, but how can just one keep warm? 12 And someone may overpower one alone, but two together can take a stand against him. And a threefold cord cannot quickly[*] be torn apart.

13 Better is a poor but wise child than an old but stupid king, who no longer has enough sense to heed a warning. 14 For he[*] went out from prison to become king, although in that one’s kingship he was born poor. 15 I considered all those alive who walk about under the sun, as well as how it goes with the young successor who stands up in the other’s place. 16 Although there is no end to all his supporters, those who come later will not be happy with him. This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

^ Eccl. 4:4 Or “hard work.”

^ Eccl. 4:5 Lit., “and is eating his own flesh.”

^ Eccl. 4:8 Or “my soul.”

^ Eccl. 4:9 Or “greater benefit.”

^ Eccl. 4:12 Or “easily.”

^ Eccl. 4:14 Perhaps referring to the wise child.

Isaiah  9 : 1 - 21

9 However, the gloom will not be as when the land had distress, as in former times when the land of Zeb′u·lun and the land of Naph′ta·li were treated with contempt. But at a later time He will cause it to be honored—the way by the sea, in the region of the Jordan, Gal′i·lee of the nations.

 2 The people who were walking in the darkness

Have seen a great light.

As for those dwelling in the land of deep shadow,

Light has shone on them.

 3 You have made the nation populous;

You have made its rejoicing great.

They rejoice before you

As people rejoice in the harvesttime,

As those who joyfully divide up the spoil.

 4 For you have shattered to pieces the yoke of their load,

The rod on their shoulders, the staff of the taskmaster,

As in the day of Mid′i·an.

 5 Every boot that shakes the earth as it marches

And every garment soaked in blood

Will become fuel for the fire.

 6 For a child has been born to us,

A son has been given to us;

And the rulership[*] will rest on his shoulder.

His name will be called Wonderful Counselor, Mighty God, Eternal Father, Prince of Peace.

 7 To the increase of his rulership[*]

And to peace, there will be no end,

On the throne of David and on his kingdom

In order to establish it firmly and to sustain it

Through justice and righteousness,

From now on and forever.

The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

 8 Jehovah sent a word against Jacob,

And it has come against Israel.

 9 And all the people will know it

—E′phra·im and the inhabitants of Sa·mar′i·a—

Who say in their haughtiness and in their insolence of heart:

10 “Bricks have fallen,

But we will build with hewn stone.

Sycamore trees have been cut down,

But we will replace them with cedars.”

11 Jehovah will raise up Re′zin’s adversaries against him

And will stir his enemies to action,

12 Syria from the east and the Phi·lis′tines from the west,[*]

They will devour Israel with open mouths.

In view of all this, his anger has not turned back,

But his hand is still stretched out to strike.

13 For the people have not returned to the One who strikes them;

They have not sought Jehovah of armies.

14 Jehovah will cut off from Israel

Head and tail, shoot and rush,[*] in one day.

15 The elder and highly respected one is the head,

And the prophet giving false instruction is the tail.

16 Those leading this people are causing them to wander,

And those who are being led are confused.

17 That is why Jehovah will not rejoice over their young men,

And he will have no mercy on their fatherless children[*] and their widows

Because all of them are apostates and evildoers

And every mouth is speaking senselessness.

In view of all this, his anger has not turned back,

But his hand is still stretched out to strike.

18 For wickedness burns like a fire,

Consuming thornbushes and weeds.

It will set fire to the thickets of the forest,

And they will go up in clouds of smoke.

19 In the fury of Jehovah of armies

The land has been set on fire,

And the people will become fuel for the fire.

No one will spare even his brother.

20 One will cut down on the right

But still be hungry;

And one will eat on the left

But will not be satisfied.

Each will devour the flesh of his own arm,

21 Ma·nas′seh will devour E′phra·im,

And E′phra·im Ma·nas′seh.

Together they will be against Judah.

In view of all this, his anger has not turned back,

But his hand is still stretched out to strike.

^ Isa. 9:6 Or “government; princely rule.”

^ Isa. 9:7 Or “government; princely rule.”

^ Isa. 9:12 Lit., “from behind.”

^ Isa. 9:14 Or possibly, “palm branch and reed.”

^ Isa. 9:17 Or “their orphans.”

Isaiah  16 : 1 - 14

16 Send a ram to the ruler of the land,

From Se′la through the wilderness

To the mountain of the daughter of Zion.

 2 Like a bird chased away from its nest,

So the daughters of Mo′ab will be at the fords of Ar′non.

 3 “Offer counsel, carry out the decision.

Make your shadow at high noon like the night.

Conceal the dispersed and do not betray those fleeing.

 4 May my dispersed ones reside in you, O Mo′ab.

Become a place of concealment to them because of the destroyer.

The oppressor will reach his end,

The destruction will come to an end,

And those trampling others down will perish from the earth.

 5 Then a throne will be firmly established in loyal love.

The one who sits on it in the tent of David will be faithful;

He will judge fairly and will swiftly execute righteousness.”

 6 We have heard about the pride of Mo′ab—he is very proud—

His haughtiness and his pride and his fury;

But his empty talk will come to nothing.

 7 So Mo′ab will wail for Mo′ab;

They will all wail.

Those who are stricken will moan for the raisin cakes of Kir-har′e·seth.

 8 For the terraces of Hesh′bon have withered,

The vine of Sib′mah,

The rulers of the nations have trampled its bright-red branches;[*]

They had reached as far as Ja′zer;

They had extended into the wilderness.

Its shoots had spread out and gone as far as the sea.

 9 That is why I will weep over the vine of Sib′mah as I weep for Ja′zer.

With my tears I will drench you, O Hesh′bon and E·le·a′leh,

Because the shouting over your summer fruit and your harvest has ended.[*]

10 Rejoicing and joyfulness have been taken away from the orchard,

And there are no songs of joy or shouting in the vineyards.

The treader no longer treads out wine in the presses,

For I have caused the shouting to cease.

11 That is why deep within me I am boisterous over Mo′ab,

Like the strumming of a harp,

And my innermost being over Kir-har′e·seth.

12 Even when Mo′ab wears himself out on the high place and goes to pray in his sanctuary, he will accomplish nothing.

13 This is the word that Jehovah previously spoke concerning Mo′ab. 14 And now Jehovah says: “Within three years, like the years of a hired worker,[*] the glory of Mo′ab will be disgraced with much tumult of every sort, and those who remain will be very few and insignificant.”

^ Isa. 16:8 Or “its branches laden with red grapes.”

^ Isa. 16:9 Or possibly, “Because the battle cry has descended on your summer fruit and your harvest.”

^ Isa. 16:14 Or “counted as carefully as a hired worker does”; that is, in exactly three years.

Isaiah  36 : 1 - 22

36 In the 14th year of King Hez·e·ki′ah, Sen·nach′er·ib the king of As·syr′i·a came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and captured them. 2 The king of As·syr′i·a then sent the Rab′sha·keh[*] with a vast army from La′chish to King Hez·e·ki′ah in Jerusalem. They took up a position by the conduit of the upper pool, which is at the highway of the laundryman’s field. 3 Then E·li′a·kim son of Hil·ki′ah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Sheb′na the secretary, and Jo′ah son of A′saph the recorder came out to him.

4 So the Rab′sha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·ki′ah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a, says: “What is the basis for your confidence? 5 You are saying, ‘I have a strategy and the power to wage war,’ but these are empty words. In whom have you put trust, so that you dare to rebel against me? 6 Look! You trust in the support of this crushed reed, Egypt, which if a man should lean on it would enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Phar′aoh king of Egypt is to all those who trust in him. 7 And if you should say to me, ‘We trust in Jehovah our God,’ is he not the one whose high places and altars Hez·e·ki′ah has removed, while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You should bow down before this altar’?”’ 8 So now make this wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syr′i·a: I will give you 2,000 horses if you are able to find enough riders for them. 9 How, then, could you drive back even one governor who is the least of my lord’s servants, while you put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 10 Now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this land to destroy it? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land and destroy it.’”

11 At this E·li′a·kim and Sheb′na and Jo′ah said to the Rab′sha·keh: “Speak to your servants, please, in the Ar·a·ma′ic[*] language, for we can understand it; do not speak to us in the language of the Jews in the hearing of the people on the wall.” 12 But the Rab′sha·keh said: “Is it just to your lord and to you that my lord sent me to speak these words? Is it not also to the men who sit on the wall, those who will eat their own excrement and drink their own urine along with you?”

13 Then the Rab′sha·keh stood and called out loudly in the language of the Jews, saying: “Hear the word of the great king, the king of As·syr′i·a. 14 This is what the king says, ‘Do not let Hez·e·ki′ah deceive you, for he is not able to rescue you. 15 And do not let Hez·e·ki′ah cause you to trust in Jehovah by saying: “Jehovah will surely rescue us, and this city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 16 Do not listen to Hez·e·ki′ah, for this is what the king of As·syr′i·a says: “Make peace with me and surrender,[*] and each of you will eat from his own vine and from his own fig tree and will drink the water of his own cistern, 17 until I come and take you to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards. 18 Do not let Hez·e·ki′ah mislead you by saying, ‘Jehovah will rescue us.’ Have any of the gods of the nations rescued their land out of the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a? 19 Where are the gods of Ha′math and Ar′pad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·va′im? And have they rescued Sa·mar′i·a out of my hand? 20 Who among all the gods of these lands have rescued their land out of my hand, so that Jehovah should rescue Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”

21 But they kept silent and did not say a word to him in reply, for the order of the king was, “You must not answer him.” 22 But E·li′a·kim son of Hil·ki′ah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Sheb′na the secretary, and Jo′ah son of A′saph the recorder came to Hez·e·ki′ah with their garments ripped apart and told him the words of the Rab′sha·keh.

^ Isa. 36:2 Or “the chief cupbearer.”

^ Isa. 36:3 Or “palace.”

^ Isa. 36:11 Or “Syrian.”

^ Isa. 36:16 Lit., “Make with me a blessing and come out to me.”

^ Isa. 36:22 Or “palace.”

Isaiah  37 : 1 - 38

37 As soon as King Hez·e·ki′ah heard this, he ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and went into the house of Jehovah. 2 Then he sent E·li′a·kim, who was in charge of the household,[*] Sheb′na the secretary, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah, the son of A′moz. 3 They said to him: “This is what Hez·e·ki′ah says, ‘This day is a day of distress, of rebuke,[*] and of disgrace; for the children are ready to be born,[*] but there is no strength to give birth. 4 Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear the words of the Rab′sha·keh, whom the king of As·syr′i·a his lord sent to taunt the living God, and he will call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. So offer up a prayer in behalf of the remnant who have survived.’”

5 So the servants of King Hez·e·ki′ah went in to Isaiah, 6 and Isaiah said to them: “This is what you should say to your lord, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Do not be afraid because of the words that you heard, the words with which the attendants of the king of As·syr′i·a blasphemed me. 7 Here I am putting a thought in his mind,[*] and he will hear a report and return to his own land; and I will make him fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

8 After the Rab′sha·keh heard that the king of As·syr′i·a had pulled away from La′chish, he returned to him and found him fighting against Lib′nah. 9 Now the king heard it said about King Tir·ha′kah of E·thi·o′pi·a: “He has come out to fight against you.” When he heard this, he sent messengers again to Hez·e·ki′ah, saying: 10 “This is what you should say to King Hez·e·ki′ah of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you trust deceive you by saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syr′i·a.” 11 Look! You have heard what the kings of As·syr′i·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction. Will you alone be rescued? 12 Did the gods of the nations that my forefathers destroyed rescue them? Where are Go′zan, Ha′ran, Re′zeph, and the people of E′den who were in Tel-as′sar? 13 Where is the king of Ha′math, the king of Ar′pad, and the king of the cities of Seph·ar·va′im, and of He′na, and of Iv′vah?’”

14 Hez·e·ki′ah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them. Hez·e·ki′ah then went up to the house of Jehovah and spread them[*] out before Jehovah. 15 And Hez·e·ki′ah began to pray to Jehovah and say: 16 “O Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, sitting enthroned above[*] the cherubs, you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You made the heavens and the earth. 17 Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear! Open your eyes, O Jehovah, and see! Hear all the words that Sen·nach′er·ib has sent to taunt the living God. 18 It is a fact, O Jehovah, that the kings of As·syr′i·a have devastated all the lands, as well as their own land. 19 And they have thrown their gods into the fire, because they were not gods but the work of human hands, wood and stone. That is why they could destroy them. 20 But now, O Jehovah our God, save us out of his hand, so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone are God, O Jehovah.”

21 Isaiah son of A′moz then sent this message to Hez·e·ki′ah: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Because you prayed to me concerning King Sen·nach′er·ib of As·syr′i·a, 22 this is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:

“The virgin daughter of Zion despises you, she scoffs at you.

The daughter of Jerusalem shakes her head at you.

23 Whom have you taunted and blasphemed?

Against whom have you raised your voice

And lifted your arrogant eyes?

It is against the Holy One of Israel!

24 Through your servants you have taunted Jehovah and said,

‘With the multitude of my war chariots

I will ascend the heights of mountains,

The remotest parts of Leb′a·non.

I will cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.

I will enter its highest retreats, its densest forests.

25 I will dig wells and drink waters;

I will dry up the streams[*] of Egypt with the soles of my feet.’

26 Have you not heard? From long ago it was determined.[*]

From days gone by I have prepared[*] it.

Now I will bring it about.

You will turn fortified cities into desolate piles of ruins.

27 Their inhabitants will be helpless;

They will be terrified and put to shame.

They will become as vegetation of the field and green grass,

As grass of the roofs that is scorched by the east wind.

28 But I well know when you sit, when you go out, when you come in,

And when you are enraged against me,

29 Because your rage against me and your roaring have reached my ears.

So I will put my hook in your nose and my bridle between your lips,

And I will lead you back the way you came.”

30 “‘And this will be the sign for you:[*] This year you will eat what grows on its own;[*] and in the second year, you will eat grain that sprouts from that; but in the third year you will sow seed and reap, and you will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 31 Those of the house of Judah who escape, those who are left, will take root downward and produce fruit upward. 32 For a remnant will go out of Jerusalem and survivors from Mount Zion. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

33 “‘Therefore this is what Jehovah says about the king of As·syr′i·a:

“He will not come into this city

Or shoot an arrow there

Or confront it with a shield

Or cast up a siege rampart against it.”’

34 ‘By the way he came he will return;

He will not come into this city,’ declares Jehovah.

35 ‘I will defend this city and save it for my own sake

And for the sake of my servant David.’”

36 And the angel of Jehovah went out and struck down 185,000 men in the camp of the As·syr′i·ans. When people rose up early in the morning, they saw all the dead bodies. 37 So King Sen·nach′er·ib of As·syr′i·a departed and returned to Nin′e·veh and stayed there. 38 And as he was bowing down at the house[*] of his god Nis′roch, his own sons A·dram′me·lech and Shar·e′zer struck him down with the sword and then escaped to the land of Ar′a·rat. And his son E′sar-had′don became king in his place.

^ Isa. 37:2 Or “palace.”

^ Isa. 37:3 Or “insult.”

^ Isa. 37:3 Lit., “have come to the opening of the womb.”

^ Isa. 37:7 Lit., “a spirit in him.”

^ Isa. 37:14 Lit., “it.”

^ Isa. 37:16 Or possibly, “between.”

^ Isa. 37:25 Or “the Nile canals.”

^ Isa. 37:26 Lit., “done.”

^ Isa. 37:26 Or “formed.”

^ Isa. 37:30 That is, Hezekiah.

^ Isa. 37:30 Or “the growth from spilled kernels of grain.”

^ Isa. 37:38 Or “temple.”

Isaiah  62 : 1 - 12

62 For the sake of Zion I will not keep silent,

And for the sake of Jerusalem I will not keep still

Until her righteousness shines like a bright light

And her salvation burns like a torch.

 2 “The nations will see your righteousness, O woman,

And all kings your glory.

And you will be called by a new name,

Which Jehovah’s own mouth will designate.

 3 You will become a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah,

A royal turban in the palm of your God.

 4 No more will you be called an abandoned woman,

And your land will no longer be called desolate.

But you will be called My Delight Is in Her,

And your land will be called the Married One.

For Jehovah will take delight in you,

And your land will be as one married.

 5 For just as a young man marries a virgin,

Your sons will marry you.

With the rejoicing of a bridegroom over a bride,

Your God will rejoice over you.

 6 Upon your walls, O Jerusalem, I have commissioned watchmen.

Continuously, all day long and all night long, they should not be silent.

You who make mention of Jehovah,

Do not rest,

 7 And do not give him any rest until he firmly establishes Jerusalem,

Yes, until he makes her the praise of the earth.”

 8 Jehovah has sworn an oath with his right hand, with his strong arm:

“I will no longer give your grain as food to your enemies,

Nor will foreigners drink your new wine, for which you have toiled.

 9 But those gathering it will eat it and they will praise Jehovah;

And those collecting it will drink it in my holy courtyards.”

10 Pass through, pass through the gates.

Clear the way for the people.

Build up, build up the highway.

Rid it of stones.

Raise up a signal[*] for the peoples.

11 Look! Jehovah has proclaimed to the ends of the earth:

“Say to the daughter of Zion,

‘Look! Your salvation is coming.

Look! His reward is with him,

And the wage he pays is before him.’”

12 They will be called the holy people, those repurchased by Jehovah,

And you will be called Sought After, a City Not Abandoned.

^ Isa. 62:10 Or “signal pole.”

Jeremiah  3 : 1 - 25

3 People ask: “If a man sends his wife away and she leaves him and becomes another man’s, should he return to her anymore?”

Has that land not been utterly polluted?

“You have committed prostitution with many companions,

And should you now return to me?” declares Jehovah.

 2 “Raise your eyes to the bare hills and see.

Where have you not been raped?

You sat along the roadways for them,

Like a nomad[*] in the wilderness.

You keep polluting the land

With your prostitution and your wickedness.

 3 So showers of rain are withheld,

And there is no rain in the spring.

You have the brazen look[*] of a wife who commits prostitution;

You refuse to feel shame.

 4 But now you call out to me,

‘My Father, you are the companion of my youth!

 5 Should one stay resentful forever,

Or always hold a grudge?’

This is what you say,

But you keep doing all the evil you are capable of doing.”

6 In the days of King Jo·si′ah, Jehovah said to me: “‘Have you seen what unfaithful Israel has done? She has gone up on every high mountain and underneath every luxuriant tree to commit prostitution. 7 Even after she did all these things, I kept telling her to return to me, but she did not return; and Judah kept watching her treacherous sister. 8 When I saw that, I sent unfaithful Israel away with a full certificate of divorce because of her adultery. But her treacherous sister Judah did not become afraid; she too went out and committed prostitution. 9 She took her prostitution lightly, and she kept polluting the land and committing adultery with stones and with trees. 10 Despite all this, her treacherous sister Judah did not return to me with all her heart, only in pretense,’ declares Jehovah.”

11 Jehovah then said to me: “Unfaithful Israel has shown herself[*] to be more righteous than treacherous Judah. 12 Go and proclaim these words to the north:

“‘“Return, O renegade Israel,” declares Jehovah.’ ‘“I will not look down angrily[*] on you, for I am loyal,” declares Jehovah.’ ‘“I will not stay resentful forever. 13 Only acknowledge your guilt, for you have rebelled against Jehovah your God. You continued scattering your favors[*] to strangers[*] under every luxuriant tree, but you would not obey my voice,” declares Jehovah.’”

14 “Return, you renegade sons,” declares Jehovah. “For I have become your true master;[*] and I will take you, one from a city and two from a family, and I will bring you to Zion. 15 And I will give you shepherds after my own heart, and they will feed you with knowledge and insight. 16 You will become many and will bear fruit in the land in those days,” declares Jehovah. “No more will they say, ‘The ark of the covenant of Jehovah!’ It will not come up into the heart, nor will they remember it or miss it, and it will not be made again. 17 At that time they will call Jerusalem the throne of Jehovah; and all the nations will be brought together to the name of Jehovah at Jerusalem, and they will no longer stubbornly follow their own wicked heart.”

18 “In those days they will walk together, the house of Judah alongside the house of Israel, and together they will come from the land of the north into the land that I gave to your forefathers as an inheritance. 19 And I thought, ‘How I placed you among the sons and gave you the desirable land, the most beautiful inheritance among the nations!’[*] I also thought that you would call me, ‘My Father!’ and that you would not turn away from following me. 20 ‘Truly as a wife treacherously leaves her husband,[*] so also you, O house of Israel, have dealt treacherously with me,’ declares Jehovah.”

21 On the bare hills a sound is heard,

The weeping and the pleading of the people of Israel,

For they have distorted their way;

They have forgotten Jehovah their God.

22 “Return, you renegade sons.

I will heal your renegade condition.”

“Here we are! We have come to you,

For you, O Jehovah, are our God.

23 Truly the hills and the turmoil on the mountains are a delusion.

Truly in Jehovah our God is the salvation of Israel.

24 But the shameful thing[*] has consumed the toil of our forefathers since our youth,

Their flocks and their herds,

Their sons and their daughters.

25 Let us lie down in our shame,

And let our disgrace cover us,

For we have sinned against Jehovah our God,

We and our fathers since our youth until this day,

And we have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah our God.”

^ Jer. 3:2 Lit., “an Arabian.”

^ Jer. 3:3 Lit., “the forehead.”

^ Jer. 3:11 Or “her soul.”

^ Jer. 3:12 Lit., “make my face fall.”

^ Jer. 3:13 Lit., “ways.”

^ Jer. 3:13 Or “foreign gods.”

^ Jer. 3:14 Or possibly, “your husband.”

^ Jer. 3:19 Lit., “of the armies of the nations.”

^ Jer. 3:20 Lit., “companion.”

^ Jer. 3:24 Or “the shameful god.”

Jeremiah  5 : 1 - 31

5 Roam the streets of Jerusalem.

Look around and take note.

Search her public squares to see

Whether you can find a man who acts with justice,

One who seeks to be faithful,

And I will forgive her.

 2 Even if they say: “As surely as Jehovah is alive!”

They would still swear to what is false.

 3 O Jehovah, do your eyes not look for faithfulness?

You struck them, but it made no impact on them.[*]

You exterminated them, but they refused to accept discipline.

They made their faces harder than a rock,

And they refused to turn around.

 4 But I said to myself: “Surely these must be the lowly.

They act foolishly, for they do not know the way of Jehovah,

The judgment of their God.

 5 I will go to the prominent men and speak with them,

For they must have taken note of the way of Jehovah,

The judgment of their God.

But they had all broken the yoke

And torn apart the restraints.”[*]

 6 That is why a lion of the forest attacks them,

A wolf of the desert plains keeps ravaging them,

A leopard lies awake at their cities.

Everyone going out from them is torn to pieces.

For their transgressions are many;

Their acts of unfaithfulness are numerous.

 7 How can I forgive you for this?

Your sons have abandoned me,

And they swear by what is no God.

I satisfied their needs,

But they kept committing adultery,

And they flocked to the house of a prostitute.

 8 They are like eager, lustful horses,

Each neighing after another man’s wife.

 9 “Should I not call them to account for these things?” declares Jehovah.

“Should I[*] not avenge myself on such a nation?”

10 “Come up against her vineyard terraces and bring ruin,

But do not make a complete extermination.

Take away her spreading shoots,

For they do not belong to Jehovah.

11 For the house of Israel and the house of Judah

Have been utterly treacherous with me,” declares Jehovah.

12 “They have denied Jehovah, and they keep saying,

‘He will do nothing.[*]

No calamity will come upon us;

We will not see sword or famine.’

13 The prophets are full of wind,

And the word[*] is not in them.

Let this happen to them!”

14 Therefore this is what Jehovah, the God of armies, says:

“Because these men are saying this,

Here I am making my words a fire in your mouth,

And this people is the wood,

And it will consume them.”

15 “Here I am bringing in on you a nation from far away, O house of Israel,” declares Jehovah.

“It is an enduring nation.

It is an ancient nation,

A nation whose language you do not know,

And whose speech you cannot understand.

16 Their quiver is like an open grave;

All of them are warriors.

17 They will devour your harvest and your bread.

They will devour your sons and your daughters.

They will devour your flocks and your herds.

They will devour your vines and your fig trees.

They will destroy with the sword your fortified cities in which you trust.”

18 “But even in those days,” declares Jehovah, “I will not carry out a complete extermination of you. 19 And when they ask, ‘Why has Jehovah our God done all these things to us?’ you should answer them, ‘Just as you abandoned me to serve a foreign god in your land, so you will serve foreigners in a land that is not yours.’”

20 Declare this in the house of Jacob,

And proclaim it in Judah, saying:

21 “Hear this, you foolish and senseless people:[*]

They have eyes but cannot see;

They have ears but cannot hear.

22 ‘Do you not fear me?’ declares Jehovah,

‘Should you not tremble before me?

It is I who placed the sand as the boundary for the sea,

A permanent regulation that it cannot pass over.

Although its waves toss, they cannot prevail;

Although they roar, they still cannot pass beyond it.

23 But this people has a stubborn and rebellious heart;

They have turned aside and gone their own way.

24 And they do not say in their heart:

“Let us now fear Jehovah our God,

The One who gives the rain in its season,

Both the autumn rain and the spring rain,

The One who guards for us the appointed weeks of the harvest.”

25 Your own errors have prevented these things from coming;

Your own sins have deprived you of what is good.

26 For among my people there are wicked men.

They keep peering, as when birdcatchers crouch down.

They set a deadly trap.

It is men whom they catch.

27 Like a cage full of birds,

So their houses are full of deception.

That is why they have become powerful and rich.

28 They have grown fat and smooth;

They overflow with evil.

They do not plead the legal case of the fatherless,

That they may gain success;

And they deny justice to the poor.’”

29 “Should I not call them to account for these things?” declares Jehovah.

“Should I[*] not avenge myself on such a nation?

30 Something appalling and horrible has occurred in the land:

31 The prophets prophesy lies,

And the priests dominate by their own authority.

And my own people love it that way.

But what will you do when the end comes?”

^ Jer. 5:3 Lit., “they did not become weak.”

^ Jer. 5:5 Lit., “bands.”

^ Jer. 5:9 Or “my soul.”

^ Jer. 5:12 Or possibly, “He does not exist.”

^ Jer. 5:13 That is, God’s word.

^ Jer. 5:21 Lit., “you foolish people without heart.”

^ Jer. 5:29 Or “my soul.”

Jeremiah  9 : 1 - 26

9 O that my head were waters,

My eyes a fountain of tears!

Then I would weep day and night

For the slain ones of my people.

 2 O that I had a traveler’s lodging place in the wilderness!

Then I would leave my people and go away from them,

For they are all adulterers,

A band of treacherous people.

 3 They bend their tongue like a bow;

Falsehood, not faithfulness, prevails in the land.

“They advance from evil to evil,

And they pay no attention to me,” declares Jehovah.

 4 “Everyone, be on guard against your neighbor,

And do not trust even your brother.

For every brother is a betrayer,

And every neighbor is a slanderer.

 5 Each one cheats his neighbor,

And no one speaks truth.

They have taught their tongue to speak falsehood.

They wear themselves out doing what is wrong.

 6 You are living in the midst of deception.

In their deception they refused to know me,” declares Jehovah.

 7 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies says:

“I will smelt them and test them,

For what else can I do with the daughter of my people?

 8 Their tongue is a deadly arrow that speaks deception.

With his mouth a person speaks of peace to his neighbor,

But inside he lays an ambush.”

 9 “Should I not call them to account for these things?” declares Jehovah.

“Should I[*] not avenge myself on such a nation?

10 I will weep and lament over the mountains

And take up a dirge[*] over the pastures of the wilderness,

For they have been burned up so that no man passes through,

And the sound of livestock is not heard.

The birds of heaven and the beasts have fled; they are gone.

11 I will make Jerusalem piles of stones, the lair of jackals,

And I will make the cities of Judah desolate, without an inhabitant.

12 Who is wise enough to understand this?

To whom has the mouth of Jehovah spoken, that he may declare it?

Why has the land perished?

Why is it scorched like the wilderness,

So that no one is passing through?”

13 Jehovah replied: “Because of their rejecting my law[*] that I set before them, and because they have not followed it and obeyed my voice. 14 Instead, they stubbornly followed their own hearts, and they followed the Ba′al images, as their fathers had taught them to do. 15 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Here I am making this people eat wormwood, and I will make them drink poisoned water. 16 I will scatter them among the nations that they and their fathers have not known, and I will send a sword after them until I will have exterminated them.’

17 This is what Jehovah of armies says,

‘Behave with understanding.

Summon the women who sing dirges,[*]

And send for the skilled women to come,

18 So that they may hurry and raise a lamentation for us,

So that our eyes may stream with tears

And our eyelids trickle with water.

19 For the sound of lamentation has been heard from Zion:

“How we have been devastated!

How great our shame is!

For we have left the land, and they have thrown down our homes.”

20 You women, hear the word of Jehovah.

May your ear receive the word of his mouth.

Teach your daughters this lamentation,

And teach one another this dirge.[*]

21 For death has come up through our windows;

It has entered our fortified towers

To take away the children from the streets

And the young men from the public squares.’

22 Say, ‘This is what Jehovah declares:

“The dead bodies of people will fall like manure on the surface of the field,

Like a row of newly cut grain after the reaper,

With no one to gather them up.”’”

23 This is what Jehovah says:

“Let not the wise man boast about his wisdom;

Let not the mighty man boast about his mightiness;

And let not the rich man boast about his riches.”

24 “But let the one boasting boast about this:

That he has insight and knowledge of me,

That I am Jehovah, the One showing loyal love, justice, and righteousness in the earth,

For in these things I take delight,” declares Jehovah.

25 “Look! Days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “and I will hold an accounting with everyone circumcised and yet uncircumcised, 26 with Egypt and Judah and E′dom and the Am′mon·ites and Mo′ab and with all of those with hair clipped at the temples who are dwelling in the wilderness; for all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.”

^ Jer. 9:9 Or “my soul.”

^ Jer. 9:10 Or “song of mourning.”

^ Jer. 9:13 Or “instruction.”

^ Jer. 9:17 Or “songs of mourning.”

^ Jer. 9:20 Or “song of mourning.”

Jeremiah  21 : 1 - 14

21 Jeremiah received the word from Jehovah when King Zed·e·ki′ah sent to him Pash′hur son of Mal·chi′jah and Zeph·a·ni′ah son of Ma·a·sei′ah, the priest, requesting: 2 “Please inquire of Jehovah in our behalf, because King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon is waging war against us. Perhaps Jehovah will perform one of his wonderful works in our behalf, so that he will withdraw from us.”

3 Jeremiah said to them: “This is what you should say to Zed·e·ki′ah, 4 ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “Here I am turning around against you[*] the weapons of war that are in your own hands, with which you are fighting the king of Babylon and the Chal·de′ans who are outside the wall besieging you. And I will gather them into the middle of this city. 5 And I myself will fight against you with an outstretched hand and a mighty arm, with anger and wrath and great indignation. 6 I will strike the inhabitants of this city, both man and beast. By a great pestilence[*] they will die.”’

7 “‘“And after that,” declares Jehovah, “I will give King Zed·e·ki′ah of Judah and his servants and the people of this city—those who survive the pestilence, the sword, and the famine—into the hand of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon, into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those who are seeking to take their life.[*] He will strike them down with the sword. He will not feel sorry for them, nor will he show compassion or have any mercy.”’

8 “And to this people you should say, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Here I am putting before you the way of life and the way of death. 9 Those who remain in this city will die by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence. But whoever goes out and surrenders to the Chal·de′ans who are besieging you will keep living, and he will have his life[*] as a spoil.”’[*]

10 “‘“For I have set my face against this city for calamity and not for good,” declares Jehovah. “It will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will burn it with fire.”

11 “‘To the household of the king of Judah: Hear the word of Jehovah. 12 O house of David, this is what Jehovah says:

“Uphold justice every morning,

And rescue the one being robbed from the hand of the defrauder,

So that my wrath does not blaze like a fire

And burn with no one to extinguish it

Because of your evil deeds.”’

13 ‘Here I am against you, O inhabitant of the valley,[*]

O rock of the level land,’ declares Jehovah.

‘As for you who say: “Who will come down against us?

And who will invade our dwellings?”

14 I will hold an accounting against you

As your deeds deserve,’ declares Jehovah.

‘And I will set her forest ablaze,

And it will consume all the things around her.’”

^ Jer. 21:2 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 21:4 Or “turning in reverse.”

^ Jer. 21:6 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 21:7 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 21:7 Or “seeking their soul.”

^ Jer. 21:9 Or “soul.”

^ Jer. 21:9 Or “will escape with his life.”

^ Jer. 21:13 Or “low plain.”

Jeremiah  23 : 1 - 40

23 “Woe to the shepherds who are destroying and scattering the sheep of my pasture!” declares Jehovah.

2 Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says against the shepherds who are shepherding my people: “You have scattered my sheep; you kept dispersing them, and you have not turned your attention to them.”

“So I will turn my attention to you because of your evil deeds,” declares Jehovah.

3 “Then I will gather together the remnant of my sheep from all the lands to which I have dispersed them, and I will bring them back to their pasture, and they will be fruitful and become many. 4 And I will raise up over them shepherds who will really shepherd them. They will no longer be afraid or be terrified, and none will be missing,” declares Jehovah.

5 “Look! The days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when I will raise up to David a righteous sprout.[*] And a king will reign and show insight and uphold justice and righteousness in the land. 6 In his days Judah will be saved, and Israel will reside in security. And this is the name by which he will be called: Jehovah Is Our Righteousness.”

7 “However, the days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when they will no longer say, ‘As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought the people of Israel out of the land of Egypt!’ 8 but rather, ‘As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought out and brought back the descendants of the house of Israel from the land of the north and from all the lands to which I had dispersed them,’ and they will dwell in their own land.”

9 Concerning the prophets:

My heart is broken within me.

All my bones are shaking.

I am like a man who is drunk

And like a man overcome by wine,

Because of Jehovah and because of his holy words.

10 For the land is full of adulterers;

Because of the curse the land has gone into mourning

And the pastures of the wilderness have dried up.

Their course is evil, and they abuse their power.

11 “Both the prophet and the priest are polluted.[*]

Even in my own house I have found their wickedness,” declares Jehovah.

12 “So their path will become slippery and dark;

They will be pushed and will fall.

For I will bring calamity on them

In the year of reckoning,” declares Jehovah.

13 “And in the prophets of Sa·mar′i·a I have seen what is repulsive.

Their prophecies are incited by Ba′al,

And they lead my people Israel astray.

14 And in the prophets of Jerusalem I have seen horrible things.

They commit adultery and walk in falsehood;

They encourage[*] evildoers,

And they do not turn away from their wickedness.

To me they are all like Sod′om,

And her inhabitants are like Go·mor′rah.”

15 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies says against the prophets:

“Here I am making them eat wormwood

And giving them poisoned water to drink.

For from the prophets of Jerusalem apostasy has spread throughout the land.”

16 This is what Jehovah of armies says:

“Do not listen to the words of the prophets who are prophesying to you.

They are deluding you.[*]

The vision they speak is from their own heart,

Not from the mouth of Jehovah.

17 They are saying again and again to those who disrespect me,

‘Jehovah has said: “You will enjoy peace.”’

And to everyone who follows his own stubborn heart they say,

‘No calamity will come upon you.’

18 For who has stood in the inner circle of Jehovah

To see and hear his word?

Who has paid attention to his word in order to hear it?

19 Look! The windstorm of Jehovah will burst out in fury;

Like a whirling tempest it will whirl down on the head of the wicked.

20 The anger of Jehovah will not turn back

Until he has carried out and accomplished the intentions of his heart.

In the final part of the days you will clearly understand this.

21 I did not send the prophets, yet they ran.

I did not speak to them, yet they prophesied.

22 But if they had stood in my inner circle,

They would have made my people hear my words

And would have caused them to turn back from their bad way and their evil deeds.”

23 “Am I only a God nearby,” declares Jehovah, “and not a God also from far away?”

24 “Can any man hide in a concealed place where I cannot see him?” declares Jehovah.

“Do I not fill the heavens and the earth?” declares Jehovah.

25 “I have heard the prophets who are prophesying lies in my name say, ‘I had a dream! I had a dream!’ 26 How long will this continue in the heart of the prophets, to prophesy lies? They are prophets of the deceit of their own heart. 27 They intend to make my people forget my name by the dreams they relate to one another, just as their fathers forgot my name because of Ba′al. 28 Let the prophet who has a dream relate the dream, but the one who has my word should speak my word truthfully.”

“What does the straw have in common with the grain?” declares Jehovah.

29 “Is not my word just like a fire,” declares Jehovah, “and like a forge hammer that smashes the crag?”

30 “So here I am against the prophets,” declares Jehovah, “who steal my words from one another.”

31 “Here I am against the prophets,” declares Jehovah, “those who use their tongue to say, ‘He declares!’”

32 “Here I am against the prophets of lying dreams,” declares Jehovah, “who relate them and lead my people astray because of their lies and their boasting.”

“But I did not send them or command them. So they will not benefit this people at all,” declares Jehovah.

33 “And when this people or a prophet or a priest asks you, ‘What is the burden[*] of Jehovah?’ you should reply to them, ‘“You people are the burden! And I will cast you off,” declares Jehovah.’ 34 As for the prophet or the priest or the people who say, ‘This is the burden[*] of Jehovah!’ I will turn my attention on that man and on his household. 35 This is what each of you is saying to his fellow and to his brother, ‘What has Jehovah answered? And what has Jehovah spoken?’ 36 But the burden[*] of Jehovah you should mention no more, for the burden[*] is each one’s own word, and you have changed the words of the living God, Jehovah of armies, our God.

37 “This is what you will say to the prophet, ‘What answer has Jehovah given you? And what has Jehovah spoken? 38 And if you keep saying, “The burden[*] of Jehovah!” this is what Jehovah says: “Because of your saying, ‘This word is the burden[*] of Jehovah,’ after I told you, ‘You must not say: “The burden[*] of Jehovah!”’ 39 look! I will lift you up and throw you away from my presence, both you and the city that I gave to you and your forefathers. 40 And I will bring on you everlasting disgrace and everlasting humiliation, which will not be forgotten.”’”

^ Jer. 23:5 Or “heir.”

^ Jer. 23:11 Or “apostate.”

^ Jer. 23:14 Lit., “strengthen the hands of.”

^ Jer. 23:16 Or “They are filling you with empty hopes.”

^ Jer. 23:33 Or “burdensome message.” The Hebrew word has a double meaning: “a weighty divine pronouncement” or “something burdensome.”

^ Jer. 23:34 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:36 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:36 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

Jeremiah  31 : 1 - 40

31 “At that time,” declares Jehovah, “I will become God to all the families of Israel, and they will become my people.”

 2 This is what Jehovah says:

“The people who survived the sword found favor in the wilderness

When Israel was walking to his resting-place.”

 3 From far away Jehovah appeared to me and said:

“I have loved you with an everlasting love.

That is why I have drawn you to me with loyal love.[*]

 4 Yet again I will rebuild you and you will be rebuilt.

O virgin of Israel, you will again take up your tambourines

And go forth dancing joyfully.[*]

 5 You will again plant vineyards in the mountains of Sa·mar′i·a;

The planters will plant and enjoy their fruit.

 6 For the day will come when the watchmen in the mountains of E′phra·im will call out:

‘Rise up, let us go up to Zion, to Jehovah our God.’”

 7 For this is what Jehovah says:

“Cry out to Jacob with rejoicing.

Shout for joy because you are over the nations.

Proclaim it; offer praise and say,

‘O Jehovah, save your people, the remnant of Israel.’

 8 I am bringing them back from the land of the north.

I will gather them together from the remotest parts of the earth.

Among them will be the blind and the lame,

The pregnant woman and the one giving birth, all together.

As a great congregation they will return here.

 9 They will come weeping.

I will lead them as they beg for favor.

I will guide them to streams[*] of water,

On a level path that will not make them stumble.

For I am a Father to Israel, and E′phra·im is my firstborn.”

10 Hear the word of Jehovah, you nations,

And proclaim it among the islands far away:

“The One who scattered Israel will gather him together.

He will watch over him as a shepherd does his flock.

11 For Jehovah will redeem Jacob

And rescue[*] him out of the hand of the one stronger than he is.

12 They will come and shout joyfully on the height of Zion

And become radiant over the goodness of[*] Jehovah,

Over the grain and the new wine and the oil,

And over the young of the flock and the herd.

They[*] will become like a well-watered garden,

And they will never languish again.”

13 “At that time the virgin will dance joyfully,

Also the young men and the old men together.

I will change their mourning into exultation.

I will comfort them and give them joy instead of their grief.

14 I will satisfy the priests[*] with plenty,[*]

And my people will be satisfied with my goodness,” declares Jehovah.

15 “This is what Jehovah says:

‘A voice is heard in Ra′mah, lamentation and bitter weeping:

Rachel is weeping over her sons.[*]

She has refused to be comforted over her sons,

Because they are no more.’”

16 This is what Jehovah says:

“‘Hold back your voice from weeping and your eyes from tears,

For there is a reward for your activity,’ declares Jehovah.

‘They will return from the land of the enemy.’

17 ‘And there is a hope for your future,’ declares Jehovah.

‘Your sons will return to their own territory.’”

18 “I have surely heard E′phra·im’s moaning,

‘You have corrected me, and I have been corrected,

Like a calf that has not been trained.

Bring me back, and I will readily turn back,

For you are Jehovah my God.

19 For after my turning back I felt remorse;

After I was made to understand I struck my thigh in grief.

I was ashamed and humiliated,

For I bore the reproach of my youth.’”

20 “Is E′phra·im not a precious son to me, a beloved child?

For as often as I speak against him, I do remember him still.

That is why my emotions[*] are stirred for him.

And I will surely have pity on him,” declares Jehovah.

21 “Set up road markers for yourself,

And put up signposts.

Pay attention to the highway, the way that you have to go.

Return, O virgin of Israel, return to these cities of yours.

22 How long will you waver, O unfaithful daughter?

For Jehovah has created something new in the earth:

A woman will eagerly pursue a man.”

23 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “They will again say these words in the land of Judah and in its cities when I gather back their captives: ‘May Jehovah bless you, O righteous dwelling place, O holy mountain.’ 24 And in it Judah and all its cities will dwell all together, farmers and those who lead the flocks. 25 For I will satisfy the weary one[*] and fill each one[*] who is languishing.”

26 At this I awoke and opened my eyes, and my sleep had been pleasurable to me.

27 “Look! The days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when I will sow the house of Israel and the house of Judah with the seed[*] of man and with the seed of livestock.”

28 “And just as I watched over them to uproot, to pull down, to tear down, to destroy, and to do harm, so I will watch over them to build up and to plant,” declares Jehovah. 29 “In those days they will no longer say, ‘The fathers ate sour grapes, but the teeth of the sons were set on edge.’[*] 30 But then each one will die for his own error. Any man eating sour grapes will have his own teeth set on edge.”

31 “Look! The days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when I will make with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah a new covenant. 32 It will not be like the covenant that I made with their forefathers on the day I took hold of their hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt, ‘my covenant that they broke, although I was their true master,’[*] declares Jehovah.”

33 “For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days,” declares Jehovah. “I will put my law within them, and in their heart I will write it. And I will become their God, and they will become my people.”

34 “And they will no longer teach each one his neighbor and each one his brother, saying, ‘Know Jehovah!’ for they will all know me, from the least to the greatest of them,” declares Jehovah. “For I will forgive their error, and I will no longer remember their sin.”

35 This is what Jehovah says,

Who gives the sun for light by day,

The laws[*] of the moon and the stars for light by night,

Who stirs up the sea and makes its waves boisterous,

Whose name is Jehovah of armies:

36 “‘If these regulations should ever fail,’ declares Jehovah,

‘Only then would the offspring of Israel cease as a nation before me always.’”

37 This is what Jehovah says: “‘If the heavens above could be measured and the foundations of the earth below could be explored, only then could I reject all the offspring of Israel for all they have done,’ declares Jehovah.”

38 “Look! The days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when the city will be built to Jehovah from the Tower of Ha·nan′el to the Corner Gate. 39 And the measuring line will go out straight ahead to the hill of Ga′reb, and it will turn toward Go′ah. 40 And all the valley[*] of the carcasses and of ashes[*] and all the terraces as far as the Kid′ron Valley, clear to the corner of the Horse Gate toward the east, will be something holy to Jehovah. It will never again be uprooted or torn down.”

^ Jer. 31:3 Or “have continued to show loyal love to you.”

^ Jer. 31:4 Or “go forth in the dance of those who are laughing.”

^ Jer. 31:9 Or “wadis.”

^ Jer. 31:11 Or “reclaim.”

^ Jer. 31:12 Or “the good things from.”

^ Jer. 31:12 Or “Their soul.”

^ Jer. 31:14 Or “the soul of the priests.”

^ Jer. 31:14 Lit., “fatness.”

^ Jer. 31:15 Or “children.”

^ Jer. 31:20 Lit., “intestines.”

^ Jer. 31:25 Or “soul.”

^ Jer. 31:25 Or “soul.”

^ Jer. 31:27 Or “offspring.”

^ Jer. 31:29 Lit., “got blunted.”

^ Jer. 31:32 Or possibly, “their husband.”

^ Jer. 31:35 Or “statutes.”

^ Jer. 31:40 Or “low plain.”

^ Jer. 31:40 Or “fatty ashes,” that is, ashes soaked with the fat of the sacrifices.

Jeremiah  41 : 1 - 18

41 In the seventh month Ish′ma·el son of Neth·a·ni′ah son of E·lish′a·ma, who was of the royal line[*] and one of the principal men of the king, came with ten other men to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam at Miz′pah. As they were eating a meal together in Miz′pah, 2 Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and the ten men who were with him rose up and struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan with the sword. So he put to death the one whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land. 3 Ish′ma·el also struck down all the Jews who were with Ged·a·li′ah in Miz′pah, as well as the Chal·de′an soldiers who were there.

4 On the second day after Ged·a·li′ah had been put to death, before anyone knew about it, 5 there came 80 men from She′chem, from Shi′loh, and from Sa·mar′i·a. Their beards were shaved off, their garments were ripped apart, they had cut themselves, and they had grain offerings and frankincense in their hand to bring to the house of Jehovah. 6 So Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah went out from Miz′pah to meet them, weeping as he walked along. When he encountered them, he said to them: “Come to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam.” 7 But when they came into the city, Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and his men slaughtered them and threw them into the cistern.

8 But there were ten men among them who said to Ish′ma·el: “Do not put us to death, for we have hidden stores of wheat, barley, oil, and honey in the field.” So he refrained from putting them to death along with their brothers. 9 Now Ish′ma·el threw all the carcasses of the men he had killed into a great cistern, the one that King A′sa had made because of King Ba′a·sha of Israel. This was the cistern that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah filled with the slain men.

10 Ish′ma·el took captive all the rest of the people in Miz′pah, including the daughters of the king and all the people left in Miz′pah, whom Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard had put in the custody of Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam. Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah took them captive and went off to cross over to the Am′mon·ites.

11 When Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the army chiefs who were with him heard about all the evil that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah had done, 12 they took all the men and went off to fight against Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, and they found him by the great waters[*] in Gib′e·on.

13 All the people who were with Ish′ma·el rejoiced when they saw Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the army chiefs with him. 14 Then all the people whom Ish′ma·el had taken captive from Miz′pah turned around and went back with Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah. 15 But Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and eight of his men escaped from Jo·ha′nan and went to the Am′mon·ites.

16 Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the army chiefs who were with him took with them the rest of the people from Miz′pah, those whom they had rescued from Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah after he had struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam. They brought the men, the soldiers, the women, the children, and the court officials back from Gib′e·on. 17 So they went and stayed in the lodging place of Chim′ham next to Beth′le·hem, intending to go on into Egypt 18 because of the Chal·de′ans. For they had become afraid of them, since Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah had struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam, whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land.

^ Jer. 41:1 Lit., “the seed of the kingdom.”

^ Jer. 41:12 Or possibly, “great pool.”

Jeremiah  49 : 1 - 39

49 For the Am′mon·ites, this is what Jehovah says:

“Does Israel have no sons?

Does he have no heir?

Why has Mal′cam taken possession of Gad?

And why are his people living in Israel’s cities?”

 2 “‘Therefore look! the days are coming,’ declares Jehovah,

‘When I will cause the alarm signal of war[*] to be heard against Rab′bah of the Am′mon·ites.

She will become a desolate mound,

And her dependent[*] towns will be set on fire.’

‘And Israel will take possession of those who dispossessed him,’ says Jehovah.

 3 ‘Wail, O Hesh′bon, for A′i has been destroyed!

Cry out, O dependent towns of Rab′bah.

Put on sackcloth.

Wail and rove about among the stone pens,[*]

For Mal′cam will go into exile,

Together with his priests and his princes.

 4 Why do you brag about the valleys,[*]

About your flowing plain, O unfaithful daughter,

Who trusts in her treasures

And who says: “Who will come against me?”’”

 5 “‘Here I am bringing something dreadful on you,’ declares the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies,

‘From all those around you.

You will be dispersed in every direction,

And no one will gather those who flee.’”

 6 “‘But afterward I will gather the captives of the Am′mon·ites,’ declares Jehovah.”

7 For E′dom, this is what Jehovah of armies says:

“Is there no longer any wisdom in Te′man?

Has good advice perished from those with understanding?

Has their wisdom rotted?

 8 Flee, turn back!

Go and dwell down in the depths, O inhabitants of De′dan!

For I will bring disaster on E′sau

When the time comes to turn my attention to him.

 9 If grape gatherers came in to you,

Would they not leave some behind for gleaning?

If thieves came in by night,

They would cause only as much ruin as they wanted.

10 But I will strip E′sau bare.

I will uncover his places of concealment,

So that he cannot hide.

His children and his brothers and his neighbors will all be destroyed,

And he will be no more.

11 Leave your fatherless children,

And I will preserve them alive,

And your widows will trust in me.”

12 For this is what Jehovah says: “Look! If those not sentenced to drink the cup must drink it, should you be left completely unpunished? You will not be left unpunished, for you must drink it.”

13 “For by myself I have sworn,” declares Jehovah, “that Boz′rah will become an object of horror, a reproach, a devastation, and a curse; and all her cities will become perpetual ruins.”

14 I have heard a report from Jehovah,

An envoy has been sent among the nations, saying:

“Gather yourselves together and come against her;

Prepare for battle.”

15 “For look! I have made you insignificant among the nations,

Despised among men.

16 The shuddering you caused has deceived you,

The presumptuousness of your heart,

O you who reside in the retreats of the crag,

Occupying the highest hill.

Although you build your nest high up like an eagle,

I will bring you down from there,” declares Jehovah.

17 “And E′dom must become an object of horror. Everyone passing along by her will stare in horror and whistle on account of all her plagues. 18 Just as in the overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and of their neighboring towns,” Jehovah says, “no one will dwell there, and no man will settle there.

19 “Look! Someone will come up against the secure pastures like a lion from the dense thickets along the Jordan, but in a moment I will make him run away from her. And I will appoint over her the chosen one. For who is like me, and who will challenge me? What shepherd can stand before me? 20 Therefore hear, O men, the decision[*] that Jehovah has made against E′dom and what he has thought out against the inhabitants of Te′man:

Surely the little ones of the flock will be dragged away.

He will make their dwelling place desolate because of them.

21 At the sound of their falling, the earth has quaked.

There is an outcry!

The sound has been heard as far as the Red Sea.

22 Look! Just like an eagle he will ascend and swoop down,

And he will spread out his wings over Boz′rah.

In that day the heart of the warriors of E′dom

Will become like the heart of a woman in childbirth.”

23 For Damascus:

“Ha′math and Ar′pad have been put to shame,

For they have heard a bad report.

They melt in fear.

There is anxiety in the sea that cannot be calmed.

24 Damascus has lost courage.

She has turned to flee, but panic has seized her.

Distress and pain have taken hold of her,

Like a woman who is giving birth.

25 How is it that the city of praise has not been abandoned,

The town of exultation?

26 For her young men will fall in her public squares,

And all the soldiers will perish in that day,” declares Jehovah of armies.

27 “I will set the wall of Damascus on fire,

And it will consume the fortified towers of Ben-ha′dad.”

28 For Ke′dar and the kingdoms of Ha′zor, which King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon struck down, this is what Jehovah says:

“Rise up, go up to Ke′dar,

And destroy the sons of the East.

29 Their tents and their flocks will be taken,

Their tent cloths and all their goods.

Their camels will be carried off,

And they will cry out to them, ‘Terror is all around!’”

30 “Flee, go far away!

Go and dwell down in the depths, O inhabitants of Ha′zor,” declares Jehovah.

“For King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon has devised a strategy against you,

And he has thought out a plan against you.”

31 “Rise up, go up against the nation that is at peace,

Dwelling in security!” declares Jehovah.

“It has no doors or bars; they live in isolation.

32 Their camels will become plunder,

And their abundant livestock a spoil.

I will scatter them to every wind,[*]

Those who clip their hair at the temples,

And I will bring their disaster from every direction,” declares Jehovah.

33 “And Ha′zor will become a lair of jackals,

A perpetual desolation.

No one will dwell there,

And no man will settle in her.”

34 This is the word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah the prophet concerning E′lam in the beginning of the reign of King Zed·e·ki′ah of Judah: 35 “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Here I am breaking the bow of E′lam, the source[*] of their mightiness. 36 I will bring in on E′lam the four winds from the four extremities of the heavens, and I will scatter them to all these winds. There will not be a nation to which the dispersed ones of E′lam will not go.’”

37 “I will shatter the E′lam·ites before their enemies and before those seeking to take their life;[*] and I will bring calamity on them, my burning anger,” declares Jehovah. “And I will send the sword after them until I have exterminated them.”

38 “And I will set my throne in E′lam, and I will destroy from there the king and the princes,” declares Jehovah.

39 “But in the final part of the days, I will gather the captives of E′lam,” declares Jehovah.

^ Jer. 49:2 Or possibly, “the sound of the battle cry.”

^ Jer. 49:2 Or “surrounding.”

^ Jer. 49:3 Or “sheep pens.”

^ Jer. 49:4 Or “low plains.”

^ Jer. 49:20 Or “counsel.”

^ Jer. 49:28 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 49:30 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 49:32 Or “in every direction.”

^ Jer. 49:35 Lit., “beginning.”

^ Jer. 49:37 Or “seeking their soul.”

Jeremiah  50 : 1 - 46

50 The word that Jehovah spoke concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chal·de′ans, through Jeremiah the prophet:

 2 “Declare it among the nations and proclaim it.

Raise a signal[*] and proclaim it.

Do not hide anything!

Say, ‘Babylon has been captured.

Bel has been put to shame.

Mer′o·dach has become terrified.

Her images have been put to shame.

Her disgusting idols[*] have become terrified.’

 3 For a nation has come against her from the north.

It makes her land an object of horror;

No one is dwelling in her.

Both man and beast have taken flight;

They have gone away.”

4 “In those days and at that time,” declares Jehovah, “the people of Israel and the people of Judah will come together. They will weep as they walk, and together they will seek Jehovah their God. 5 They will ask the way to Zion, with their faces turned in that direction, saying, ‘Come and let us join ourselves to Jehovah in an everlasting covenant that will not be forgotten.’ 6 My people have become a flock of lost sheep. Their own shepherds caused them to stray. They led them away onto the mountains, roaming from mountain to hill. They have forgotten their resting-place. 7 All those finding them have devoured them, and their enemies have said, ‘We are not guilty, because they sinned against Jehovah, against the dwelling place of righteousness and the hope of their forefathers, Jehovah.’”

 8 “Flee out of the midst of Babylon,

Go out of the land of the Chal·de′ans,

And be like the leading animals before the flock.

 9 For here I am raising up and bringing against Babylon

An assembly of great nations from the land of the north.

They will come against her in battle formation;

From there she will be captured.

Their arrows are like those of a warrior

Causing bereavement of children;

They do not come back without results.

10 Chal·de′a will become a spoil.

All those taking spoil from her will be fully satisfied,” declares Jehovah.

11 “For you kept rejoicing, you kept exulting

When pillaging my own inheritance.

For you kept pawing like a heifer in the grass,

And you kept neighing like stallions.

12 Your mother has been put to shame.

She who gave birth to you has been disappointed.

Look! She is the least of the nations,

A waterless wilderness and a desert.

13 Because of the indignation of Jehovah she will not be inhabited;

She will become utterly desolate.

Anyone passing by Babylon will stare in horror

And whistle because of all her plagues.

14 Come against Babylon in battle formation on every side,

All you who are bending[*] the bow.

Shoot at her, spare no arrow,

For it is against Jehovah that she has sinned.

15 Shout a war cry against her on every side.

She has surrendered.[*]

Her pillars have fallen, her walls are torn down,

For it is the vengeance of Jehovah.

Take your vengeance on her.

Do to her just as she has done.

16 Cut off the sower from Babylon

And the one handling the sickle in harvesttime.

Because of the cruel sword, each will return to his own people,

Each one will flee to his own land.

17 “The people of Israel are scattered sheep. Lions have dispersed them. First the king of As·syr′i·a devoured them; then King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon gnawed on their bones. 18 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Here I will deal with the king of Babylon and with his land in the same way that I dealt with the king of As·syr′i·a. 19 And I will bring Israel back to his pasture, and he will graze on Car′mel and on Ba′shan, and on the mountains of E′phra·im and of Gil′e·ad he[*] will be satisfied.’”

20 “In those days and at that time,” declares Jehovah,

“Israel’s guilt will be searched for,

But there will be none,

And the sins of Judah will not be found,

For I will forgive those whom I let remain.”

21 “Go up against the land of Mer·a·tha′im and against the inhabitants of Pe′kod.

Let them be massacred and completely destroyed,”[*] declares Jehovah.

“Do all that I have commanded you.

22 There is the sound of war in the land,

A great catastrophe.

23 How the forge hammer of all the earth has been cut down and broken!

How Babylon has become an object of horror among the nations!

24 I have laid a snare for you, and you have been caught, O Babylon,

And you did not know it.

You were found and captured,

For it was Jehovah whom you opposed.

25 Jehovah has opened his storehouse,

And he brings out the weapons of his indignation.

For the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has a work

In the land of the Chal·de′ans.

26 Come against her from distant places.

Open up her granaries.

Pile her up like heaps of grain.

Destroy her completely.[*]

May she have no one left.

27 Massacre all her young bulls;

Let them go down to the slaughter.

Woe to them, for their day has come,

Their time of reckoning!

28 There is the sound of those fleeing,

Those escaping from the land of Babylon,

To declare in Zion the vengeance of Jehovah our God,

The vengeance for his temple.

29 Summon archers against Babylon,

All who are bending[*] the bow.

Camp all around her; let no one escape.

Repay her according to her activity.

Do to her just as she has done.

For she has acted arrogantly against Jehovah,

Against the Holy One of Israel.

30 So her young men will fall in her public squares,

And all her soldiers will perish[*] in that day,” declares Jehovah.

31 “Look! I am against you, O defiant one,” declares the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies,

“For your day must come, the time that I will call you to account.

32 You, O defiant one, will stumble and fall,

With no one to raise you up.

And I will set your cities on fire,

And it will consume everything around you.”

33 This is what Jehovah of armies says:

“The people of Israel and Judah are oppressed,

And all those taking them captive have held onto them.

They have refused to let them go.

34 But their Repurchaser is strong.

Jehovah of armies is his name.

He will surely plead their legal case,

In order to give rest to the land

And to bring agitation to the inhabitants of Babylon.”

35 “There is a sword against the Chal·de′ans,” declares Jehovah,

“Against the inhabitants of Babylon and against her princes and against her wise ones.

36 There is a sword against the empty talkers,[*] and they will act foolishly.

There is a sword against her warriors, and they will become terrified.

37 There is a sword against their horses and their war chariots,

And against all the mixed populations in her midst,

And they will become like women.

There is a sword against her treasures, and they will be plundered.

38 There is a devastation on her waters, and they will be dried up.

For it is a land of graven images,

And because of their frightful visions they keep acting with madness.

39 Therefore, the desert creatures will dwell with the howling animals,

And in her the ostriches will dwell.

She will never again be inhabited,

Nor will she be a place of residence throughout all generations.”

40 “Just as with God’s overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and of their neighboring towns,” declares Jehovah, “no one will dwell there, and no man will settle there.

41 Look! A people is coming in from the north;

A great nation and grand kings will be raised up

From the remotest parts of the earth.

42 Bow and javelin they wield.

They are cruel and will show no mercy.

Their sound is like the roaring sea,

As they ride on their horses.

Like one man, they line up in battle formation against you, O daughter of Babylon.

43 The king of Babylon has heard the report about them,

And his hands drop down.

Anguish seizes him,

Pain like that of a woman giving birth.

44 “Look! Someone will come up against the secure pastures like a lion from the dense thickets along the Jordan, but in a moment I will make them run away from her. And I will appoint over her the chosen one. For who is like me, and who will challenge me? What shepherd can stand before me? 45 Therefore hear, O men, the decision[*] that Jehovah has made against Babylon and what he has thought out against the land of the Chal·de′ans.

Surely the little ones of the flock will be dragged away.

He will make their dwelling place desolate because of them.

46 At the sound of Babylon’s capture, the earth will quake,

And an outcry will be heard among the nations.”

^ Jer. 50:2 Or “signal pole.”

^ Jer. 50:2 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ Jer. 50:14 Lit., “treading.”

^ Jer. 50:15 Lit., “given her hand.”

^ Jer. 50:17 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 50:19 Or “his soul.”

^ Jer. 50:21 Or “and devote them to destruction.”

^ Jer. 50:26 Or “Devote her to destruction.”

^ Jer. 50:29 Lit., “treading.”

^ Jer. 50:30 Lit., “be silenced.”

^ Jer. 50:36 Or “the false prophets.”

^ Jer. 50:45 Or “counsel.”

Jeremiah  52 : 1 - 34

52 Zed·e·ki′ah was 21 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·mu′tal the daughter of Jeremiah of Lib′nah. 2 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Je·hoi′a·kim had done. 3 It was because of Jehovah’s anger that these things took place in Jerusalem and in Judah, until he cast them out of his sight. And Zed·e·ki′ah rebelled against the king of Babylon. 4 In the ninth year of Zed·e·ki′ah’s reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] of Babylon came with all his army against Jerusalem. They camped against it and built a siege wall all around it. 5 And the city was under siege until the 11th year of King Zed·e·ki′ah.

6 In the fourth month, on the ninth day of the month, the famine was severe in the city, and there was no food for the people of the land. 7 Finally the city wall was broken through, and all the soldiers fled from the city by night through the gate between the double wall near the king’s garden, while the Chal·de′ans were surrounding the city; and they continued by the way of the Ar′a·bah. 8 But the Chal·de′an army pursued the king, and they overtook Zed·e·ki′ah in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho, and all his troops were scattered from his side. 9 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math, and he passed sentence on him. 10 And the king of Babylon slaughtered Zed·e·ki′ah’s sons before his eyes, and he also slaughtered all the princes of Judah there at Rib′lah. 11 Then the king of Babylon blinded Zed·e·ki′ah’s eyes, bound him with copper fetters, brought him to Babylon, and kept him imprisoned until the day of his death.

12 In the fifth month, on the tenth day of the month, that is, in the 19th year of King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] the king of Babylon, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard, who was an attendant of the king of Babylon, came into Jerusalem. 13 He burned down the house of Jehovah, the king’s house,[*] and all the houses of Jerusalem; he also burned down every large house. 14 And the walls surrounding Jerusalem were pulled down by the entire Chal·de′an army that was with the chief of the guard.

15 Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took into exile some of the lowly people and the rest of the people who were left in the city. He also took the deserters who had defected to the king of Babylon as well as the rest of the master craftsmen. 16 But Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard left some of the poorest people of the land to serve as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers.

17 And the Chal·de′ans broke into pieces the copper pillars of the house of Jehovah and the carriages and the copper Sea that were in the house of Jehovah, and they carried all the copper away to Babylon. 18 They also took the cans, the shovels, the extinguishers, the bowls, the cups, and all the copper utensils used in the temple service. 19 The chief of the guard took the basins, the fire holders, the bowls, the cans, the lampstands, the cups, and the bowls that were of genuine gold and silver. 20 As for the two pillars, the Sea, the 12 copper bulls under the Sea, and the carriages that King Sol′o·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, the copper of all these articles was beyond weighing.

21 As for the pillars, each pillar was 18 cubits[*] high, a measuring cord of 12 cubits could encircle it; its thickness was four fingerbreadths,[*] and it was hollow. 22 And the capital on it was of copper; and the height of the one capital was five cubits; and the network and pomegranates all around on the capital were all made of copper. The second pillar was just like it, also the pomegranates. 23 There were 96 pomegranates on the sides; in all, there were 100 pomegranates around the network.

24 The chief of the guard also took Se·rai′ah the chief priest, Zeph·a·ni′ah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. 25 And he took from the city one court official who was the commissioner over the soldiers, seven close associates of the king who were found in the city, as well as the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and 60 men of the common people of the land who were yet found in the city. 26 Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah. 27 The king of Babylon struck them down and put them to death at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math. Thus Judah went into exile from its land.

28 These are the people whom Neb·u·chad·nez′zar[*] took into exile: in the seventh year, 3,023 Jews.

29 In the 18th year of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar,[*] 832 people[*] were taken from Jerusalem.

30 In the 23rd year of Neb·u·chad·nez′zar,[*] Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the guard took Jews into exile, 745 people.[*]

In all, 4,600 people[*] were taken into exile.

31 Then in the 37th year of the exile of King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah, in the 12th month, on the 25th day of the month, King E′vil-mer′o·dach of Babylon, in the year he became king, released[*] King Je·hoi′a·chin of Judah and brought him out of prison. 32 He spoke kindly with him and put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. 33 So Je·hoi′a·chin took off his prison garments, and he regularly ate before him all the days of his life. 34 A regular allowance of food was given him from the king of Babylon, day after day, until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

^ Jer. 52:4 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:12 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:13 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 52:21 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ Jer. 52:21 A fingerbreadth equaled 1.85 cm (0.73 in.). See App. B14.

^ Jer. 52:28 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:29 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:29 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:30 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:30 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:30 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:31 Lit., “raised up the head of.”

Ezekiel  27 : 1 - 36

27 The word of Jehovah again came to me, saying: 2 “As for you, son of man, sing a dirge[*] over Tyre, 3 and say to Tyre,

‘You who dwell at the gateways of the sea,

The merchant for the peoples of many islands,

This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says:

“O Tyre, you yourself have said, ‘I am perfect in beauty.’

 4 Your territories are in the heart of the sea,

And your builders have perfected your beauty.

 5 They made all your planks from the juniper trees of Se′nir,

And they took a cedar from Leb′a·non to make a mast for you.

 6 They made your oars from oaks of Ba′shan,

And your prow was of cypress inlaid with ivory from the islands of Kit′tim.

 7 Colorful linen from Egypt served as cloth for your sail,

And your deck awnings were of blue thread and purple wool from the islands of E·li′shah.

 8 The inhabitants of Si′don and of Ar′vad were your rowers.

Your own skilled men, O Tyre, were your sailors.

 9 The experienced[*] and skilled men of Ge′bal caulked your seams.

All the ships of the sea and their mariners came to you to trade merchandise.

10 Men of Persia, Lud, and Put were in your army, your men of war.

They hung their shields and helmets in you, and they brought you splendor.

11 The men of Ar′vad in your army were stationed on your walls all around,

And brave men manned your towers.

They hung circular shields all around your walls

And perfected your beauty.

12 “‘“Tar′shish did business with you because of your abundant wealth. They exchanged silver, iron, tin, and lead for your goods. 13 Ja′van, Tu′bal, and Me′shech traded with you, exchanging slaves and articles of copper for your merchandise. 14 The house of To·gar′mah exchanged horses and steeds and mules for your goods. 15 The people of De′dan traded with you; you employed merchants on many islands; they gave ivory tusks and ebony as your tribute. 16 E′dom did business with you because of the abundance of your products. They gave turquoise, purple wool, colorful embroidery, fine fabric, corals, and rubies in exchange for your goods.

17 “‘“Judah and the land of Israel traded with you, giving the wheat of Min′nith, choice foods, honey, oil, and balsam in exchange for your goods.

18 “‘“Damascus did business with you because of the abundance of your products and all your wealth, trading the wine of Hel′bon and wool of Za′har.[*] 19 Ve′dan and Ja′van from U′zal gave wrought iron, cassia,[*] and cane[*] in exchange for your goods. 20 De′dan traded with you in saddlecloths[*] for riding. 21 You employed the Arabs and all the chieftains of Ke′dar, who were merchants of lambs and rams and goats. 22 The merchants of She′ba and Ra′a·mah traded with you; they gave all sorts of the finest perfumes, precious stones, and gold in exchange for your goods. 23 Ha′ran, Can′neh, E′den, the merchants of She′ba, As′shur, and Chil′mad traded with you. 24 In your marketplace they traded beautiful garments, cloaks made of blue material and colorful embroidery, and multicolored carpets, all bound and secured with ropes.

25 The ships of Tar′shish were the caravans for your merchandise,

So that you were filled and loaded down[*] in the heart of the open sea.

26 Your rowers have brought you into heavy seas;

The east wind has wrecked you in the heart of the open sea.

27 Your wealth, your goods, your merchandise, your mariners, and your sailors,

Those caulking your seams, those trading your merchandise, and all the men of war

—The entire multitude[*] within you—

They will all sink in the heart of the open sea on the day of your downfall.

28 When your sailors cry out, the coastlands will shudder.

29 All the oarsmen, the mariners, and the seamen

Will come down from their ships and stand on the land.

30 They will raise their voices and cry out bitterly over you

As they throw dust on their heads and wallow in ashes.

31 They will make themselves bald and put on sackcloth;

They will weep bitterly[*] over you with intense wailing.

32 In their lamentation they will sing a dirge and chant over you:

‘Who is like Tyre, now silent in the midst of the sea?

33 When your goods came in from the open sea, you satisfied many peoples.

Your abundant wealth and your merchandise enriched earth’s kings.

34 Now you have been wrecked in the open sea, in the deep waters,

And all your merchandise and your people have sunk with you.

35 All the inhabitants of the islands will stare at you in amazement,

And their kings will shudder with horror—their faces will be troubled.

36 The merchants among the nations will whistle over what happened to you.

Your end will be sudden and terrible,

And you will cease to exist for all time.’”’”

^ Ezek. 27:2 Or “song of mourning.”

^ Ezek. 27:9 Lit., “The old men.”

^ Ezek. 27:18 Or “and reddish-gray wool.”

^ Ezek. 27:19 A tree of the same family as the cinnamon tree.

^ Ezek. 27:19 An aromatic reed.

^ Ezek. 27:20 Or “garments of woven material.”

^ Ezek. 27:25 Or possibly, “and glorious.”

^ Ezek. 27:27 Lit., “congregation.”

^ Ezek. 27:31 Or “with bitterness of soul.”

Ezekiel  47 : 1 - 23

47 Then he brought me back to the entrance of the temple, and there I saw water flowing eastward from under the threshold of the temple, for the front of the temple was facing east. The water was flowing down from under the right side of the temple, south of the altar.

2 He then led me out by way of the north gate and took me outside and around to the outer gate that is facing east, and I saw water trickling from the right side.

3 When the man went out toward the east with a measuring line in his hand, he measured off 1,000 cubits[*] and had me pass through the water; the water was ankle deep.

4 Then he measured off another 1,000 and had me pass through the water, and it was up to the knees.

He measured off another 1,000 and had me pass through, and the water was up to the hips.

5 When he measured off another 1,000, it was a torrent that I was unable to walk across, for the water was so deep that one had to swim, a torrent of water that could not be crossed on foot.

6 He asked me: “Have you seen this, son of man?”

Then he had me walk and return to the bank of the stream. 7 When I returned, I saw that on the bank of the stream were very many trees on both sides. 8 Then he said to me: “This water flows toward the eastern region and continues down through the Ar′a·bah[*] and enters the sea. When it enters the sea, the water there will be healed. 9 Swarms of living creatures[*] will be able to live wherever the waters[*] flow. There will be an abundance of fish, because this water will flow there. The seawater will be healed, and everything will live wherever the stream goes.

10 “Fishermen will stand beside it from En-ged′i clear to En-eg′la·im, where there will be a drying yard for dragnets. There will be an abundance of many kinds of fish, like the fish of the Great Sea.[*]

11 “It will have swampy places and marshy places, and these will not be healed. They will be abandoned to salt.

12 “All sorts of trees for food will grow on both banks of the stream. Their leaves will not wither; nor will their fruitage fail. Each month they will bear new fruit, because the water for them flows from the sanctuary. Their fruitage will serve as food and their leaves for healing.”

13 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “This is the territory that you will assign as the land inheritance of the 12 tribes of Israel, and Joseph will have two portions. 14 You will inherit it and receive equal shares.[*] I swore to give this land to your forefathers, and now it is assigned[*] to you as an inheritance.

15 “This is the boundary of the land on the northern side: It goes from the Great Sea by the way to Heth′lon toward Ze′dad, 16 Ha′math, Be·ro′thah, and Sib′ra·im, which is between the territory of Damascus and the territory of Ha′math, to Ha′zer-hat′ti·con, which is by the boundary of Ha·u·ran′. 17 So the boundary will run from the sea to Ha′zar-e′non, along the boundary of Damascus to the north, and the boundary of Ha′math. This is the northern border.

18 “The eastern side runs between Ha·u·ran′ and Damascus and along the Jordan between Gil′e·ad and the land of Israel. You should measure from the boundary to the eastern sea.[*] This is the eastern border.

19 “The southern border[*] will be from Ta′mar to the waters of Mer′i·bath-ka′desh, then to the Wadi[*] and to the Great Sea. This is the southern border.[*]

20 “On the western side is the Great Sea, from the boundary up to a point opposite Le′bo-ha′math.[*] This is the western border.”

21 “You are to apportion this land among yourselves, among the 12 tribes of Israel. 22 You should distribute it for inheritance among yourselves and to the foreigners residing with you who have had children while living among you; and they will be like native-born Israelites to you. They will receive an inheritance among the tribes of Israel along with you. 23 You should give the foreign resident an inheritance in the territory of the tribe where he has taken up residence,” declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

^ Ezek. 47:3 This refers to long cubits. See App. B14.

^ Ezek. 47:8 Or “the desert plain.”

^ Ezek. 47:9 Or “souls.”

^ Ezek. 47:9 Lit., “the two streams.”

^ Ezek. 47:10 That is, the Mediterranean.

^ Ezek. 47:14 Lit., “inherit it, each like his brother.”

^ Ezek. 47:14 Lit., “falls.”

^ Ezek. 47:18 That is, the Dead Sea.

^ Ezek. 47:19 Lit., “the south side southward.”

^ Ezek. 47:19 That is, the Wadi of Egypt.

^ Ezek. 47:19 Lit., “the south side southward.”

^ Ezek. 47:20 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

Daniel  3 : 1 - 30

3 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king made an image[*] of gold that was 60 cubits[*] high and 6 cubits[*] wide. He set it up on the plain of Du′ra in the province[*] of Babylon. 2 Then King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar sent word to assemble the satraps, prefects, governors, advisers, treasurers, judges, magistrates, and all the administrators of the provinces[*] to come to the inauguration of the image that King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had set up.

3 So the satraps, prefects, governors, advisers, treasurers, judges, magistrates, and all the administrators of the provinces[*] assembled for the inauguration of the image that King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had set up. And they stood in front of the image that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had set up. 4 The herald loudly proclaimed: “You are commanded, O peoples, nations, and language groups, 5 that when you hear the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, triangular harp, stringed instrument, bagpipe, and all the other musical instruments, you must fall down and worship the image of gold that King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar has set up. 6 Whoever does not fall down and worship will immediately be thrown into the burning fiery furnace.” 7 So when all the peoples heard the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, triangular harp, stringed instrument, and all the other musical instruments, all the peoples, nations, and language groups fell down and worshipped the image of gold that King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had set up.

8 Now at that time some of the Chal·de′ans came forward and accused[*] the Jews. 9 They said to King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar: “O king, may you live on forever. 10 You, O king, gave the command that every man who hears the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, triangular harp, stringed instrument, bagpipe, and all the other musical instruments should fall down and worship the image of gold; 11 and that whoever would not fall down and worship should be thrown into the burning fiery furnace. 12 But there are certain Jews whom you appointed to administer the province[*] of Babylon: Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go. These men have paid no regard to you, O king. They are not serving your gods, and they refuse to worship the image of gold that you have set up.”

13 Then Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, in a furious rage, ordered Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go to be brought in. So these men were brought in before the king. 14 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar said to them: “Is it really true, Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go, that you are not serving my gods and that you refuse to worship the image of gold that I have set up? 15 Now when you hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, the zither, the triangular harp, the stringed instrument, the bagpipe, and all the other musical instruments, if you are ready to fall down and worship the image that I have made, fine. But if you refuse to worship, you will immediately be thrown into the burning fiery furnace. And who is the god who can rescue you out of my hands?”

16 Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go answered the king: “O Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, we have no need to answer you in this matter. 17 If it must be, our God whom we serve is able to rescue us from the burning fiery furnace, O king, and to rescue us from your hand. 18 But even if he does not, let it be known to you, O king, that we will not serve your gods or worship the image of gold that you have set up.”

19 Then Neb·u·chad·nez′zar became so furious with Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go that the expression of his face changed[*] toward them, and he gave orders to heat the furnace seven times hotter than usual. 20 He ordered some of the mighty men from his army to bind Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go and to throw them into the burning fiery furnace.

21 So these men were tied up while still wearing their cloaks, garments, caps, and all their other clothing, and they were thrown into the burning fiery furnace. 22 Because the king’s command was so harsh and the furnace was exceptionally hot, the men who took up Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go were the ones killed by the flames of the fire. 23 But these three men, Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go, fell bound into the burning fiery furnace.

24 King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar then became frightened and quickly rose up and said to his high officials: “Did we not tie up three men and throw them into the fire?” They answered the king: “Yes, O king.” 25 He said: “Look! I see four men walking about free in the midst of the fire, and they are unharmed, and the fourth one looks like a son of the gods.”

26 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar approached the door of the burning fiery furnace and said: “Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go, you servants of the Most High God, step out and come here!” Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go stepped out from the midst of the fire. 27 And the satraps, prefects, governors, and the high officials of the king who were assembled there saw that the fire had had no effect on[*] the bodies of these men; not a hair of their heads had been singed, their cloaks looked no different, and there was not even the smell of fire on them.

28 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar then declared: “Praised be the God of Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go, who sent his angel and rescued his servants. They trusted in him and went against the command of the king and were willing to die[*] rather than serve or worship any god except their own God. 29 I am therefore issuing an order that any people, nation, or language group that says anything against the God of Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go should be dismembered, and their houses should be turned into public latrines;[*] for there is no other god who is able to rescue like this one.”

30 The king then promoted[*] Sha′drach, Me′shach, and A·bed′ne·go in the province[*] of Babylon.

^ Dan. 3:1 Or “statue.”

^ Dan. 3:1 About 27 m (88 ft). See App. B14.

^ Dan. 3:1 About 2.7 m (8.8 ft). See App. B14.

^ Dan. 3:1 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Dan. 3:2 Or “jurisdictional districts.”

^ Dan. 3:3 Or “jurisdictional districts.”

^ Dan. 3:8 Or “slandered.”

^ Dan. 3:12 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Dan. 3:19 Or “that his attitude changed completely.”

^ Dan. 3:27 Or “power over.”

^ Dan. 3:28 Or “and gave up their bodies.”

^ Dan. 3:29 Or possibly, “garbage dumps; dunghills.”

^ Dan. 3:30 Lit., “caused to prosper.”

^ Dan. 3:30 Or “jurisdictional district.”

Daniel  5 : 1 - 31

5 As regards King Bel·shaz′zar, he held a great feast for a thousand of his nobles, and he was drinking wine in front of them. 2 While under the influence of the wine, Bel·shaz′zar gave an order to bring in the vessels of gold and silver that his father Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had taken from the temple in Jerusalem, so that the king and his nobles, his concubines and his secondary wives could drink from them. 3 Then they brought in the gold vessels that had been taken from the temple of the house of God in Jerusalem, and the king and his nobles, his concubines and his secondary wives drank from them. 4 They drank wine, and they praised the gods of gold and silver, of copper, iron, wood, and stone.

5 At that very moment the fingers of a man’s hand appeared and began writing on the plaster of the wall of the king’s palace opposite the lampstand, and the king could see the back of the hand as it was writing. 6 Then the king turned pale[*] and his thoughts terrified him, and his hips shook and his knees began to knock together.

7 The king called out loudly to summon the conjurers, the Chal·de′ans,[*] and the astrologers. The king said to the wise men of Babylon: “Any man who reads this writing and tells me its interpretation will be clothed with purple, a gold necklace will be placed around his neck, and he will rule as the third one in the kingdom.”

8 Then all the wise men of the king came in, but they were not able to read the writing or to make known the interpretation to the king. 9 So King Bel·shaz′zar was very frightened and his face turned pale; and his nobles were perplexed.

10 Because of the words of the king and his nobles, the queen entered the banqueting hall. The queen said: “O king, may you live on forever. Do not let your thoughts terrify you, nor let your face turn pale. 11 There is a man[*] in your kingdom who has the spirit of holy gods. In the days of your father, enlightenment and insight and wisdom like the wisdom of gods were found in him. King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar your father appointed him as chief of the magic-practicing priests, conjurers, Chal·de′ans,[*] and astrologers; your father did this, O king. 12 For Daniel, whom the king named Bel·te·shaz′zar, had an extraordinary spirit and knowledge and insight to interpret dreams, to explain riddles, and to solve knotty problems.[*] Now let Daniel be summoned, and he will tell you the interpretation.”

13 So Daniel was brought in before the king. The king asked Daniel: “Are you Daniel of the exiles of Judah, whom my father the king brought out of Judah? 14 I have heard concerning you that the spirit of gods is in you and that enlightenment and insight and extraordinary wisdom have been found in you. 15 Now the wise men and the conjurers were brought in before me to read this writing and to make its interpretation known to me, but they are not able to tell the interpretation of the message. 16 But I have heard concerning you that you are able to provide interpretations and to solve knotty problems.[*] Now if you are able to read the writing and to make its interpretation known to me, you will be clothed with purple, a gold necklace will be placed around your neck, and you will rule as the third one in the kingdom.”

17 Daniel then replied to the king: “You may keep your gifts and give your presents to others. However, I will read the writing to the king and make known its interpretation to him. 18 As for you, O king, the Most High God granted to Neb·u·chad·nez′zar your father the kingdom and greatness and honor and majesty. 19 Because of the greatness He gave him, all peoples, nations, and language groups trembled with fear before him. Whomever he wanted, he killed or let live, and whomever he wanted, he exalted or humiliated. 20 But when his heart became haughty and his spirit became hardened, so that he acted presumptuously, he was brought down from the throne of his kingdom, and his dignity was taken away from him. 21 He was driven away from mankind, and his heart was made like that of a beast, and his dwelling was with the wild donkeys. He was given vegetation to eat just like bulls, and his body became wet with the dew of the heavens, until he came to know that the Most High God is Ruler in the kingdom of mankind and that he sets up over it whomever he wants.

22 “But you, his son Bel·shaz′zar, have not humbled your heart, although you knew all of this. 23 Instead, you exalted yourself against the Lord of the heavens, and you had them bring you the vessels of his house. Then you and your nobles, your concubines and your secondary wives drank wine from them and praised gods of silver and gold, of copper, iron, wood, and stone, gods that see nothing and hear nothing and know nothing. But you have not glorified the God in whose hand is your breath and all your ways. 24 So the hand was sent from him, and this writing was inscribed. 25 And this is the writing that was inscribed: ME′NE, ME′NE, TE′KEL, and PAR′SIN.

26 “This is the interpretation of the words: ME′NE, God has numbered the days of your kingdom and brought it to an end.

27 “TE′KEL, you have been weighed in the balances and found lacking.

28 “PE′RES, your kingdom has been divided and given to the Medes and the Persians.”

29 Then Bel·shaz′zar gave the command, and they clothed Daniel with purple and placed a gold necklace around his neck; and they heralded concerning him that he was to become the third ruler in the kingdom.

30 That very night Bel·shaz′zar the Chal·de′an king was killed. 31 And Da·ri′us the Mede received the kingdom; he was about 62 years old.

^ Dan. 5:6 Or “the king’s appearance changed.”

^ Dan. 5:7 That is, a group skilled in divination and astrology.

^ Dan. 5:11 Or “a capable man.”

^ Dan. 5:11 That is, a group skilled in divination and astrology.

^ Dan. 5:12 Lit., “to untie knots.”

^ Dan. 5:16 Lit., “to untie knots.”

Amos  1 : 1 - 15

AMOS

1 The words of A′mos,[*] who was among the sheep raisers from Te·ko′a, which he received in vision concerning Israel in the days of King Uz·zi′ah of Judah and in the days of Jer·o·bo′am son of Jo′ash, the king of Israel, two years before the earthquake. 2 He said:

“Jehovah will roar out of Zion,

And he will raise his voice out of Jerusalem.

The pastures of the shepherds will mourn,

And the summit of Car′mel will dry up.”

 3 “This is what Jehovah says,

‘“For three revolts[*] of Damascus, and for four, I will not reverse it,

Because they threshed Gil′e·ad with iron threshing sledges.

 4 So I will send a fire upon the house of Haz′a·el,

And it will consume the fortified towers of Ben-ha′dad.

 5 I will break the bars of Damascus;

I will destroy the inhabitants from Bik′ath-a′ven

And the one ruling[*] from Beth-e′den;

And the people of Syria will go as exiles to Kir,” says Jehovah.’

 6 This is what Jehovah says,

‘“For three revolts of Gaz′a, and for four, I will not reverse it,

Because they took a whole group of exiles to hand them over to E′dom.

 7 So I will send a fire onto the wall of Gaz′a,

And it will consume her fortified towers.

 8 I will destroy the inhabitants from Ash′dod,

And the one ruling[*] from Ash′ke·lon;

I will turn my hand against Ek′ron,

And the remaining Phi·lis′tines will perish,” says the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’

 9 This is what Jehovah says,

‘For three revolts of Tyre, and for four, I will not reverse it,

Because they handed over a whole group of exiles to E′dom,

And because they did not remember the covenant of brothers.

10 So I will send a fire onto the wall of Tyre,

And it will consume her fortified towers.’

11 This is what Jehovah says,

‘For three revolts of E′dom, and for four, I will not reverse it,

Because he pursued his own brother with the sword,

And because he refused to show mercy;

In his anger he keeps tearing them apart relentlessly,

And he remains furious with them continually.

12 So I will send a fire into Te′man,

And it will consume the fortified towers of Boz′rah.’

13 This is what Jehovah says,

‘“For three revolts of the Am′mon·ites, and for four, I will not reverse it,

Because they ripped open the pregnant women of Gil′e·ad to widen out their own territory.

14 So I will set fire to the wall of Rab′bah,

And it will consume her fortified towers,

With a war cry in the day of battle,

With a tempest in the day of storm wind.

15 And their king will go into exile together with his princes,” says Jehovah.’

^ Amos 1:1 Meaning “Being a Load” or “Carrying a Load.”

^ Amos 1:3 Or “crimes.”

^ Amos 1:5 Lit., “the one holding the scepter.”

^ Amos 1:8 Lit., “the one holding the scepter.”

Amos  4 : 1 - 13

4 “Hear this word, you cows of Ba′shan,

Who are on the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a,

You women who are defrauding the lowly and crushing the poor,

Who say to their husbands,[*] ‘Bring us something to drink!’

 2 The Sovereign Lord Jehovah has sworn by his holiness,

‘“Look! The days are coming upon you when he will lift you up with butcher hooks

And the rest of you with fishhooks.

 3 You will go out through the breaches in the wall, each one straight ahead;

And you will be cast out to Har′mon,” declares Jehovah.’

 4 ‘Come to Beth′el and commit transgression,[*]

To Gil′gal and transgress even more!

Bring your sacrifices in the morning,

And your tithes[*] on the third day.

 5 Burn a thanksgiving sacrifice of leavened bread;

Loudly proclaim your voluntary offerings!

For that is what you love to do, O people of Israel,’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

 6 ‘And for my part, I made your teeth clean of food[*] in all your cities

And caused a lack of bread in all your houses;

But you did not come back to me,’ declares Jehovah.

 7 ‘I also withheld rain from you three months before the harvest;

I made it rain on one city but not on another city.

One plot of land would have rain,

But another plot of land where there was no rain would dry up.

 8 People of two or three cities staggered to one city to drink water,

And they would not get satisfied;

But you did not come back to me,’ declares Jehovah.

 9 ‘I struck you with scorching heat and mildew.

You multiplied your gardens and vineyards,

But the locust would devour your fig trees and olive trees;

And you still did not come back to me,’ declares Jehovah.

10 ‘I sent among you a pestilence like that of Egypt.

With the sword I killed your young men and captured your horses.

I made the stench of your camps rise up into your nostrils;

But you did not come back to me,’ declares Jehovah.

11 ‘I caused an overthrow among you

Like God’s overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah.

And you were like a log snatched out of the fire;

But you did not come back to me,’ declares Jehovah.

12 So that is what I will do to you, O Israel.

Because this is what I will do to you,

Get ready to meet your God, O Israel.

13 For look! he is the One who formed the mountains and created the wind;

He tells man what His thoughts are,

He turns the dawn into darkness,

And he treads on earth’s high places;

Jehovah the God of armies is his name.”

^ Amos 4:1 Or “masters.”

^ Amos 4:4 Or “rebel.”

^ Amos 4:4 Or “tenth parts.”

^ Amos 4:6 Or “gave you no food to eat.”

Amos  9 : 1 - 15

9 I saw Jehovah stationed above the altar, and he said: “Strike the head of the pillar, and the thresholds will shake. Cut them off at the head, and I will kill the last of them with the sword. No one who flees will get away, and no one trying to escape will succeed.

 2 If they dig down into the Grave,[*]

From there my hand will take them;

And if they go up to the heavens,

From there I will bring them down.

 3 And if they hide themselves on the top of Car′mel,

From there I will search them out and take them.

If they conceal themselves from my eyes on the bottom of the sea,

There I will command the serpent to bite them.

 4 If they go into captivity before their enemies,

From there I will command the sword, and it will kill them;

I will fix my eyes on them for bad, and not for good.

 5 For the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of the armies, is the One who touches the land,[*]

So that it melts, and all its inhabitants will mourn;

And all of it will rise like the Nile,

And sink down like the Nile of Egypt.

 6 ‘The one who builds his stairs in the heavens

And establishes his structure[*] over the earth;

The one who summons the waters of the sea,

To pour them out on the surface of the earth

—Jehovah is his name.’

 7 ‘Are you not like the sons of the Cush′ites to me, O people of Israel?’ declares Jehovah.

‘Did I not bring Israel up out of the land of Egypt,

The Phi·lis′tines out of Crete, and Syria out of Kir?’

 8 ‘Look! The eyes of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah are on the sinful kingdom,

And he will annihilate it from the surface of the land.

But I will not completely annihilate the house of Jacob,’ declares Jehovah.

 9 ‘For look! I am giving the command,

And I will shake the house of Israel among all the nations,

Just as one shakes a sieve,

And not a pebble falls to the ground.

10 They will die by the sword, all the sinners of my people,

Those who are saying, “The calamity will not come near us or reach us.”’

11 ‘In that day I will raise up the booth[*] of David that is fallen,

I will repair the[*] breaches,

And I will restore its ruins;

I will rebuild it as in the days of long ago,

12 So that they may take possession of what is remaining of E′dom,

And all the nations on whom my name has been called,’ declares Jehovah, who is doing this.

13 ‘Look! The days are coming,’ declares Jehovah,

‘When the plowman will overtake the harvester,

And the treader of grapes, the one carrying seed;

And the mountains will drip with sweet wine,

And all the hills will flow with it.[*]

14 I will gather back the captives of my people Israel,

And they will rebuild the desolated cities and inhabit them;

They will plant vineyards and drink their wine,

And make gardens and eat their fruit.’

15 ‘I will plant them on their land,

And they will never again be uprooted

From their land that I have given them,’ says Jehovah your God.”

^ Amos 9:2 Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ Amos 9:5 Or “earth.”

^ Amos 9:6 Or “dome; vault.”

^ Amos 9:11 Or “tent; hut.”

^ Amos 9:11 Or “their.”

^ Amos 9:13 Lit., “will melt.”

Obadiah 1 - 21

OBADIAH

1 The vision of O·ba·di′ah:[*]

This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says regarding E′dom:

“We have heard a report from Jehovah,

An envoy has been sent among the nations:

‘Rise up, let us prepare for battle against her.’”

 2 “Look! I have made you insignificant among the nations;

You are utterly despised.

 3 The presumptuousness of your heart has deceived you,

You who reside in the retreats of the crag,

Dwelling in the height, saying in your heart,

‘Who will bring me down to the earth?’

 4 Even if you make your dwelling high[*] like the eagle,

Or if you place your nest among the stars,

I would bring you down from there,” declares Jehovah.

 5 “If thieves would come to you, robbers by night,

(How utterly you will be destroyed!)[*]

Would they not steal only what they wanted?

Or if it were grape gatherers who would come to you,

Would they not leave some gleanings behind?

 6 O how E′sau has been searched out!

How his hidden treasures have been sought after!

 7 They have driven you to the border.

All your allies[*] have deceived you.

The men at peace with you have prevailed against you.

Those eating bread with you will place a net under you,

But you will not discern it.

 8 In that day,” declares Jehovah,

“Will I not destroy the wise ones out of E′dom

And discernment out of the mountainous region of E′sau?

 9 And your warriors will become terrified, O Te′man,

Because each one in the mountainous region of E′sau will be destroyed in the slaughter.

10 Because of the violence done to your brother Jacob,

Shame will cover you,

And you will perish forever.

11 On the day when you stood off to the side,

On the day when strangers took his army into captivity,

When foreigners entered his gate and cast lots over Jerusalem,

You acted like one of them.

12 You should not gloat over your brother’s day on the day of his misfortune,

You should not rejoice over the people of Judah on the day of their perishing,

And you should not speak so arrogantly on the day of their distress.

13 You should not come into the gate of my people in the day of their disaster,

You should not gloat over his calamity in the day of his disaster,

And you should not lay your hands on his wealth in the day of his disaster.

14 You should not stand at the crossroads to slaughter his escapees,

And you should not hand over his survivors in the day of distress.

15 For the day of Jehovah against all the nations is near.

As you have done, so it will be done to you.

The way you treated others will come back on your own head.

16 For in the way that you have drunk on my holy mountain,

All the nations will keep drinking constantly.

They will drink and gulp down,

And they will be as though they had never existed.

17 But on Mount Zion will be those who escape,

And it will be holy;

And the house of Jacob will take possession of the things belonging to them.

18 The house of Jacob will become a fire,

The house of Joseph a flame,

And the house of E′sau like stubble;

They will set them ablaze and consume them,

And there will be no survivor of the house of E′sau,

For Jehovah himself has spoken.

19 They will take possession of the Neg′eb and the mountainous region of E′sau,

Of the She·phe′lah and the land of the Phi·lis′tines.

They will take possession of the field of E′phra·im and the field of Sa·mar′i·a,

And Benjamin will take possession of Gil′e·ad.

20 To the exiles of this rampart,[*]

To the people of Israel will belong the land of the Ca′naan·ites as far as Zar′e·phath.

And the exiles of Jerusalem, who were in Se·phar′ad, will possess the cities of the Neg′eb.

21 And saviors will go up on Mount Zion

To judge the mountainous region of E′sau,

And the kingship will become Jehovah’s.”

^ Obad. 1 Meaning “Servant of Jehovah.”

^ Obad. 4 Or possibly, “you fly high.”

^ Obad. 5 Or possibly, “How much would they destroy?”

^ Obad. 7 Or “those in covenant with you.”

^ Obad. 20 Or “fortification.”

Jonah  3 : 1 - 10

3 Then the word of Jehovah came to Jo′nah a second time, saying: 2 “Get up, go to Nin′e·veh the great city, and proclaim to her the message that I tell you.”

3 So Jo′nah got up and went to Nin′e·veh in obedience to the word of Jehovah. Now Nin′e·veh was a very large city[*]—a walking distance of three days. 4 Then Jo′nah entered the city, and walking a day’s journey, he was proclaiming: “In just 40 days more, Nin′e·veh will be overthrown.”

5 And the men of Nin′e·veh put faith in God, and they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth, from the greatest to the least of them. 6 When the message reached the king of Nin′e·veh, he rose up from his throne and took off his royal garment and covered himself with sackcloth and sat down in the ashes. 7 Furthermore, he issued a proclamation throughout Nin′e·veh,

“By the decree of the king and his nobles: No man or beast, herd or flock, should eat anything at all. They should not take food, nor should they drink any water. 8 Let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and beast; and let them call out earnestly to God and turn from their evil ways and from the violence they practice. 9 Who knows whether the true God may reconsider[*] what he intends to do and turn from his burning anger, so that we may not perish?”

10 When the true God saw what they did, how they had turned back from their evil ways, he reconsidered[*] the calamity that he said he would bring on them, and he did not bring it.

^ Jonah 3:3 Lit., “a city great to God.”

^ Jonah 3:9 Or “feel regret over.”

^ Jonah 3:10 Or “felt regret over.”

Nahum  3 : 1 - 19

3 Woe to the city of bloodshed!

She is completely full of deception and robbery.

She is never without prey!

 2 There is the crack of the whip and the rattle of wheels,

The dashing horse and the bounding chariot.

 3 The mounted horseman, the flashing sword, and the glittering spear,

The multitude of the slain and the heaps of carcasses

—There is no end to the dead bodies.

They keep stumbling over the dead bodies.

 4 This is because of the many acts of prostitution of the prostitute,

She who is attractive and charming, a mistress of sorceries,

Who ensnares nations by her prostitution and families by her sorceries.

 5 “Look! I am against you,”[*] declares Jehovah of armies,

“I will lift your skirts up over your face;

I will cause nations to see your nakedness,

And kingdoms your disgrace.

 6 And I will throw filth on you

And make you despicable;

I will make a spectacle of you.

 7 Everyone who sees you will flee from you and say,

‘Nin′e·veh has been devastated!

Who will sympathize with her?’

Where will I find comforters for you?

 8 Are you better than No-a′mon,[*] which sat by the Nile canals?

Waters surrounded her;

Her wealth was the sea and her wall was the sea.

 9 E·thi·o′pi·a was her source of boundless strength, also Egypt.

Put and the Lib′y·ans were your helpers.

10 But even she became an exile;

She went into captivity.

Her children also were dashed to pieces on every street corner.[*]

They cast lots over her honored men,

And all her great men have been bound with fetters.

11 You will also become drunk;

You will go into hiding.

You will seek refuge from the enemy.

12 All your fortifications are like fig trees with the first ripe fruits;

If they are shaken, they will fall into the mouth of devourers.

13 Look! Your troops are like women in your midst.

The gates of your land will be wide open for your enemies.

Fire will consume the bars of your gates.

14 Draw water for the siege!

Strengthen your fortifications.

Go down into the mire and tread the clay;

Grab hold of the brick mold.

15 Even there fire will consume you.

A sword will cut you down.

It will devour you as the young locusts do.

Make yourself as numerous as the young locusts!

Yes, make yourself as numerous as the locusts!

16 You have multiplied your merchants more than the stars of the heavens.

The young locust strips off its skin and flies away.

17 Your guards are like the locust,

And your officers like a locust swarm.

They camp in the stone pens on a cold day,

But when the sun shines, they fly away;

And no one knows where they are.

18 Your shepherds are drowsy, O king of As·syr′i·a;

Your nobles stay in their residences.

Your people are scattered on the mountains,

And no one is gathering them together.

19 There is no relief for your catastrophe.

Your wound is beyond healing.

All those hearing the report about you will clap their hands;

For who has not suffered from your relentless cruelty?”

^ Nah. 3:5 That is, Nineveh.

^ Nah. 3:8 That is, Thebes.

^ Nah. 3:10 Lit., “at the head of all streets.”

Zechariah  5 : 1 - 11

5 Again I looked up, and I saw a flying scroll. 2 He asked me: “What do you see?”

I replied: “I see a flying scroll, which is 20 cubits[*] long and 10 cubits wide.”

3 Then he said to me: “This is the curse that is going out over the face of all the earth, because everyone who steals, as written on its one side, has gone unpunished; and everyone who makes a sworn oath, as written on its other side, has gone unpunished. 4 ‘I have sent it out,’ declares Jehovah of armies, ‘and it will enter into the house of the thief and into the house of the one who makes a false oath in my name; and it will remain inside that house and consume it and its timbers and its stones.’”

5 Then the angel who was speaking with me came forward and said to me: “Look up, please, and see what is going out.”

6 So I asked: “What is it?”

He replied: “This is the e′phah container[*] that is going out.” He continued: “This is their appearance in all the earth.” 7 And I saw that the round lid of lead was lifted up, and there was a woman sitting inside the container. 8 So he said: “This is Wickedness.” Then he threw her back into the e′phah container, after which he thrust the lead weight over its mouth.

9 Then I looked up and saw two women coming forward, and they were soaring in the wind. They had wings like the wings of a stork. And they lifted up the container between the earth and heaven. 10 So I asked the angel who was speaking with me: “Where are they taking the e′phah container?”

11 He replied: “To the land of Shi′nar[*] to build her a house; and when it is prepared, she will be deposited there in her proper place.”

^ Zech. 5:2 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ Zech. 5:6 Lit., “the ephah,” here referring to a container or basket used to measure an ephah. An ephah equaled 22 L (20 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ Zech. 5:11 That is, Babylonia.

Zechariah  11 : 1 - 17

11 “Open your doors, O Leb′a·non,

So that a fire may consume your cedars.

 2 Wail, you juniper, for the cedar has fallen;

The majestic trees have been destroyed!

Wail, you oaks of Ba′shan,

For the dense forest has come down!

 3 Listen! The wailing of shepherds,

For their majesty has been devastated.

Listen! The roaring of young lions,[*]

For the dense thickets along the Jordan have been destroyed.

4 “This is what Jehovah my God says, ‘Shepherd the flock meant for the slaughter, 5 whose buyers slaughtered them and are not held guilty. And those who sell them say, “May Jehovah be praised, for I will become rich.” And their shepherds have no compassion for them.’

6 “‘For I will no longer show compassion on the inhabitants of the land,’ declares Jehovah. ‘So I will cause each man to fall into the hand of his neighbor and his king; and they will crush the land, and I will not rescue them out of their hand.’”

7 And I began to shepherd the flock meant for slaughter, in your behalf, O afflicted ones of the flock. So I took two staffs, and I called one Pleasantness, and the other Union, and I began to shepherd the flock. 8 And I dismissed three shepherds in one month, for I[*] became impatient with them, and they[*] detested me as well. 9 And I said: “I will not keep shepherding you. Let the one who is dying die, and let the one perishing perish. As for those who are left, let them devour one another’s flesh.” 10 So I took my staff Pleasantness and cut it up, breaking my covenant that I had made with all the peoples. 11 So it was broken in that day, and the afflicted ones of the flock who were watching me knew that it was the word of Jehovah.

12 Then I said to them: “If it seems good to you, give me my wages; but if not, withhold them.” And they paid[*] my wages, 30 pieces of silver.

13 Then Jehovah said to me: “Throw it into the treasury—the magnificent value with which they valued me.” So I took the 30 pieces of silver and threw it into the treasury at the house of Jehovah.

14 Then I cut up my second staff, the Union, breaking the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 And Jehovah said to me: “Now take the equipment of a useless shepherd. 16 For I am letting a shepherd rise up in the land. He will not take care of the sheep that are perishing; he will not seek out the young or heal the injured or feed those able to stand. Instead, he devours the flesh of the fat one and tears off the hooves of the sheep.

17 Woe to my worthless shepherd, who is abandoning the flock!

A sword will strike his arm and his right eye.

His arm will wither completely,

And his right eye will go completely blind.”[*]

^ Zech. 11:3 Or “maned young lions.”

^ Zech. 11:8 Or “my soul.”

^ Zech. 11:8 Or “their soul.”

^ Zech. 11:12 Lit., “weighed out.”

^ Zech. 11:17 Lit., “dim.”

Matthew  24 : 1 - 51

24 Now as Jesus was departing from the temple, his disciples approached to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 In response he said to them: “Do you not see all these things? Truly I say to you, by no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.”

3 While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence[*] and of the conclusion of the system of things?”[*]

4 In answer Jesus said to them: “Look out that nobody misleads you, 5 for many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am the Christ,’ and will mislead many. 6 You are going to hear of wars and reports of wars. See that you are not alarmed, for these things must take place, but the end is not yet.

7 “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, and there will be food shortages and earthquakes in one place after another. 8 All these things are a beginning of pangs of distress.

9 “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name. 10 Then, too, many will be stumbled and will betray one another and will hate one another. 11 Many false prophets will arise and mislead many; 12 and because of the increasing of lawlessness, the love of the greater number will grow cold. 13 But the one who has endured[*] to the end will be saved. 14 And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

15 “Therefore, when you catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation, as spoken about by Daniel the prophet, standing in a holy place (let the reader use discernment), 16 then let those in Ju·de′a begin fleeing to the mountains. 17 Let the man on the housetop not come down to take the goods out of his house, 18 and let the man in the field not return to pick up his outer garment. 19 Woe to the pregnant women and those nursing a baby in those days! 20 Keep praying that your flight may not occur in wintertime nor on the Sabbath day; 21 for then there will be great tribulation such as has not occurred since the world’s beginning until now, no, nor will occur again. 22 In fact, unless those days were cut short, no flesh would be saved; but on account of the chosen ones those days will be cut short.

23 “Then if anyone says to you, ‘Look! Here is the Christ,’ or, ‘There!’ do not believe it. 24 For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will perform great signs and wonders so as to mislead, if possible, even the chosen ones. 25 Look! I have forewarned you. 26 Therefore, if people say to you, ‘Look! He is in the wilderness,’ do not go out; ‘Look! He is in the inner rooms,’ do not believe it. 27 For just as the lightning comes out of the east and shines over to the west, so the presence[*] of the Son of man will be. 28 Wherever the carcass is, there the eagles will be gathered together.

29 “Immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, and the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken. 30 Then the sign of the Son of man will appear in heaven, and all the tribes of the earth will beat themselves in grief, and they will see the Son of man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

32 “Now learn this illustration from the fig tree: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and sprouts its leaves, you know that summer is near. 33 Likewise also you, when you see all these things, know that he is near at the doors. 34 Truly I say to you that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen. 35 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will by no means pass away.

36 “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father. 37 For just as the days of Noah were, so the presence[*] of the Son of man will be. 38 For as they were in those days before the Flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, 39 and they took no note until the Flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be. 40 Then two men will be in the field; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 41 Two women will be grinding at the hand mill; one will be taken along and the other abandoned. 42 Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming.

43 “But know one thing: If the householder had known in what watch[*] the thief was coming, he would have kept awake and not allowed his house to be broken into. 44 On this account, you too prove yourselves ready, because the Son of man is coming at an hour that you do not think to be it.

45 “Who really is the faithful and discreet[*] slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

48 “But if ever that evil slave says in his heart, ‘My master is delaying,’ 49 and he starts to beat his fellow slaves and to eat and drink with the confirmed drunkards, 50 the master of that slave will come on a day that he does not expect and in an hour that he does not know, 51 and he will punish him with the greatest severity and will assign him his place with the hypocrites. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.

^ Matt. 24:3 See Glossary.

^ Matt. 24:3 Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ Matt. 24:13 Or “who endures.”

^ Matt. 24:27 See Glossary.

^ Matt. 24:37 See Glossary.

^ Matt. 24:43 Or “at what time of night.”

^ Matt. 24:45 Or “wise.”

Romans  16 : 1 - 27

16 I am introducing[*] to you Phoe′be, our sister, who is a minister of the congregation that is in Cen′chre·ae, 2 so that you may welcome her in the Lord in a way worthy of the holy ones and give her whatever help she may need, for she herself also proved to be a defender of many, including me.

3 Give my greetings to Pris′ca and Aq′ui·la, my fellow workers in Christ Jesus, 4 who have risked their own necks for me[*] and to whom not only I but also all the congregations of the nations give thanks. 5 Also greet the congregation that is in their house. Greet my beloved E·pae′ne·tus, who is a firstfruits of Asia for Christ. 6 Greet Mary, who has worked hard for you. 7 Greet An·dron′i·cus and Ju′ni·as, my relatives and fellow prisoners, who are men well-known to the apostles and who have been in union with Christ longer than I have.

8 Give my greetings to Am·pli·a′tus, my beloved in the Lord. 9 Greet Ur·ba′nus, our fellow worker in Christ, and my beloved Sta′chys. 10 Greet A·pel′les, the approved one in Christ. Greet those from the household of A·ris·tob′u·lus. 11 Greet He·ro′di·on, my relative. Greet those from the household of Nar·cis′sus who are in the Lord. 12 Greet Try·phae′na and Try·pho′sa, women who are working hard in the Lord. Greet Per′sis, our beloved one, for she has worked hard in the Lord. 13 Greet Ru′fus, the chosen one in the Lord, and his mother and mine. 14 Greet A·syn′cri·tus, Phle′gon, Her′mes, Pat′ro·bas, Her′mas, and the brothers with them. 15 Greet Phi·lol′o·gus and Julia, Ne′reus and his sister, and O·lym′pas, and all the holy ones with them. 16 Greet one another with a holy kiss. All the congregations of the Christ greet you.

17 Now I urge you, brothers, to keep your eye on those who create divisions and causes for stumbling contrary to the teaching that you have learned, and avoid them. 18 For men of that sort are slaves, not of our Lord Christ, but of their own appetites,[*] and by smooth talk and flattering speech they seduce the hearts of unsuspecting ones. 19 Your obedience has come to the notice of all, and so I rejoice over you. But I want you to be wise as to what is good, but innocent as to what is evil. 20 For his part, the God who gives peace will crush Satan under your feet shortly. May the undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus be with you.

21 Timothy, my fellow worker, greets you, and so do Lucius, Ja′son, and So·sip′a·ter, my relatives.

22 I, Ter′tius, who have done the writing of this letter, greet you in the Lord.

23 Ga′ius, host to me and to all the congregation, greets you. E·ras′tus, the city treasurer,[*] greets you, and so does Quar′tus, his brother. ^24[*] ——

25 Now to Him who can make you firm according to the good news I declare and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the sacred secret that has been kept in silence for long-lasting times 26 but has now been made manifest[*] and has been made known through the prophetic Scriptures among all the nations according to the command of the everlasting God to promote obedience by faith; 27 to God, who alone is wise, be the glory through Jesus Christ forever. Amen.

^ Rom. 16:1 Or “I recommend.”

^ Rom. 16:4 Or “my soul.”

^ Rom. 16:18 Or “bellies.”

^ Rom. 16:23 Or “steward.”

^ Rom. 16:24 See App. A3.

^ Rom. 16:26 Or “revealed.”

1 Corinthians  1 : 1 - 31

THE FIRST TO THE CORINTHIANS

1 Paul, called to be an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will, and Sos′the·nes our brother, 2 to the congregation of God that is in Corinth, to you who have been sanctified in union with Christ Jesus, called to be holy ones, together with all those everywhere who are calling on the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, their Lord and ours:

3 May you have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

4 I always thank my God for you in view of the undeserved kindness of God given to you in Christ Jesus; 5 because in everything you have been enriched in him, in full ability to speak and in full knowledge, 6 just as the witness about the Christ has been made firm among you, 7 so that you do not lack in any gift at all, while you are eagerly waiting for the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ. 8 He will also make you firm to the end so that you may be open to no accusation in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9 God is faithful, by whom you were called into fellowship[*] with his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.

10 Now I urge you, brothers, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that you should all speak in agreement and that there should be no divisions among you, but that you may be completely united in the same mind and in the same line of thought. 11 For some from the house of Chlo′e have informed me regarding you, my brothers, that there are dissensions among you. 12 What I mean is this, that each one of you says: “I belong to Paul,” “But I to A·pol′los,” “But I to Ce′phas,”[*] “But I to Christ.” 13 Is the Christ divided? Paul was not executed on the stake for you, was he? Or were you baptized in the name of Paul? 14 I thank God that I baptized none of you except Cris′pus and Ga′ius, 15 so that no one may say that you were baptized in my name. 16 Yes, I also baptized the household of Steph′a·nas. As for the rest, I do not know whether I baptized anyone else. 17 For Christ sent me, not to baptize, but to declare the good news; and not with wisdom of speech,[*] so that the torture stake[*] of the Christ should not be made useless.

18 For the speech about the torture stake[*] is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved, it is God’s power. 19 For it is written: “I will make the wisdom of the wise men perish, and the intelligence of the intellectuals I will reject.”[*] 20 Where is the wise man? Where is the scribe?[*] Where is the debater of this system of things?[*] Has not God made the wisdom of the world foolish? 21 For since, in the wisdom of God, the world did not get to know God through its wisdom, God was pleased through the foolishness of what is preached to save those believing.

22 For the Jews ask for signs and the Greeks look for wisdom; 23 but we preach Christ executed on the stake, to the Jews a cause for stumbling but to the nations foolishness. 24 However, to those who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God. 25 Because a foolish thing of God is wiser than men, and a weak thing of God is stronger than men.

26 For you see his calling of you, brothers, that there are not many wise in a fleshly way,[*] not many powerful, not many of noble birth,[*] 27 but God chose the foolish things of the world to put the wise men to shame; and God chose the weak things of the world to put the strong things to shame; 28 and God chose the insignificant things of the world and the things looked down on, the things that are not, to bring to nothing the things that are, 29 so that no one[*] might boast in the sight of God. 30 But it is due to him that you are in union with Christ Jesus, who has become to us wisdom from God, also righteousness and sanctification and release by ransom, 31 so that it may be just as it is written: “The one who boasts, let him boast in Jehovah.”[*]

^ 1 Cor. 1:9 Or “a sharing.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:12 Also called Peter.

^ 1 Cor. 1:17 Or “clever speech.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:17 See Glossary.

^ 1 Cor. 1:18 See Glossary.

^ 1 Cor. 1:19 Or “shove aside.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:20 That is, an expert in the Law.

^ 1 Cor. 1:20 Or “this age.” See Glossary.

^ 1 Cor. 1:26 Or “by human standards.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:26 Or “from important families.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:29 Lit., “flesh.”

^ 1 Cor. 1:31 See App. A5.